<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../finkfaq.dtd">
<document filename="index" lang="en">
  <title>The Fink F.A.Q.</title>
  <shorttitle>F.A.Q.</shorttitle>
  <cvsid>$Id: faq.en.xml,v 1.69 2006/06/09 14:57:47 dmrrsn Exp $</cvsid>
  <preface>
    <p>This is the list of frequently asked questions about Fink. Like in most FAQs, some questions are taken from real life and some are made up. It's really more like a documentation written in an ad-hoc, question and answer style.</p>
    <p>The FAQ consists of several pages, one for each section. All questions are listed and linked in the table of contents below.</p>
  </preface>
  <chapter filename="general">
    <title>General Questions</title>
    <shorttitle>General</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="what">
      <question>
        <p>What is Fink?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Fink wants to bring more Unix software to Mac OS X, which results in two main goals:</p>
        <p>Goal number one is porting software to Mac OS X. That means we take commodity Open Source Unix software and fix whatever is necessary so that it will compile and run on Mac OS X. Sometimes that's easy, but it can also be very hard or even impossible for some packages. We're trying to provide tools and documentation to make this easier.</p>
        <p>Goal number two is making the results available to casual users.  For this, we build a distribution using package management tools ported over from Linux, namely <code>dpkg</code> and <code>apt-get</code>, written by and for the  <link url="http://www.debian.org/">Debian GNU/Linux</link> project. The binary distribution uses the <code>.deb</code> package format. For building packages from source, we have our own tool, named <code>fink</code>, which creates those <code>.deb</code> package files.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="naming">
      <question>
        <p>What does the name Fink stand for?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>	Nothing, it's just a name. It's not even an acronym.</p>
        <p>	Well, actually Fink is the German name for Finch, a kind of bird. I was looking for a name for the project, and the name of the OS, Darwin, led me to think about Charles Darwin, the Galapagos Islands and evolution. I remembered a piece about the so-called Darwin Finches and their beaks from school, and well, that's it...</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="bsd-ports">
      <question>
        <p>	How is Fink different from the BSD port mechanism (this includes OpenPackages and GNU-Darwin)?
		</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>	Some main advantages:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p> It's written in Perl, not make/shell. Thus it  doesn't rely on special features only found in BSD make. There is no need to flag packages that need GNU make to build.</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p> dpkg provides sophisticated management for binary packages - smooth updating, special handling for configuration files, virtual packages and other advanced dependencies. </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p> Fink doesn't install into /usr/local unless explicitly requested and doesn't require fiddling with /usr/bin/make or other system-provided commands. That makes it safer to use and reduces interference with Mac OS X and third-party packages to a minimum.</p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="usr-local">
      <question>
        <p>Why doesn't Fink install into /usr/local?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>	There are several reasons, but the common line is "because breakage will occur".</p>
        <p>	Reason One: Third-party software. /usr/local is the well-established place to put software that is not part of the system shipped by the original vendor. This means that it is a good place to put stuff. However, it also means that other people will put stuff there, too. Most install routines will just overwrite what's there - this also applies to dpkg. One can, of course, choose not to install third-party software in /usr/local. Unfortunately, most installers don't tell you beforehand what they will install where.</p>
        <p>	Reason Two: /usr/local/bin is in the default PATH. This means that your shell will find the installed programs without additional measures. But it also means that you do have to take additional measures if you do not want to use the programs. In extreme cases, this can also affect the system itself - many parts depend on shell scripts.</p>
        <p>	Reason Three: The compiler tool chain searches /usr/local by default. The compiler searches /usr/local/include for header files and the linker searches /usr/local/lib for libraries. Again, this is sometimes a welcome convenience, but it's very hard to disable should the need arise. You can easily disable the compiler by putting a garbage file called <code>stdio.h</code> into /usr/local/include.</p>
        <p>	All that said, it is possible to install Fink into /usr/local. The installation script will warn you explicitly, but proceed once you acknowledge that you're doing this at your own risk.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="why-sw">
      <question>
        <p>Then why did you choose /sw?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p> That choice is quite arbitrary, but is likely to stay for the foreseeable future for practical (upgrade) issues as well as the fact that it's safe from conflicting with other packaging systems.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="relations">
    <title>Relations with Other Projects</title>
    <shorttitle>Relations</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="upstream">
      <question>
        <p>Do you contribute your patches back to the upstream maintainers?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>We're trying to. Sometimes sending patches back is easy and  everyone is happy once the next release of the package is out. Unfortunately with most packages it's not that easy. Some common problems:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The Fink package maintainer is very busy and doesn't have the time to send the patch and accompanying explanations to the upstream
          maintainers.</li>
          <li>The upstream maintainers reject the patch. There are lots of valid reasons for this. Most upstream maintainers have a strong interest in clean code, clean configure checks, and compatibility with other platforms.</li>
          <li>The upstream maintainers accept the patch, but it takes some weeks or months until they release a new version of their package.</li>
          <li>The package has been abandoned by the original authors and there will be no new releases into which the patch could be merged.</li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="debian">
      <question>
        <p>What is your relation with the Debian project? Are you porting Debian Linux to Mac OS X?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There is no formal relation between Fink and <link url="http://www.debian.org">Debian</link>. Fink is <em>not</em> a port  of the Debian GNU/Linux distribution. We have ported Debian's package management tools (dpkg, dselect, apt-get) though, and use these tools and the .deb binary package format. The actual packages are tailor-made for Mac OS X / Darwin and don't use the Debian source package  format.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple">
      <question>
        <p>What is your relation with Apple?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>
          <link url="http://www.apple.com/">Apple</link> is aware of Fink and has given us some support as part of their Open Source relations efforts. In the summer and fall of 2001, they provided us with pre-release seeds of new Mac OS X versions in the hope that Fink packages can be adapted in time for the release. Quote:  <em>"Hopefully it underscores the commitment that many suspect we're not willing to provide. We'll get better at the open source game over time."</em> Thanks Apple!</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="darwinports">
      <question>
        <p>What is your relation with Darwinports?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Darwinports and Fink are complementary projects. There is some overlap between the two projects, and several people contribute to both the Fink and DarwinPorts projects. For example, Benjamin Reed is doing the KDE packages for both. Darwinports and Fink are free to make use of each other's patches, and we have discussed collaboration on a new dependency engine.</p>
        <p>DarwinPorts started from scratch to try a different approach to a packaging system. Read the statement on <link url="http://darwinports.opendarwin.org/">the DarwinPorts homepage</link>
        for details.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="mirrors">
    <title>Fink mirrors</title>
    <shorttitle>Mirrors</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="when-use">
      <question>
        <p>What are Fink Mirrors?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Fink mirrors are rsync servers mirroring the current and stable description files that Fink uses to build packages from source.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="why">
      <question>
        <p>Why should I use rsync mirrors?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Rsync is a very fast protocol. It will update the description files faster than the old CVS update method. Furthermore, CVS updates are  always done from sourceforge.net while rsync updates can be done from a mirror close to you.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="where">
      <question>
        <p>Where can I find more information about Fink mirrors?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>All Fink mirrors are consolidated under the finkmirrors.net domain. The Web-Site at http://finkmirrors.net/ has more information.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="when-not">
      <question>
        <p>I cannot connect to rsync server, what should I do?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Sometimes very strict firewalls forbid you to connect to rsync services. If that is the case simply continue using the CVS  method</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="otherinfogone">
      <question>
        <p>I have switched to the rsync method now all info files from the unused trees are gone</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is normal. The rsync update method will only update your active tree, e.g. 10.3, and it will also delete the CVS subdirectories.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="howswitch">
      <question>
        <p>How can I switch back and forth between methods.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>By using fink selfupdate-rsync or fink selfupdate-cvs to switch to rsync or CVS, respectively.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="status">
      <question>
        <p>Can I see what the current status of rsync mirrors is?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Yes, go to http://finkmirrors.net/status.html</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="Master">
      <question>
        <p>What is a Distfiles mirror?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Sometimes it is hard to fetch a certain version of sources from the Internet. Distfile mirrors hold and mirror the source packages needed by fink to build its source packages.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="upgrade-fink">
    <title>Upgrading Fink (version-specific troubleshooting)</title>
    <shorttitle>Upgrading Fink</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="gcc-0.16.0">
      <question>
        <p>I just upgraded to 0.16.0 and it tells me "Your version of the gcc 3.3 compiler is out of date." What do I do?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>As of the release of Panther, Fink has been updated to understand the newer gcc 3.3 compiler. In order to be able to support users on both 10.2 (Jaguar) and 10.3 (Panther), we are requiring all users to install the latest gcc 3.3 update (August 2003 Updater, and the Panther XCode tools, respectively). You will get this warning if you installed the earlier XCode beta updater for Mac OS X 10.2's December 2002 developer tools. If you're on 10.2, the command:</p>
        <codeblock>gcc --version</codeblock>
        <p>should tell you what version you have. As of October 24th, 2003, we require build 1493 or higher.</p>
        <p>10.2 users can download the August 2003 Updater from <link url="http://developer.apple.com/">Apple Developer Connection</link> (free registration required).</p>
        <p>10.3 users should upgrade to a Panther-compatible developer tools release (i.e. XCode). A CD with XCode should have been provided with your Panther media.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="fink-0220">
      <question>
        <p>I haven't had any package updates from Fink in a while.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Check your version:</p>
        <codeblock>fink --version</codeblock>
        <p>There is a known problem with <code>fink-0.22.0</code> wherein rsync selfupdating stopped working.  To fix this, switch to CVS selfupdating via</p>
        <codeblock>fink selfupdate-cvs	</codeblock>
        <p>This will bring you a newer <code>fink</code> version.  After you do this we recommend switching back to rsync selfupdating:</p>
        <codeblock>fink selfupdate-rsync</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="usage-fink">
    <title>Installing, Using and Maintaining Fink</title>
    <shorttitle>Fink Usage</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="what-packages">
      <question>
        <p>How can I find out what packages Fink supports?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Since Fink 0.2.3, there is the <code>list</code> command. It produces a list of all packages known to your Fink installation. Example:</p>
        <codeblock>fink list</codeblock>
        <p>If you're using the binary distribution, <code>dselect</code> gives you a nice browsable listing of available packages. Note that you must run it as root if you want to select and install packages from within dselect.</p>
        <p>There's also the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/pdb/">package database</link> at the
        website.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="proxy">
      <question>
        <p>I'm behind a firewall. How do I configure Fink to use an HTTP proxy?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The <code>fink</code> command supports explicit proxy settings that are passed on to <code>wget</code>/<code>curl</code>. If you were not asked for proxies on first time installation, you can run <code>fink configure</code> to set it up. You can also run that command at any time to reconfigure the <code>fink</code> command. If you  followed the instructions in the installation guide, and use  <filename>/sw/bin/init.csh</filename> (or <filename>/sw/bin/init.sh</filename>), then <code>apt-get</code> and <code>dselect</code> also will use these proxy settings. Make sure that you put the protocol in front of the proxy, e.g.</p>
        <codeblock>ftp://proxy.yoursite.somewhere</codeblock>
        <p>If you are still having problems, go into System Preferences, select the Network pane, select the Proxies tab, and make sure that the box labeled "Use Passive FTP Mode (PASV)" is checked.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="firewalled-cvs">
      <question>
        <p>How do I update available packages from CVS when I am behind a firewall?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The package <em>cvs-proxy</em> can tunnel through HTTP proxies.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>First download the <link url="http://fink.cvs.sourceforge.net/fink/dists/10.2/unstable/main/finkinfo/devel/">cvs-proxy</link>
          files (an .info file and a .patch file) and place them into your
          local tree (i.e. /sw/fink/dists/local/main/finkinfo/).</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Install the <em>cvs-proxy</em> package with the command:</p>
            <p>
              <code>fink install <em>cvs-proxy</em>
              </code>
            </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Packages are then updated with the commands:</p>
            <p>
              <code>fink selfupdate-cvs</code>
            </p>
            <p>
              <code>fink
          update-all</code>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>If fink is not configured to use your proxy, change the settings
        using:</p>
        <p>
          <code>fink configure</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="moving">
      <question>
        <p>Can I move Fink to another location after installation?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>No. Well, of course you can move the files using mv or the Finder,
        but 99% of the programs will stop working when you do. That's because
        basically all Unix software depends on hardcoded paths to find data
        files, libraries and other stuff.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="moving-symlink">
      <question>
        <p>If I move Fink after installation and provide a symlink from the
        old location, will it work?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Maybe. The general expectation is that it should work, but there
        may be hidden traps somewhere.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="removing">
      <question>
        <p>How can I uninstall all of Fink?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Almost all files installed by Fink are in /sw (or wherever you
        chose to install it). Thus in order to get rid of Fink, enter this
        command:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo rm -rf /sw</codeblock>
        <p>The only exception to this rule is XFree86 or X.org. If you installed
        an X server through Fink (i.e., you installed the <code>xfree86</code>,
        <code>xfree86-rootless</code>, or <code>xorg</code> packages, instead of using
        <code>system-xfree86</code>) and want to remove it, you will need
        additionally to enter this:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo rm -rf /usr/X11R6 /etc/X11 /Applications/XDarwin.app</codeblock>
        <p>If you aren't planning to reinstall Fink you also will want to
        remove the "<code>source /sw/bin/init.csh</code>" line you added to
        your <filename>.cshrc</filename> file or the "<code>source
        /sw/bin/init.sh</code>" line you added to your
        <filename>.bashrc</filename> file, whichever is appropriate to your
        setup, using a text editor.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="bindist">
      <question>
        <p>The package database at the website lists package xxx, but apt-get
        and dselect know nothing about it. Who's lying?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Both are correct. The <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/pdb/">package database</link> knows
        about every package, including those that are still in the unstable
        section. The <code>dselect</code> and <code>apt-get</code> tools on
        the other hand only know about the packages available as precompiled
        binary packages. Many packages are not available in precompiled form
        through these tools for a variety of reasons. A package must be in the
        "stable" section of the latest point release to be considered, and it
        must pass additional checks for policy compliance as well as licensing
        and patent restrictions.</p>
        <p>If you want to install a package that is not available via
        <code>dselect</code> / <code>apt-get</code>, you have to compile it
        from source using <code>fink install <em>packagename</em>
          </code>.
        Make sure you have the Developer Tools installed before you try this.
        (If there is no installer for the Developer Tools in your
        <code>/Applications</code> folder, you can get them from the <link url="http://connect.apple.com/">Apple Developer Connection</link>
        after free registration.) See also the question about unstable
        below.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="unstable">
      <question>
        <p>There's this package in unstable that I want to install, but the
        fink command just says 'no package found'. How can I install it?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>First make sure you understand what 'unstable' means. Packages in
        the unstable tree are not in stable for any number of reasons.  It
        could be because there are known issues, validation errors, or just
        not enough people giving feedback that the package works for them.
        For that reason, Fink doesn't search the unstable tree by
        default.</p>
        <p>If you do enable unstable, please remember to e-mail the
        maintainer if something works (or even if it doesn't). Feedback from
        users like you is what we use to determine if something is ready for
        stable! To find out the maintainer of a package, run <code>fink info
        <em>packagename</em></code>.</p>
        <p>To configure Fink to use unstable, edit
        <filename>/sw/etc/fink.conf</filename>, add <code>unstable/main</code>
        and <code>unstable/crypto</code> to the <code>Trees:</code> line, and
        then run <code>fink selfupdate; fink index; fink scanpackages</code>.
        </p>
        <p>Also note, if you don't want to install any more from unstable than
        your specific packages and their dependencies, don't use the
        <code>update-all</code> command until you turn the unstable tree
        back off.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="unstable-onepackage">
      <question>
        <p>Do I <em>really</em> need to enable all of unstable just to install
        one unstable package that I want?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>No, but it is highly recommended you do.  Mixing and matching can
        cause unforeseen issues that make it difficult to debug problems when
        they do arise.</p>
        <p>That said, if you only want one or two specific packages, and nothing
        else from unstable, then you need to switch over to CVS updating (i.e.
        use <code>fink selfupdate-cvs</code>), because rsync only updates the
        trees that are active in your <filename>fink.conf</filename>. Edit
        <filename>/sw/etc/fink.conf</filename> and add <code>local/main</code>
        to the <code>Trees:</code> line, if not present. Then you'll need to
        run <code>fink selfupdate</code> to download the package description
        files. Now copy the relevant <code>.info</code> files (and their
        associated <code>.patch</code> files, if there are any) from
        <filename>/sw/fink/dists/unstable/main/finkinfo</filename> (or
        <filename>/sw/fink/dists/unstable/crypto/finkinfo</filename>) to
        <filename>/sw/fink/dists/local/main/finkinfo</filename>. However, note
        that your package may depend on other packages (or particular
        versions) which are also only in unstable. You will have to move their
        <code>.info</code> and <code>.patch</code> files as well. After you
        move all of the files, make sure to run <code>fink index</code>, so
        that Fink's record of available packages is updated. Once you're done
        you can switch back to rsync (<code>fink selfupdate-rsync</code>) if
        you want.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="sudo">
      <question>
        <p>I'm tired of typing my password into sudo again and again. Is there
        a way around this?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you're not paranoid, you can configure sudo to not ask you for a
        password. To do this, run <code>visudo</code> as root and add a line like this:</p>
        <codeblock>username ALL = NOPASSWD: ALL</codeblock>
        <p>Replace <code>username</code> with your actual username, of course.
        This line allows you to run any command via sudo without typing your
        password.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="exec-init-csh">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to run init.csh or init.sh, I get a "Permission denied"
        error. What am I doing wrong?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>init.csh and init.sh are not supposed to be run like normal
        commands. These files set environment variables like PATH and MANPATH
        in your shell. To have a lasting effect on the shell, it must be
        processed with the <code>source</code> command for csh/tcsh, or with
        the <code>.</code> command for bash/zsh, like this:</p>
        <p>for csh/tcsh:</p>
        <codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.csh</codeblock>
        <p>for bash/zsh:</p>
        <codeblock>. /sw/bin/init.sh</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="dselect-access">
      <question>
        <p>Help! I used the "[A]ccess" menu entry in dselect and now I can't
        download packages any more!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You probably pointed apt at a Debian mirror, which of course
        doesn't have the Fink files. You can fix this manually or through
        dselect. To fix it manually, edit the file
        <code>/sw/etc/apt/sources.list</code> in a text editor as root. Remove
        lines that mention debian.org and replace them with these:</p>
        <codeblock>deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download release main crypto
deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download current main crypto</codeblock>
        <p>(Or if you live in Europe, you can use
        <code>eu.dl.sourceforge.net</code> instead of
        <code>us.dl.sourceforge.net</code>)</p>
        <p>To fix it through dselect, run "[A]ccess" again, choose the "apt"
        method and enter the following info:</p>
        <p>URL: http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download -
        Distribution: release - Components: main crypto</p>
        <p>Then, say you want to add another source and repeat the process
        with "current" instead of "release".</p>
        <p>A fixed version of the apt package (which provides the
        configuration script as a plug-in for dselect) is making it's way
        through CVS now.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cvs-busy">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to run <quote>fink selfupdate</quote> or "fink
        selfupdate-cvs", I get the error "<code>Updating using CVS failed.
        Check the error messages above.</code>"</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If the message is</p>
        <codeblock>Can't exec "cvs": No such file or directory at 
/sw/lib/perl5/Fink/Services.pm line 216, &lt;STDIN&gt; line 3.
### execution of cvs failed, exit code -1</codeblock>
        <p>then you need to install the Developer Tools.</p>
        <p>If, on the other hand, the last line is</p>
        <codeblock>### execution of su failed, exit code 1</codeblock>
        <p>you'll need to look further back in the output to see the error. If
        you see a message that your connection was refused:</p>
        <codeblock>(Logging in to anonymous@fink.cvs.sourceforge.net)
CVS password:
cvs [login aborted]: connect to fink.cvs.sourceforge.net:2401 failed: 
Connection refused
### execution of su failed, exit code 1
Failed: Logging into the CVS server for anonymous read-only access failed.</codeblock>
        <p>or a message like the following:</p>
        <codeblock>cvs [update aborted]: recv() from server fink.cvs.sourceforge.net: 
Connection reset by peer 
### execution of su failed, exit code 1 
Failed: Updating using CVS failed. Check the error messages above.</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>cvs [update aborted]: End of file received from server</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>cvs [update aborted]: received broken pipe signal</codeblock>
        <p>then it's likely that the cvs servers are overloaded and you have
        to try the update later.</p>
        <p>Another possibility is that you have some bad permissions in your
        CVS directories, in which case you get "Permission denied"
        messages:</p>
        <codeblock>cvs update: in directory 10.2/stable/main: 
cvs update: cannot open CVS/Entries for reading: No such file or directory
cvs server: Updating 10.2/stable/main 
cvs update: cannot write 10.2/stable/main/.cvsignore: Permission denied
cvs [update aborted]: cannot make directory 10.2/stable/main/finkinfo: 
No such file or directory 
### execution of su failed, exit code 1 Failed: 
Updating using CVS failed. Check the error messages above.</codeblock>
        <p>In this case you need to reset your cvs directories. Use the
        command:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo find /sw/fink -type d -name 'CVS' -exec rm -rf {}\
; fink selfupdate-cvs</codeblock>
        <p>If, you don't see either of the above messages, then this almost
        always means you've modified a file in your /sw/fink/dists tree and
        now the maintainer has changed it. Look further back in the
        selfupdate-cvs output for lines that start with "C", like so:</p>
        <codeblock>C 10.2/unstable/main/finkinfo/libs/db31-3.1.17-6.info 
... (other info and patch files) ... 
### execution of su failed, exit code 1 
Failed: Updating using CVS failed. Check the error messages above.</codeblock>
        <p>The "C" means CVS had a conflict in trying to update the latest
        version.  The fix is to delete any files that show up as starting with "C" in
        the output of selfupdate-cvs, and try again:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo rm /sw/fink/10.2/unstable/main/finkinfo/libs/db31-3.1.17-6.info
fink selfupdate-cvs</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="kernel-panics">
      <question>
        <p>When I use Fink, my whole machine freezes up/kernel panics/dies.
        Help!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>A number of reports in fall, 2002 on the <link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=fink-users">fink-users
        mailing list</link> indicated problems (including kernel panics
        and infinite hangs during patching) when using Fink to compile
        packages while anti-virus software is installed. You may need to
        switch off any anti-virus software before using Fink.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="not-found">
      <question>
        <p>I'm trying to install a package, but Fink can't download it. The
        download site shows a later version number of the package than what
        Fink has. What do I do?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The package sources get moved around by the upstream sites when new
        versions are released.</p>
        <p>The first thing you should do is run <code>fink selfupdate</code>.
        It may be that the package maintainer has already fixed this, and you
        will get an updated package description with either a more recent
        version or a revised download URL.</p>
        <p>If this doesn't work, most sources are available on <link url="http://distfiles.master.finkmirrors.net/">http://distfiles.master.finkmirrors.net/</link>
        (thanks to Rob Braun) , and you can run <code>fink configure</code> to
        choose to search "Master" source mirrors so that Fink will
        automatically look there.</p>
        <p>If this doesn't work, please let the package maintainer (available
        from "<code>fink describe <em>packagename</em>
          </code>") know that the
        URL is broken; not all maintainers read the mailing lists all of the
        time.</p>
        <p>To get a usable source, first try hunting around the remote site in
        other directories for the same version of the source that Fink wants
        (e.g. in an "old" directory). Keep in mind, though, that some remote
        sites like to trash the old versions of their packages. If the
        official site doesn't have it, then try a web search--sometimes there
        are unofficial sites that have the tarball you want. Another place to
        look is <link url="http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download/source/">http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download/source/</link>,
        which is where Fink stores sourcefiles from packages that have been
        released in binary form. If all of the above fail, then you might
        consider posting on the <link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=fink-users">fink-users
        mailing list</link> to ask if anybody has the old source available to
        give you.</p>
        <p>Once you locate the proper source tarball, download it manually,
        and then move the file into your Fink source location (i.e. for a
        default Fink install, "<code>sudo mv <em>package-source.tar.gz</em>
        /sw/src/</code>". Then use '<code>fink install <em>packagename</em>
          </code>' as normal.</p>
        <p>If you can't get the source file, then you'll have to wait for the
        maintainer to deal with the problem. They may either post a link to
        the old source, or update the .info and .patch files to use the newer
        version.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="fink-not-found">
      <question>
        <p>I get "command not found" errors when I run Fink or anything that I
        installed with Fink.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If this always happens, then you may have inadvertently
        modified (or failed to modify) your startup scripts. Run the
        <filename>/sw/bin/pathsetup.sh</filename> script in a terminal
        window. This program will attempt to detect your default shell
        and add a command to load Fink's shell initialization script
        into your shell's configuration. You'll then need to open a
        new terminal session so that your environment settings are
        loaded. <em>Note:</em> Some older versions fink called this
        script <filename>pathsetup.command</filename> instead
        of <filename>pathsetup.sh</filename>. Alternately, you can run
        the <filename>pathsetup.app</filename> application on the Fink
        binary distribution disk image.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if you only have problems in the Apple X11
        terminal, the easy solution is to modify the "Terminal" entry in the X11 Application menu via the <em>Applications-&gt;Customize Menu... </em>option.  Instead of just</p>
        <codeblock>xterm</codeblock>
        <p>change the command field to read</p>
        <codeblock>xterm -ls</codeblock>
        <p><code>ls</code> here means <quote>login shell</quote>, and the result is that your full login setup gets used (just like the OS X Terminal).</p>
        <p>These <filename>/sw/bin/init.*</filename> scripts do much
	more than just add <filename>/sw/bin</filename> to your PATH.
	Many packages will not work correctly without these additional
	actions.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="invisible-sw">
      <question>
        <p>I want to hide /sw in the Finder to keep users from damaging the
        Fink setup.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You can indeed do this. If you have the Development Tools
        installed, then you can run the following command:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo /Developer/Tools/SetFile -a V /sw</codeblock>
        <p>This makes /sw invisible, just like the standard system folders
        (/usr, etc.). If you don't have the Developer Tools, there are various
        third-party applications that let you manipulate file attributes--you
        need to set /sw to be invisible.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="install-info-bad">
      <question>
        <p>I can't install anything, because I get the following error:
        "install-info: unrecognized option `--infodir=/sw/share/info'"</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This usually is due to a problem in your PATH. In a terminal window
        type:</p>
        <codeblock>printenv PATH</codeblock>
        <p>If <filename>/sw/sbin</filename> doesn't appear at all, then you
        need to set your environment up as per the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/users-guide/install.php#setup">instructions</link>
        in the Users Guide. If <filename>/sw/sbin</filename> is there, but
        there are other directories ahead of it (e.g.
        <filename>/usr/local/bin</filename>), then you will either want to
        reorder your PATH so that <filename>/sw/sbin</filename> is near the
        beginning. Or if you really need the other directory to be before
        <filename>/sw/sbin</filename>,  and this former directory includes another install-info directory, then you'll want to temporarily rename this <filename>install-info</filename> subdirectory when you use Fink.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="bad-list-file">
      <question>
        <p>I can't install or remove anything, because of a problem with a
        "files list file".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Typically these errors take the form:</p>
        <codeblock>files list file for package <em>packagename</em> contains empty filename</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>files list file for package <em>packagename</em> is missing final newline</codeblock>
        <p>This can be fixed, with a little work. If you have the .deb file
        for the offending package currently available on your system, then
        check its integrity by running</p>
        <codeblock>dpkg --contents <em>full-path-to-debfile</em>
        </codeblock>
        <p>e.g.</p>
        <codeblock>dpkg --contents /sw/fink/debs/libgnomeui2-dev_2.0.6-2_darwin-powerpc.deb</codeblock>
        <p>If you get back a listing of directories and files, then your .deb
        is OK. If the output is something other than directories and files, or
        if you don't have the .deb file, you can still proceed because the
        error doesn't interfere with builds.</p>
        <p>If you have been installing from the binary distribution or you
        know for sure that the version in the binary distribution is the same
        as what you have installed (e.g. by checking the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/pdb/index.php">package
        database</link>), then you can get a .deb file by running <code>sudo
        apt=get install --reinstall --download-only <em>packagename</em>
          </code>. Otherwise you can build one yourself by running <code>fink
        rebuild <em>packagename</em>
          </code>, but it won't install yet.</p>
        <p>Once you have a valid .deb file, then you can reconstitute the
        file. First become root by using <code>sudo -s</code> (enter your
        administrative user password if necessary), and then use the following
        command:</p>
        <codeblock>dpkg -c <em>full-path-to-debfile</em> | awk '{if ($6 == "./"){ print "/."; } \
else if (substr($6, length($6), 1) == "/")\
{print substr($6, 2, length($6) - 2); } \
else { print substr($6, 2, length($6) - 1);}}'\ 
&gt; /sw/var/lib/dpkg/info/<em>packagename</em>.list</codeblock>
        <p>e.g.</p>
        <codeblock>dpkg -c /sw/fink/debs/libgnomeui2-dev_2.0.6-2_darwin-powerpc.deb | awk \
'{if ($6 == "./") { print "/."; } \
else if (substr($6, length($6), 1) == "/") \
{print substr($6, 2, length($6) - 2); } \
else { print substr($6, 2, length($6) - 1);}}' \ 
&gt; /sw/var/lib/dpkg/info/libgnomeui2-dev.list</codeblock>
        <p>What this does is to extract the contents of the .deb file, remove
        everything but the filenames, and write these to the .list file.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="dselect-garbage">
      <question>
        <p>I get a bunch of garbage when I select packages in
        <filename>dselect</filename>. How can I use it?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There are issues between <filename>dselect</filename> and
        <filename>Terminal.app</filename>. A workaround is to enter the
        following command</p>
        <p>tcsh users:</p>
        <codeblock>setenv TERM xterm-color</codeblock>
        <p>bash users:</p>
        <codeblock>export TERM=xterm-color</codeblock>
        <p>before you run <filename>dselect</filename>. You may want to put
        this in your startup file (e.g. <code>.cshrc</code> |
        <code>.profile</code>) so that it gets run all of the time.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="perl-undefined-symbol">
      <question>
        <p>Why do I get a bunch of "dyld: perl undefined symbols" errors when
        I run Fink commands?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Obsolete</p>
        <p>If you see an error sequence like the following:</p>
        <codeblock>dyld: perl Undefined symbols: 
_Perl_safefree
_Perl_safemalloc 
_Perl_saferealloc 
_Perl_sv_2pv 
_perl_call_sv
_perl_eval_sv 
_perl_get_sv</codeblock>
        <p>then what has probably happened is that you updated Perl to a new
        version and now <filename>storable-pm</filename> needs to be updated.
        You should update Fink. During the process you will be prompted to
        install either <filename>perl-core</filename> or
        <filename>system-perl</filename>; choose the latter. In addition,
        <filename>storable-pm</filename> should also get updated.</p>
        <p>For OS 10.1.x, perform the following commands (you'll need the
        Developer Tools):</p>
        <codeblock>sudo mv /sw/lib/perl5/darwin/Storable.pm /tmp 
sudo mv /sw/lib/perl5/darwin/auto/Storable /tmp 
fink rebuild storable-pm 
fink selfupdate-cvs</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cant-upgrade">
      <question>
        <p>I can't seem to update Fink's version.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If neither running <code>fink selfupdate</code> nor <code>sudo apt-get update ; sudo apt-get dist-upgrade</code> updates you to a newer Fink release, then you may need to download a newer version of the <code>fink</code> package manually.  The relevant commands are:</p>
        <ul>
          <li><em>10.3.x:</em> (0.7.1 distribution)
		<codeblock>curl -O http://us.dl.sf.net/fink/direct_download/dists/fink-0.7.1-updates/main/binary-darwin-powerpc/base/fink_0.22.4-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
sudo dpkg -i fink_0.22.4-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
rm fink_0.22.4-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
fink selfupdate</codeblock></li>
          <li><em>10.2.x:</em> (0.6.3 distribution)
		<codeblock>curl -O http://us.dl.sf.net/fink/direct_download/dists/fink-0.6.3/release/main/binary-darwin-powerpc/base/fink_0.18.3-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
sudo dpkg -i fink_0.18.3-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
rm fink_0.18.3-1_darwin-powerpc.deb
fink selfupdate</codeblock></li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="spaces-in-directory">
      <question>
        <p>Can I put Fink in a volume or directory with a space in its
        name?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>We recommend against putting your Fink directory tree inside a
        directory with spaces in its name. It's just not worth the hassle.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="packages-gz">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to do a binary update, there are many messages with
        "File not found" or "Couldn't stat package source list file".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you see something like the following:</p>
        <codeblock>Err file: local/main Packages 
File not found 
Ign file: local/main Release 
Err file: stable/main Packages 
File not found 
Ign file: stable/main Release 
Err file: stable/crypto Packages 
File not found 
Ign file: stable/crypto Release 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/release/main Packages 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/release/main Release 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/release/crypto Packages 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/release/crypto Release 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/current/main Packages 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/current/main Release 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/current/crypto Packages 
Hit http://us.dl.sourceforge.net 10.3/current/crypto Release 
Failed to fetch file:/sw/fink/dists/local/main/binary-darwin-powerpc/Packages
File not found 
Failed to fetch file:/sw/fink/dists/stable/main/binary-darwin-powerpc/Packages
File not found
Failed to fetch file:/sw/fink/dists/stable/crypto/binary-darwin-powerpc/Packages
File not found 
Reading Package Lists... Done 
Building Dependency Tree...Done 
E: Some index files failed to download, 
they have been ignored, or old ones used instead. 
update available list script returned error exit status 1.</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>W: Couldn't stat source package list file: unstable/main Packages
(/sw/var/lib/apt/lists/_sw_fink_dists_unstable_main_binary-darwin-
powerpc_Packages) - stat (2 No such file or directory)</codeblock>
        <p>then all you need to do is run <code>fink scanpackages</code>. This
        generates the files that aren't being found.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="wrong-tree">
      <question>
        <p>I've changed my OS | Developer Tools, but Fink doesn't recognize
        the change.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>When changing the Fink distribution (of which the source and binary
        distros are subsets), Fink needs to be told that this has happened. To
        do this, you can run a script that normally gets run when you first
        install Fink:</p>
        <codeblock>/sw/lib/fink/postinstall.pl</codeblock>
        <p>Doing this will point Fink to the correct place.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="seg-fault">
      <question>
        <p>I get errors with <code>gzip</code> | <code>dpkg-deb</code>I
        applications from the<code> fileutils </code>package! Help!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Errors of the form:</p>
        <codeblock>gzip -dc /sw/src/dpkg-1.10.9.tar.gz | /sw/bin/tar -xf - 
### execution of gzip failed, exit code 139</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>gzip -dc /sw/src/aquaterm-0.3.0a.tar.gz | /sw/bin/tar -xf -
gzip: stdout: Broken pipe 
### execution of gzip failed, exit code 138</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>dpkg-deb -b root-base-files-1.9.0-1 /sw/fink/dists/unstable/main/binary-darwin-powerpc/base

### execution of dpkg-deb failed, exit code 1
Failed: can't create package base-files_1.9.0-1_darwin-powerpc.deb</codeblock>
        <p>or segmentation faults when running utilities from<code>
        fileutils</code>, e.g. <code>ls</code> or <code>mv</code>, are likely
        to be due to a prebinding error in a library, and can be fixed by
        running</p>
        <codeblock>sudo /sw/var/lib/fink/prebound/update-package-prebinding.pl -f</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="pathsetup-keeps-running">
      <question>
        <p>When I open a Terminal window, I get a message that "Your
        environment seems to be correctly set up for Fink already.", and it
        logs out.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>What happened is that somehow the OSX Terminal program has been
        told to run <code>/sw/bin/pathsetup.command</code> every time you log
        in. You can fix this by removing the Preferences file,
        <code>~/Library/Preferences/com.apple.Terminal.plist</code>.</p>
        <p>If you have other preferences that you want to keep, you can edit
        the file with a text editor and remove the reference to
        <code>/sw/bin/pathsetup.command</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="ext-drive">
      <question>
        <p>I have Fink installed away from the main partition and I can't update the fink package from source.  There are errors involving <quote>chowname</quote>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If your error looks like:</p>
        <codeblock>This first test is designed to die, so please ignore the error
message on the next line.
# Looks like your test died before it could output anything.
./00compile............................ok
./Base/initialize......................ok
./Base/param...........................ok
./Base/param_boolean...................ok
./Command/cat..........................ok
./Command/chowname.....................#     
Failed test (./Command/chowname.t at line 27)
#          got: 'root'
#     expected: 'nobody'</codeblock>
        <p>then you need to run <em>Get Info</em> on the drive/partition where Fink is installed and unselect the "Ignore ownership" button.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="mirror-gnu">
      <question>
        <p>Fink won't update my packages because it says it can't find the 'gnu' mirror.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you get an error that ends with</p>
        <codeblock>Failed: No mirror site list file found for mirror 'gnu'.</codeblock>
        <p>then most likely you need to update the <code>fink-mirrors</code> package, e.g. via:</p>
        <codeblock>fink install fink-mirrors</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cant-move-fink">
      <question>
        <p>I can't update Fink, because it can't move /sw/fink out of the way.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This error:</p>
        <codeblock>Failed: Can't move "/sw/fink" out of the way.</codeblock>
        <p>is usually due, in spite of what it says, to permissions errors in one of the temporary directories that get created during a <code>selfupdate</code>.  Remove these:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo rm -rf /sw/fink.tmp /sw/fink.old</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="four-oh-three">
      <question>
        <p>I keep getting 403 errors when I use <code>apt-get</code> or <code>dselect</code> or the Fink Commander Binary menu.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There have been problems with the Sourceforge download servers, and therefore we are moving the binary distribution repository for this very reason.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>If you have the Developer Tools installed then install the latest version of the <code>fink-mirrors</code> package (&gt;= 0.24.4.1), and then reinstall <code>fink</code>, either via:
<codeblock>fink reinstall fink</codeblock>
<p>or</p>
<codeblock>sudo apt-get install --reinstall fink</codeblock>
<p>(if for whatever reason you don't want to use the source distribution).</p>
</li>
          <li>If you don't have the Developer Tools installed, then you'll have to set things up manually.  Edit your <filename>sources.list</filename> file as root, e.g..via
<codeblock>sudo pico /sw/etc/apt/sources.list</codeblock>
<p>(use your favorite Unix-line-ending-compatible text editor). Change the lines that start with "Official binary distribution:" thusly:</p>
<codeblock># Official binary distribution: download location for packages
# from the latest release
deb http://bindist.finkmirrors.net/bindist 10.3/release main crypto

# Official binary distribution: download location for updated
# packages built between releases
deb http://bindist.finkmirrors.net/bindist 10.3/current main crypto</codeblock>
<p>The above of course assumes you're on 10.3.  If you're on a different OS replace <code>10.3</code> with what your current distribution is.</p>
<p>Then save your work and quit the editor.  Now update your binary package list again.</p>
</li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="fc-cache">
      <question>
        <p>I get a message that says "No fonts found".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you see the following (so far only seen on OS 10.4):</p>
        <codeblock>No fonts found; this probably means that the fontconfig
library is not correctly configured. You may need to
edit the fonts.conf configuration file. More information
about fontconfig can be found in the fontconfig(3) manual
page and on http://fontconfig.org.</codeblock>
        <p>then you can fix it by running</p>
        <codeblock>sudo fc-cache</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="non-admin-installer">
      <question>
        <p> I can't install Fink via the Installer package, because I get "volume doesn't support symlinks" errors.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This message commonly means that you've tried to run the Fink installer as user who doesn't have administrative privileges.  Make sure to log in at the login screen as such a user or switch to such a user in the Finder (i.e. fast user switching) before starting the Fink installer.</p>
        <p>If you're having trouble even when using an admin account, then it's likely a problem with the permissions on your top-level directory.  Use Apple's Disk Utility, select the hard drive in question, choose the <em>First Aid</em> tab, and press <em>Repair Disk Permissions</em>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="comp-general">
    <!-- FAQs in comp-general are coded into VirtPackage.pm
       Do not rename, remove, or otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
    <title>Compile Problems - General</title>
    <shorttitle>Compiling (1)</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="compiler">
      <question>
        <p>A configure script complains that it can't find an "acceptable cc".
        What's that?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Read the docs next time. To compile packages from source, you must
        install the Developer Tools, which among other stuff contains the C
        compiler, <code>cc</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cvs">
      <question>
        <p>When I try a "fink selfupdate-cvs" I get this message: "cvs:
        Command not found."</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You need to install the Developer Tools.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="missing-make">
      <question>
        <p>I'm getting an error message involving <code>make</code>
        </p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>if your message is of the form</p>
        <codeblock>make: command not found</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>Can't exec "make": 
No such file or directory at /sw/lib/perl5/Fink/Services.pm line 190.</codeblock>
        <p>It means you need to install the Developer Tools.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if your error message looks like</p>
        <codeblock>make: illegal option -- C</codeblock>
        <p>then you've replaced the GNU version of the <code>make</code>
        utility installed as part of the Developer Tools with a BSD version of
        make. Many packages rely on special features only supported by GNU
        make. Make sure that <code>/usr/bin/make</code> is a symlink to
        <code>gnumake</code>, not <code>bsdmake</code>. Furthermore, make sure
        that <code>/usr/local/bin/</code> does not contain another copy of
        <code>make</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="head">
      <question>
        <p>I'm getting a strange usage message from the head command. What's
        broken?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you're seeing this:</p>
        <codeblock>Unknown option: 1 Usage: head [-options] &lt;url&gt;...</codeblock>
        <p>followed by a list of option descriptions, you have a broken
        <code>head</code> executable. This happens when you install the Perl
        libwww library on an HFS+ system volume. It tries to create a new
        command <code>/usr/bin/HEAD</code>, which overwrites the existing
        <code>head</code> command because the file system is case-insensitive.
        <code>head</code> is a standard command used in many shell scripts and
        Makefiles. You need to get the original <code>head</code> executable
        back if you want to use Fink.</p>
        <p>The bootstrap script of the source release now checks for this, but
        you can still run into it if you use the binary release for first-time
        installation or install libwww after you installed Fink.</p>
        <p>This problem has also been reported due to the installation of
        <filename>/sw/bin/HEAD</filename> (not by any Fink package). This is
        easier to solve: rename <filename>/sw/bin/HEAD</filename>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="also_in">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to install a package I get an error message about trying
        to overwrite a file that is in another package.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This occasionally happens with splitoff packages (i.e. the ones
        with -dev, -shlibs, etc.) when a file gets moved from one part of the
        splitoff to another (e.g. from <code>foo</code> to
        <code>foo-shlibs</code>. What you can do is overwrite the file with
        that from the package you are trying to install (since they are
        nominally the same):</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg -i --force-overwrite <em>filename</em>
        </codeblock>
        <p>where <em>filename</em> is the .deb file corresponding to the
        package that you are trying to install.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="weak_lib">
      <question>
        <p>After I installed the December 2002 Development Tools I get
        messages about "weak libraries".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is new with the December 2002 Tools. You may occasionally see
        messages like (choosing libgdk-pixbuf as an example):</p>
        <codeblock>ld: warning dynamic shared library:
/sw/lib/libgdk-pixbuf.dylib not made a weak library in output with
MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET environment variable set to: 10.1</codeblock>
        <p>You may regard these as harmless. If you are curious, read through
        the release notes in the developer documentation directory, especially
        GCC's and the linker's, for more info. It essentially has to do with
        whether missing symbols at runtime is considered a fatal error on
        startup or not, for applications that use weak references.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="mv-failed">
      <question>
        <p>What does "execution of mv failed, exit code 1" mean when I try to
        build a package?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you have StuffIt Pro installed, it could be that you have
        "Archive Via Real Name" mode enabled. Check for a StuffIt preference
        pane in the System Preferences tool, and disable "ArchiveViaRealName"
        if it's enabled. It contains a buggy reimplementation of a few
        important system calls that will cause a number of strange and
        transient errors such as this.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, an  <filename>mv</filename> error typically means that
        another error happened earlier in the build, but the build process
        didn't stop. To track down the offending file(s), search in the output
        of the build for the nonexistent file, e.g. if you have something
        like:</p>
        <codeblock>mv /sw/src/root-foo-0.1.2-3/sw/lib/libbar*.dylib \
/sw/src/root-foo-shlibs-0.1.2-3/sw/lib/ 
mv: cannot stat `/sw/src/root-foo-0.1.2-3/sw/lib/libbar*.dylib': 
No such file or directory 
### execution of mv failed, exit code 1 
Failed: installing foo-0.1.2-3 failed</codeblock>
        <p>then you should look for <filename>libbar</filename> somewhere
        further back in the output of your build attempt.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="node-exists">
      <question>
        <p>I can't install a package | update because I get a message that a
        "node" already exists.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>These errors look something like this:</p>
        <codeblock>Failed: Internal error: node for system-xfree86 already exists</codeblock>
        <p>This problem is that the dependency engine is confused, due to
        changes in some of the package info files. To fix it:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>Remove the offending package by force, e. g.</p>
            <codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-all system-xfree86</codeblock>
            <p>for the example given above.</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>Try again to install | upgrade. At some point a "virtual
          dependency" prompt will come up that includes the package you just
          removed. Select it, and it will be reinstalled during your
          build.</p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="usr-local-libs">
      <question>
        <p>I've heard that libraries and headers installed under /usr/local sometimes
        cause build problems for Fink. Is this true?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is a frequent source of problems, because the package
        configuration script finds headers and libraries in 
        <filename>/usr/local</filename> and decides to use them rather than using those in the Fink path.
        If you are having problems with a build that aren't covered by another
        FAQ entry, you should check whether you have libraries in
        <filename>/usr/local/lib</filename> or headers in /usr/local/include. If so, then try renaming
        <filename>/usr/local</filename> to something else, e.g.:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo mv /usr/local /usr/local.moved</codeblock>
        <p>do your build, and then put <filename>/usr/local</filename>
        back:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo mv /usr/local.moved /usr/local</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="toc-out-of-date">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to build a package, I get a message that a "table of
        contents" is out of date. What do I need to do?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The output hints at what to do. The message is usually something
        like:</p>
        <codeblock>ld: table of contents for archive: 
/sw/lib/libintl.a is out of date; 
rerun ranlib(1) (can't load from it)</codeblock>
        <p>What you need to do is run ranlib (as root) on whatever library is
        causing the problem. As an example, for the case above, you would
        run:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo ranlib /sw/lib/libintl.a</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="fc-atlas">
      <question>
        <p>Fink Commander hangs when I try to install atlas.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This happens because one of the steps in the build of
        <code>atlas</code> sends a prompt to the user that Fink Commander
        doesn't display. You'll have to use <code>fink install atlas</code>
        instead.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="basic-headers">
      <question>
        <p>I get messages saying that I'm missing <filename>stddef.h</filename>, <filename>wchar.h</filename>, or <filename>crt1.o</filename>, or that my "C compiler cannot create executables".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Both of these problems are typically due to the absence of essential headers that are provided by the DevSDK package of
        the Developer Tools. Check whether
        <filename>/Library/Receipts/DevSDK.pkg</filename> exists on your
        system. If not, then run the Dev Tools Installer again, and install
        the DevSDK package using a Custom Install.</p>
        <p>The "cannot create executables" error can also occur when your Developer Tools version is for an earlier OS version.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="multiple-dependencies">
      <question>
        <p>I can't update, because Fink is "unable to resolve version conflict
        on multiple dependencies".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>To get around this, try updating a single package, then try to use
        "fink update-all" again. If you still get the message, repeat the
        process.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="dpkg-parse-error">
      <question>
        <p>I can't install anything because I get "dpkg: parse error, in file
        `/sw/var/lib/dpkg/status'"!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This means that somehow your dpkg database got corrupted, usually
        from a crash or some other unrecoverable error. You can fix it by
        copying the previous version of the database, like so:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo cp /sw/var/lib/dpkg/status-old /sw/var/lib/dpkg/status</codeblock>
        <p>You may need to re-install the last couple of packages you
        installed before the problem started occurring.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="freetype-problems">
      <question>
        <p>I get errors involving freetype.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There are several varieties of such errors. If your error looks
        like:</p>
        <codeblock>/sw/include/pango-1.0/pango/pangoft2.h:52: 
error: parse error before '*' token 
/sw/include/pango-1.0/pango/pangoft2.h:57:
error: parse error before '*' token
/sw/include/pango-1.0/pango/pangoft2.h:61: 
error: parse error before '*' token 
/sw/include/pango-1.0/pango/pangoft2.h:86: 
error: parse error before "pango_ft2_font_get_face"
/sw/include/pango-1.0/pango/pangoft2.h:86: 
warning: data definition has no type or storage class 
make[2]: *** [rsvg-gz.lo] Error 1
make[1]: *** [all-recursive] Error 1 
make: *** [all-recursive-am] Error 2 
### execution of make failed, exit code 2 
Failed: compiling librsvg2-2.4.0-3 failed</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>In file included from vteft2.c:32: 
vteglyph.h:64: error:
parse error before "FT_Library" 
vteglyph.h:64: warning: 
no semicolon at end of struct or union vteft2.c: 
In function `_vte_ft2_get_text_width': 
vteft2.c:236: error: 
dereferencing pointer to incomplete type 
vteft2.c: In function `_vte_ft2_get_text_height':
vteft2.c:244: error: 
dereferencing pointer to incomplete type
vteft2.c: In function `_vte_ft2_get_text_ascent': 
vteft2.c:252: error:
dereferencing pointer to incomplete type 
vteft2.c: In function `_vte_ft2_draw_text': 
vteft2.c:294: error: 
dereferencing pointer to incomplete type 
vteft2.c:295: error: 
dereferencing pointer to incomplete type
make[2]: *** [vteft2.lo] Error 1 
make[1]: *** [all-recursive] Error 1 
make: *** [all] Error 2 
### execution of make failed, exit code 2
Failed: compiling vte-0.11.10-3 failed</codeblock>
        <p>or</p>
        <codeblock>checking for freetype-config.../usr/X11R6/bin/freetype-config 
checking For sufficiently new FreeType (at least 2.0.1)... no 
configure: error: pangoxft 
Pango backend found but did not find freetype libraries 
make: *** No targets specified and no makefile found. Stop. 
### execution of LD_TWOLEVEL_NAMESPACE=1 failed, exit code 2 
Failed: compiling gtk+2-2.2.4-2 failed</codeblock>
        <p>the problem is due to confusion between headers from the
        <code>freetype</code> | <code>freetype-hinting</code> package and the
        <code>freetype2</code> headers that are included with X11 |
        XFree86.</p>
        <codeblock>fink remove freetype freetype-hinting</codeblock>
        <p>will remove whichever variant you have installed. On the other
        hand, if your error looks like:</p>
        <codeblock>ld: Undefined symbols: _FT_Access_Frame</codeblock>
        <p>this is typically due to a residual file from a prior installation
        of X11. Reinstall the X11 SDK. Finally, if you get an error like</p>
        <codeblock>dyld: klines Undefined symbols: /sw/lib/libqt-mt.3.dylib 
undefined reference to _FT_Access_Frame</codeblock>
        <p>then you probably have a binary version that built fine with
        <code>gcc3.3</code> on Jaguar but doesn't work on Panther. This has
        now been updated, so you you just need to update your packages, e.g.
        via <code>sudo apt-get update ; sudo apt-get dist-upgrade</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="dlfcn-from-oo">
      <question>
        <p>I get build errors involving `Dl_info'.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you have an error that looks like this</p>
        <codeblock>unix_dl.c: In function `rep_open_dl_library':
unix_dl.c:328: warning: assignment discards qualifiers from pointer target type 
unix_dl.c: In function `rep_find_c_symbol': 
unix_dl.c:466: error: `Dl_info' undeclared (first use in this function)
unix_dl.c:466: error: (Each undeclared identifier is reported only once 
unix_dl.c:466: error: for each function it appears in.)
unix_dl.c:466: error: parse error before "info" 
unix_dl.c:467: error: `info' undeclared (first use in this function) 
make[1]: *** [unix_dl.lo] Error 1</codeblock>
        <p>then most likely you have a header file,
        <code>/usr/local/include/dlfcn.h</code>, that is incompatible with
        Panther. Move it out of the way.</p>
        <p>This usually is installed by Open Office, and you should replace
        this header file, as well as the library
        <code>/usr/local/lib/libdl.dylib</code>, with symbolic links to
        Panther's builtin files</p>
        <codeblock>sudo ln -s /usr/include/dlfcn.h /usr/local/include/dlfcn.h
sudo ln -s /usr/lib/libdl.dylib /usr/local/lib/libdl.dylib</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="gcc2">
      <!-- FAQ comp-general.gcc2 is coded into VirtPackage.pm
         Do not rename, remove, move to a different chapter, or
         otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
      <question>
        <p>Fink says I'm missing <filename>gcc2</filename> or <filename>gcc3.1</filename> but I can't seem to
        install it.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is because <filename>gcc2</filename> and <filename>gcc3.1</filename> are  virtual packages to
        indicate the presence of gcc-2.95 and gcc-3.1, respectively, on your system. Install the gcc2.95 and/or the gcc3.1
        package from the XCode Tools (earlier OS versions have gcc-2.95 and gcc-3.1 as
        part of their main Developer Tools installation).</p>
        <p><em>Note:  </em>Installing gcc2.95 and/or gcc3.1 will not interfere with your gcc3.3 compiler--they can all coexist.  </p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="system-java">
      <question>
        <p>Fink says <code>Failed: Can't resolve dependency "system-java14-dev"</code>, but there's no such package.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>That's because it's a virtual package.  This type of error occurs when Java gets updated by Software Update:  the header files get removed, which causes the -dev package not to be generated.</p>
        <p>You need to download the appropriate <filename>Java Developer Tools</filename> package from <link url="http://connect.apple.com">Apple</link>.  In this specific case that's the <filename>Java 1.4.2 Developer Tools</filename>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="dpkg-split">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to install anything, I get <quote>dpkg (subprocess): failed to exec dpkg-split to see if it's part of a multiparter: No such file or directory</quote>.  How do I fix this?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Generally, this can be fixed by setting your environment up correctly, cf. <xref chapter="usage-fink" section="fink-not-found">this FAQ entry</xref>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="xml-parser">
      <question>
        <p>I get the following message: <quote>configure: error: XML::Parser perl module is required for intltool</quote>.  What do I do about it?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
	<p>If you're using the unstable tree, make sure you have intltool-0.34.1or later installed.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, you need to make sure that you have the right variant of the xml-parser-pm package to match the Perl version for your system.  For example, if you're on Panther you should have <code>xml-parser-pm581</code> rather than <code>xml-parser-pm560</code> (you may also have the <code>xml-parser-pm</code> placeholder), since you have <code>Perl-5.8.1</code> rather than <code>Perl-5.6.0</code>.  If you're on Jaguar, and are using the default system Perl version, you'll have the <code>pm560</code> variant, and if you've installed <code>Perl 5.8.0</code> you may have the <code>pm580</code> variant.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="master-problems">
      <question>
        <p>I'm trying to download a package, but Fink goes to some weird site with <quote>distfiles</quote> in its name, and the file isn't there.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>What's happened here is that Fink is trying to use one of it's so called <quote>Master</quote> mirrors.  These were set up to makes sure that sources for Fink packages are available even when the upstream site has moved them around.  Typically these errors occur when a new upstream version of a package is released, but hasn't made it to the Master mirrors yet.</p>
        <p>To remedy this, run <code>fink configure</code> and set the search order to use Master mirrors last.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="compile-options">
      <question>
        <p>I want Fink to use different options in building a package.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>The first thing to do is to contact the package maintainer to request a variant.  It may be relatively easy to do it.  If you don't hear from the maintainer or see the new packages, or want to try a different option yourself, check out the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/quick-start-pkg/index.php">Packaging Tutorial</link> and <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/packaging/index.php">Packaging Manual</link>.</p>
        <p>
          <em>Note:  </em>Fink is deliberately set up such that all official binaries are identical regardless of what machine they are built on, so things like G5 optimization won't happen with an official package.  If you want them, you'll have to do it yourself.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="gettext">
      <question>
        <p>Whenever I try to build from source, Fink keeps waffling between <code>gettext-dev</code> and <code>libgettext3-dev</code>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Some packages that need <code>gettext</code> headers to build have been updated to use <code>libgettext3-dev</code> and some still use <code>gettext-dev</code>.  Consequently, Fink may try to switch to whichever one isn't currently installed in order to satisfy a build dependency for some package that you're trying to update.  In addition, the <code>fink </code> tool treats <code>gettext-dev</code> as essential, and will install it any time you selfupdate.</p>
        <p>Similar behavior can happen for other pairs of packages, too. </p>
        <p>Unfortunately, due to limitations in the build-dependency engine, you may find that your build bombs because you've swapped in one of these but some later package in your build chain wants the other one.  You can usually proceed by repeating your update command again.</p>
<p>In extreme cases you may wind up having to install those packages which build-depend on <code>gettext-dev</code> separately from those which want <code>libgettext3-dev</code> (or whichever pair are causing problems).  You may even have to install packages one by one.</p>
        <p>A permanent fix should hopefully be available in <code>fink-0.24.9</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="python-mods">
      <question>
        <p>I get errors involving <code>MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET </code>when I try to build a Python module.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>For errors that look like the following:</p>
        <codeblock>running build
running build_ext
Traceback (most recent call last):
  File "setup_socket_ssl.py", line 21, in ?
    depends = ['socketmodule.h'] )
  File "/sw/src/root-python24-2.4.1-1/sw/lib/python2.4/distutils/core.py", line 166, in setup
SystemExit: error: $MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET mismatch: now "10.4" but "10.3" during configure
### execution of /sw/bin/python2.4 failed, exit code 1</codeblock>
        <p>the problem occurs because the <code>python2*</code> packages write the current <code>MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET</code> to a configuration file when they're built and the python build utilities use this value when compiling modules. This means that if you have, for example, a <code>python24</code> package on 10.4 that was built on 10.3, either by upgrading 10.3 =&gt; 10.4, or via the <em>10.4-transitional</em> binary distribution, in which <code>python24</code> wasn't rebuilt, there will be a mismatch between what python thinks <code>MACOSX_DEPLOYMENT_TARGET</code> should be (10.3) and what it actually is (10.4).</p>
        <p>The fix is to rebuild the offending <code>python</code> package, e.g. <code>fink rebuild python24</code> for the case above.</p>
<p>For runtime errors that give the same type of error message as above, rebuild the module after rebuilding the appropriate <code>python2*</code> package.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="comp-packages">
    <title>Compile Problems - Specific Packages</title>
    <shorttitle>Compiling (2)</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="libgtop">
      <question>
        <p>A package fails to build with errors involving
        <code>sed</code>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This can happen if your login script (e.g. <code>~/.cshrc</code>)
        does something that writes to the terminal, e.g "<code>echo
        Hello</code>" or <code>xttitle</code>. To get rid of the problem, the
        easy solution is to comment out the offending lines.</p>
        <p>If you want to keep the echo, then you can do something like the
        following:</p>
        <codeblock>if ( $?prompt) then 
	echo Hello 
endif</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cant-install-xfree">
      <question>
        <p>I want to switch to Fink's XFree86 packages, but I can't install
        <code>xfree86-base</code> | <code>xfree86</code>, because it conflicts
        with <code>system-xfree86</code>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>All flavors of X11, unfortunately, really needs to be installed in
        /usr/X11R6. Because of this the Fink <code>xfree86-base</code> and
        <code>xfree86-rootless</code> packages install there, too. However,
        since Fink won't remove any files that aren't in its database, it
        won't automatically replace a non-Fink installation of X11.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>Here's how to proceed:</p>
        <p></p>
        <p>
          <em>Note: 10.2.x users with up-to-date versions of Fink (&gt;=
        0.16.2) and 10.3.x users should skip step 1 below (it won't work
        anyway).</em>
        </p>
        <p>1. Remove <code>system-xfree86</code>. If you don't have any
        packages that depend on X11, this is straightforward. Frequently,
        however, many packages that depend on X11 are installed. Rather than
        uninstalling all of them, you can use</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg --remove --force-depends system-xfree86</codeblock>
        <p>to remove it, leaving everything in place. If you don't have
        <code>system-xfree86</code> installed then proceed to step 3.</p>
        <p>2. Manually remove all of XFree86. This can be done with</p>
        <codeblock>sudo rm -rf /Applications/XDarwin.app /usr/X11R6 /etc/X11</codeblock>
        <p>If you are switching from Apple X11, remove the X11 application,
        too.</p>
        <p>3. To get XFree86-4.2.1, Install Fink's <code>xfree86-base</code>
        and <code>xfree86-rootless</code> packages by the usual means:
        "<code>fink install</code>" for source users, "<code>apt-get
        install</code>" or <code>dselect</code> for binaries.</p>
        <p>-or-</p>
        <p>3a. To get XFree86-4.3.x and above, install Fink's <code>xfree86</code> package, with "fink install xfree86"--the latest version (XFree86-4.4.x as of May 25th, 2004) isn't in the binary distro yet, and is currently only in the unstable tree [see <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/faq/usage-fink.php#unstable\">how to install unstable packages</link>].</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="change-thread-nothread">
      <question>
        <p>How do I change from the non-threaded version of Fink's XFree86
        packages to the threaded version (or vice-versa)?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you are running the Fink version of XFree86 and you want to
        switch between the threaded and non-threaded versions of Fink, you
        need to manually remove the old version. This is done at the
        command-line with the commands:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-base 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-shlibs 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-rootless 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-rootless-shlibs</codeblock>
        <p>or to delete the threaded versions:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-base-threaded 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-shlibs-threaded 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-rootless-threaded 
sudo dpkg -r --force-depends xfree86-rootless-threaded-shlibs</codeblock>
        <p>FinkCommander also has a way to remove packages. In the source
        window, select a package, and then in the <code>Source Menu</code> use
        "<code>Force Remove</code>."</p>
        <p>If you are using system-xfree86, see the previous question for
        removing it.</p>
        <p>Install the version of xfree86 you want:</p>
        <p>
          <code>xfree86-base</code> and <code>xfree86-rootless</code>
        </p>
        <p>
          <code>xfree86-base-threaded</code> and
        <code>xfree86-rootless-threaded</code>
        </p>
        <p>by the usual means: "<code>fink install</code>" for source users,
        "<code>apt-get install</code>" or <code>dselect</code> for
        binaries.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <!--obsolete><faqentry name="apple-x11" >
<question>
<p>I've installed the Apple X11 package, but system-xfree86 won't install.</p>
</question>
<answer>
<p>If you get error messages like the following:</p>
<codeblock>- missing /usr/X11R6/lib/libX11.dylib
- missing /usr/X11R6/lib/libXpm.dylib
- missing /usr/X11R6/lib/libXaw.dylib
- missing /usr/X11R6/include/X11/Xlib.h

Your XFree86 installation is missing or incomplete. Please make sure you have
an XFree86 release installed and retry the installation of the system-xfree86
package.
</codeblock>
<p>then you need to install the SDK package as well as the User package. If you are running Panther, the SDK is on the XCode disk and is <em>NOT</em> automatically installed. The SDK as well as X11 beta for Jaguar is no longer available, and you'll either have to upgrade to Panther or use Fink's xfree86.</p>
<p>If, on the other hand, you get the following message:</p>
<codeblock>An error occurred trying to find your XFree86 installation's
version. This really shouldn't happen, so I'm bailing. :(</codeblock>
<p>then you need to update your package descriptions and install a newer version of system-xfree86. If you are installing Apple X11 Beta 3, then you will need <filename>system-xfree86-4.2-11</filename> or later.</p>
</answer>
</faqentry><-->
    <faqentry name="cctools">
      <question>
        <p>"When I try to install KDE, I get the following message: 'Can't
        resolve dependency "cctools (&gt;= 446-1)"'"</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This somewhat cryptic message means you need to install the
        December 2002 Developer Tools.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <!--obsolete><faqentry name="system-xfree86-upgrade" >
<question>
<p>I can't update system-xfree86, because of a conflict with x11.</p>
</question>
<answer>
	<p>This problem has come about because of changes needed to allow for externally installed XFree86-4.3. Originally, <code>system-xfree86</code> provided the <code>x11</code> virtual package when an externally installed XFree86 was present. Because it only worked for XFree86-4.2, it was decided to have two separate packages for XFree86 4.2.x and Apple X11 beta 3, and one for XFree86 4.3.x and Apple X11 1.0</p>
<p>Either of these will provide <code>x11</code>. <code>system-xfree86</code> is now a bundle that installs the appropriate one of the above packages, depending on the version of XFree86 / Apple X11 that is installed. Unfortunately, switching the provider of a virtual package is sufficiently complicated that the automatic upgrade procedure can't deal with it (currently). Do an additional <code>selfupdate</code> to get the latest version of the package, then try to update again.</p>
</answer>
</faqentry><-->
    <faqentry name="libiconv-gettext">
      <question>
        <p>I can't update <code>libiconv</code>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you get errors of the form:</p>
        <codeblock>libtool: link: cannot find the library `/sw/lib/libiconv.la'</codeblock>
        <p>you can solve this problem by running</p>
        <codeblock>fink remove gettext-dev
fink install libiconv</codeblock>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="cplusplus-filt">
      <question>
        <p>i can't install <code>g77</code> because <filename>c++filt</filename> is missing.  Where do I get it?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If you get errors of the form </p>
        <codeblock>xgcc: installation problem, cannot exec `c++filt': No such file or directory</codeblock>
        <p>since updating to Tiger, then you need to do the following:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Flush out your old Developer Tools versions via running <codeblock>/Developer/Tools/uninstall-devtools.pl</codeblock>in a terminal.  Then install XCode (2.0 or later).<p></p></li>
          <li>Reinstall  <code>BSD.pkg</code> (from the Tiger system installation).  If <code>/usr/bin/c++filt</code> doesn't appear, keep trying.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
1) Flush out your old
2) Reinstall BSD.pkg (from your main OS install)</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="all-others">
    <question>
      <p>I'm having issues with a package that isn't listed here.</p>
    </question>
    <answer>
      <p>Since package problems tend to be transient, we've decided to put them
      up on the Fink wiki.  Check the <link url="http://wiki.opendarwin.org/index.php/Fink:Package_issues"> Package issues page</link>.</p>
    </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="usage-general">
    <!-- FAQs in usage-general are coded into VirtPackage.pm
       Do not rename, remove, or otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
    <title>Package Usage Problems - General</title>
    <shorttitle>Usage (1)</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="xlocale">
      <question>
        <p>I'm getting lots of messages like "locale not supported by C
        library". Is that bad?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>It's not bad, it just means that the program will use the default
        English messages, date formats, etc. The program will function
        normally otherwise. The Running X11 document has <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/x11/trouble.php#locale">details</link>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="passwd">
      <question>
        <p>There are suddenly a number of strange users on my system, with
        names like "mysql", "pgsql", and "games". Where did they come
        from?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You have used Fink to install a package which is dependent on
        another package, passwd. passwd installs a number of extra users on
        your system for security reasons -- on Unix systems, files and
        processes belong to "owners", which allows system administrators to
        fine-tune the permissions and security of the system. Programs such as
        Apache and MySQL need an "owner", and it is insecure to assign these
        daemons to root (imagine what would happen if Apache were to be
        compromised and suddenly had write permission to all files on the
        system). Thus, the passwd package takes the work out of setting up
        these extra users for Fink packages that require this.</p>
        <p>It can be alarming to discover suddenly a number of unexpected
        users in your "System Preferences: Users" pane (on 10.2.x) or "System Preferences: Accounts" pane (on 10.3.x), but suppress the urge 
        to delete them:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>First of all, you have obviously chosen to install a package
          which requires their use, so deleting the user doesn't make much
          sense, does it?</li>
          <li>There are in fact a number of extra users already installed on
          Mac OS X that you may not have known about: www, daemon, nobody, are
          just a few of them. The presence of these extra users is a standard
          Unix convention for running certain services; the passwd package
          simply adds a couple of extra that Apple did not provide. You can
          see these Apple-installed users in NetInfo Manager.app, or by
          running <code>niutil -list . /users</code>
          </li>
          <li>If you do decide to delete these users, be very careful of how
          you go about it. Using the "System Preferences: Users" pane (on 10.2.x) or "System Preferences: Accounts" pane (on 10.3.x) will assign all of their files to a random administrator account, and
          there have been reports of havoc played with the administrator
          account's permissions. This is a bug with System Preferences, and
          has been submitted to Apple. A safer way to remove these users from
          your system is to do so from within NetInfo Manager.app or use the
          command line tool <code>niutil</code> in Terminal. Read the man page
          for <code>niutil</code> for more information about NetInfo.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fink <em>does</em> request permission to install these additional
        users on your system during the installation of the passwd package, so
        this should not have come as a surprise.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="compile-myself">
      <question>
        <p>How do I compile something myself using Fink-installed
        software?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <!-- TODO: maybe change this to use LIBRARY_PATH / DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH ? -->
        <p>When compiling something yourself outside of Fink, the compiler and
        linker need to be told where to find the Fink-installed libraries and
        headers. For a package that uses standard configure/make process, you
        need to set some environment variables:</p>
        <p>-tcsh-</p>
        <codeblock>setenv CFLAGS -I/sw/include 
setenv LDFLAGS -L/sw/lib 
setenv CXXFLAGS $CFLAGS 
setenv CPPFLAGS $CXXFLAGS 
setenv ACLOCAL_FLAGS "-I /sw/share/aclocal" 
setenv PKG_CONFIG_PATH "/sw/lib/pkgconfig"</codeblock>
        <p>-bash-</p>
        <codeblock>export CFLAGS=-I/sw/include 
export LDFLAGS=-L/sw/lib 
export CXXFLAGS=$CFLAGS 
export CPPFLAGS=$CXXFLAGS 
export ACLOCAL_FLAGS="-I /sw/share/aclocal" 
export PKG_CONFIG_PATH="/sw/lib/pkgconfig"</codeblock>
        <p>It is often easiest just to add these to your startup files (e.g.
        <filename>.cshrc</filename> | <filename>.profile</filename>) so they
        are set automatically. If a package does not use these variables, you
        may need to add the "-I/sw/include" (for headers) and "-L/sw/lib" (for
        libraries) to the compile lines yourself. Some packages may use
        similar non-standard variables such as EXTRA_CFLAGS or --with-qt-dir=
        configure options. "./configure --help" will usually give you a list
        of the extra configure options.</p>
        <p>In addition, you may need to install the development headers (e.g.
        <em>foo-1.0-1-dev</em>) for the library packages that you are using,
        if they aren't already installed.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple-x11-applications-menu">
      <question>
        <p>I can't run any of my Fink-installed applications using the
        Applications menu in Apple X11.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Apple X11 doesn't keep track of the Fink environment settings,
        which means that the Applications menu doesn't have the PATH set
        correctly to find your Fink applications. The solution is to preface
        the name of a Fink-installed application with</p>
        <codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.sh ;</codeblock>
        <p>For example, if you want to run a Fink-installed GIMP, then put</p>
        <codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.sh ; gimp</codeblock>
        <p>in the Command field of your GIMP entry.</p>
        <p>You can also edit your .xinitrc file (in your user directory) and
        add:</p>
        <codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.sh</codeblock>
        <p>after the first line.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="x-options">
      <question>
        <p>I'm bewildered by the X11 options: Apple X11, XFree86, etc. What
        should I install?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>All are variants on XFree86 (they're all based on the XFree86
        code), but have some slight differences between them. There are
  different options under Panther and under Jaguar.</p>
        <p>Under Panther you have the choice between:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>     Apple's X11 (on the third disk). Don't forget to install the
  X11 SDK
  (on the XCode disk) if you want to compile programs or if you plan to
  install other X11-related Fink packages from source.</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>        4.4.x built via Fink: install the <code>xfree86</code> and
  <code>xfree86-shlibs</code> packages </p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>       X.org built via Fink: install the <code>xorg</code> and
  <code>xorg-shlibs</code> packages </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>Under Jaguar, the most popular choices, and the Fink packages to
          make them work are:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p>4.2.x built via Fink: install <code>xfree86-base</code> and
          <code>xfree86-rootless</code> or <code>xfree86-base-threaded</code>
          and <code>xfree86-rootless-threaded</code> (and the respective
          <code>-shlibs</code>)</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>4.3.x built via Fink: install the <code>xfree86</code> and
          <code>xfree86-shlibs</code> packages</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p>4.2.x from Apple (assuming you have the User + SDK packages installed): the <code>system-xfree86</code> package is automatically generated for current versions of Fink; do NOT install it. (Note that the public beta of Apple's X11 for Jaguar is no longer available, so this is only an option for you if you already have this installed, from the time in which it was available.)</p>
          </li>
        </ul>
        <p>There are other options, as well. There is a more extensive
        treatment in the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/x11/index.php">Running X11
        document</link>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="no-display">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to run an application, I get a message that says "cannot
        open display:". What do I need to do?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This error means that the system isn't connecting with your X
        display. Make sure you do the following:</p>
        <p>1. Start X (Apple's X11, XFree86, ...).</p>
        <p>2. Make sure your DISPLAY environment variable is set correctly. If
        you are using the default setup for X, you can do this with</p>
        <codeblock>setenv DISPLAY :0</codeblock>
        <p>if you are running <code>tcsh</code>, or</p>
        <codeblock>export DISPLAY=:0</codeblock>
        <p>if you're running <code>bash</code>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="suggest-package">
      <question>
        <p>I don't see my favorite program in Fink. How do I suggest a new
        package for inclusion in Fink?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Make the request on the <link url="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/?atid=371315&amp;group_id=17203">Package
        Request Tracker</link> on the Fink project page.</p>
        <p>Note that you must have a SourceForge id to do so.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="virtpackage">
      <!-- FAQ usage-general.virtpackage is coded into VirtPackage.pm
         Do not rename, remove, move to a different chapter, or
         otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
      <question>
        <p>What are all these <code>system-*</code> "virtual
	  packages" that are sometimes present, but that I can't
	  seem to install or remove myself?</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>
	  Packages with names like <code>system-perl</code> are
	  placeholder packages. These do not contain actual files, but
	  merely serve as a mechanism for fink to know about programs
	  that have been installed manually outside of fink.
	</p>
        <p>
	  Starting with the 10.3 distribution, most placeholders
	  aren't even real packages that you can install and remove.
	  Instead, they are "Virtual Packages", package data
	  structures generated by the fink program itself in response
	  to a preconfigured list of manually installed programs. For
	  each virtual package, fink checks for certain files in
	  certain locations, and if they are found, considers that
	  virtual package "installed".
	</p>
        <p>
	  You can run the program <code>fink-virtual-pkgs</code>
	  (part of the fink package) to get a listing of exactly what
	  fink thinks is installed. Adding the <code>--debug</code>
	  flag will give lots of diagnostic information about exactly
	  what files fink is checking.
	</p>
        <p>
	  Unfortunately, there is no mechanism by which you can
	  install an arbitrary program yourself (outside of fink) and
	  have fink recognize that program rather than trying to
	  install its own version of it. It's just too difficult in
	  the general case to be able to check configure and compiler
	  flags, pathnames, etc.
	</p>
        <p>
	  Here are the most important virtual packages that fink
	  defines (as of fink-0.19.2):
	</p>
        <ul>
          <li>system-perl: [virtual package representing perl]
	    <p>
	      Represents <filename>/usr/bin/perl</filename>, which is
	      part of the default OS X installation. This package also
	      provides <code>system-perlXXX</code> and
	      <code>perlXXX-core</code> according to the version X.X.X
	      of that perl interpreter.
	    </p>
          </li>
          <li>system-javaXXX: [virtual package representing Java X.X.X]
	    <p>
	      Represents the Java Runtime Environment, which is part of OS
	      X (and Apple's Software Update). See
	      <link url="http://www.apple.com/java">Apple's Java
	      page</link> for more information.
	    </p>
          </li>
          <li>system-javaXXX-dev: [virtual package representing Java X.X.X development headers]
	    <p>
	      Represents the Java SDK, which must be manually
	      downloaded from <link url="http://connect.apple.com">connect.apple.com</link>
	      (free registration required) and installed. If you have
	      updated your Java Runtime Environment, your SDK may not
	      be updated automatically (and may even be deleted!).
	      Remember to check for (and download and install if
	      necessary) the SDK after installing or upgrading your
	      Runtime Environment. See also <xref chapter="comp-general" section="system-java">this FAQ
	      entry</xref>.
	    </p>
          </li>
          <li>system-java3d: [virtual package representing Java3D]</li>
          <li>system-javaai: [virtual package representing Java Advanced Imaging]
	    <p>
	      Represent Java extensions for 3D graphics and image
	      processing, which must be manually downloaded from Apple
	      and installed. See <link url="http://docs.info.apple.com/article.html?artnum=120289">Apple'
	      webpage</link> for more information.
	    </p>
          </li>
          <li>system-xfree86: [placeholder for user installed x11]</li>
          <li>system-xfree86-shlibs: [placeholder for user installed x11 shared libraries]
	    <p>
	      Represent Apple's X11/XDarwin, an optional part of OS X
	      (X11User.pkg). These packages provide <code>x11</code>
	      and <code>x11-shlibs</code>, respectively. See
	      also <xref chapter="comp-packages" section="cant-install-xfree">this FAQ entry</xref>.
	    </p>
          </li>
          <li>system-xfree86-dev [placeholder for user installed x11 development tools]
	    <p>
	      Represents Apple's X11/XDarwin SDK, an optional part of
	      OS X (X11SDK.pkg). This package provides
	      <code>x11-dev</code>. See also <xref chapter="comp-packages" section="cant-install-xfree">this FAQ entry</xref>.
	    </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
  <chapter filename="usage-packages">
    <!-- FAQs in usage-packages are coded into VirtPackage.pm
       Do not rename, remove, or otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
    <title>Package Usage Problems - Specific Packages</title>
    <shorttitle>Usage (2)</shorttitle>
    <faqentry name="xmms-quiet">
      <question>
        <p>I get no sound from XMMS</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Make sure you have the "eSound Output Plugin" selected in the XMMS
        preferences. For some strange reason, it selects the disk writer
        plugin as the default.</p>
        <p>If you still get no sound output or XMMS complains that it can't
        find your sound card try this:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Make sure you haven't muted sound output in Mac OS X.</li>
          <li>Run <code>esdcat /usr/libexec/config.guess</code> (or any other
          file of a decent size). If you hear a short noise, eSound works and
          XMMS should work too if it's configured correctly. If you don't hear
          anything, esd isn't working for some reason. You can try to start it
          up manually with <code>esd &amp;</code> and watch the messages.</li>
          <li>If it still doesn't work, check the permissions on
          <code>/tmp/.esd</code> and <code>/tmp/.esd/socket</code>. Those
          should have your normal user account as the owner. If they aren't
          owned by you, kill esd if it's running, remove the directory as root
          (<code>sudo rm -rf /tmp/.esd</code>), then start esd again (as a
          normal user, not as root).</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Note that esd is designed to be run by a normal user, not by root.
        It usually communicates via the file system socket
        <code>/tmp/.esd/socket</code>. You only need the <code>-tcp</code> and
        <code>-port</code> switches if you want to run esd clients on another
        machine over the network.</p>
        <p>There have also been reports of XMMS crashing or freezing on 10.1.
        We don't have an analysis or a fix yet.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="nedit-window-locks">
      <question>
        <p>If I am editing a file in nedit, when I open another file its
        window pops up but is unresponsive.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is a known problem that occurs with recent versions of
        <filename>nedit</filename> and <filename>lesstif</filename> on all
        platforms. The workaround is to open a new window with File--&gt;New,
        then open the next file you want to work on.</p>
        <p>This is now fixed in <filename>nedit-5.3-6</filename>, which
        depends on <filename>openmotif3</filename> rather than
        <filename>lesstif</filename>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="xdarwin-start">
      <question>
        <p>Help! When I start XDarwin, it immediately quits!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Don't Panic. The Running X11 document now has an extensive <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/x11/trouble.php#immediate-quit">troubleshooting
        section</link> for this common problem.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="no-server">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to start XDarwin I get the message "xinit: No such file
        or directory (errno 2): no server "/usr/X11R6/bin/X" in PATH".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>First, make sure you are sourcing init.sh in your X startup
        <code>~/.xinitrc</code>.</p>
        <p>In Jaguar, sometimes all of the <code>xfree86</code> packages get
        built, but only <code>xfree86-base</code> and
        <code>xfree86-base-shlibs</code> are installed. Check whether you have
        <code>xfree86-rootless</code> and <code>xfree86-rootless-shlibs</code>
        installed. If not, then <code>fink install xfree86-rootless</code>
        should do the trick.</p>
        <p>If you do have it installed, then try <code>fink rebuild
        xfree86-rootless</code>. If that doesn't work, verify that you have
        <code>/usr/bin/X11R6</code> in your PATH.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <!--
<faqentry name="xfree-keymapping" >
#<question>
<p>I just upgraded to MacOS X 10.1 and now XFree86 always quits immediately. In the messages it says &quot;assert failed on line 454 of darwinKeyboard.c!&quot;. What's wrong?</p>
</question>
<answer>
	<p>This is a known problem on 10.1. You must use the &quot;Load from file&quot; keymapping option since the default option (loading it from the kernel) doesn't work anymore. The setting is in the XDarwin Preferences dialog. Be sure that a file is selected (e.g. USA.keymapping) - simply activating the check box may not be sufficient with some versions. If you can't get to the Preferences dialog because you disabled all splash screens, you can delete <code>~/Library/Preferences/org.xfree86.XDarwin.plist</code> to get it back, then start XDarwin and go to the Preferences dialog while the splash screen is displayed. Alternatively, you can edit that file manually in a text editor to enable the keymapping option (the UseKeymappingFile and KeymappingFile bits). </p>
<p>As a last resort, you can run <code>startx -x- -quartz -keymap
USA.keymapping</code> from Terminal.app.
If this still doesn't work, you have another problem in addition to
the keymapping problem that prevents XDarwin from starting.
You'll get a bunch of diagnostic messages in Terminal.app to help you
sort this out.
</p>
</answer>
</faqentry>
-->
    <faqentry name="xterm-error">
      <question>
        <p>xterm fails with "dyld: xterm Undefined symbols: xterm undefined
        reference to _tgetent expected to be defined in
        /usr/lib/libSystem.B.dylib".</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is caused by using a 10.1 version of XFree86 on 10.2. You must
        upgrade to a 10.2 version.</p>
        <p>If you are using the Fink <code>xfree86</code> packages, then you
        can get an upgrade by the usual means ("<code>fink selfupdate-cvs ;
        fink update-all</code>" for installation from source, "<code>fink
        selfupdate ; sudo apt-get update; sudo apt-get dist-upgrade</code>"
        for installation from binaries.</p>
        <p>If you have installed XFree86 by other means, you can find patches
        to bring you up to date at the <link url="http://mrcla.com/XonX">XonX
        web site</link>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="libXmuu">
      <question>
        <p>When I try to start XFree86 I get one of the following errors:
        "dyld: xinit can't open library: /usr/X11R6/lib/libXmuu.1.dylib" or
        "dyld: xinit can't open library: /usr/X11R6/lib/libXext.6.dylib"</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You are missing a file that is supposed to be installed by
        <code>xfree86-base-(threaded)-shlibs</code>. You should reinstall it
        using <code>fink reinstall xfree86-base-shlibs</code> (<code>fink
        reinstall xfree86-base-threaded-shlibs</code> if you are using the
        threaded XFree86 packages) for source, or <code>sudo apt-get install
        --reinstall xfree86-base-shlibs</code> for binaries.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple-x-bugs">
      <question>
        <p>I had Fink's XFree86 installed, and I've replaced it with Apple's
        X11, and now everything's crashing!</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>First of all, if you previously had the "threaded" versions of
        Fink's XFree86 packages installed, you may need to rebuild the
        application that is crashing. Some programs check for the availability
        of threading at build time, and then from then on believe that
        threading is available to them.</p>
        <p>Secondly, you may have just hit an Apple X11 bug. As of the time of
        this writing, a number of bugs are known by the Apple team and are
        being worked on.</p>
        <p>If you have general questions regarding Apple's X11 that are not
        really related to Fink, you may want to check <link url="http://www.lists.apple.com/x11-users">Apple's official discussion
        list on X11</link>. They also have also recommended that bugs in X11
        be <link url="http://developer.apple.com/bugreporter">submitted to the
        Apple bug reporter</link>.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple-x-delete">
      <question>
        <p>I want the delete key in Apple's X11.app to behave like that in
        XDarwin.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Some users have reported that the behavior of the
        <code>delete</code> key is different between XDarwin and Apple X11.
        This can be rectified by adding lines to the appropriate X startup
        files:</p>
        <p>
          <em>.Xmodmap:</em>
        </p>
        <codeblock>keycode 59 = Delete</codeblock>
        <p>
          <em>.Xresources:</em>
        </p>
        <codeblock>xterm*.deleteIsDEL: true 
xterm*.backarrowKey: false
xterm*.ttyModes: erase ^?</codeblock>
        <p>
          <em>.xinitrc</em>
        </p>
        <codeblock>xrdb -load $HOME/.Xresources 
xmodmap $HOME/.Xmodmap</codeblock>
        <p></p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="gnome-two">
      <question>
        <p>I upgraded from GNOME 1.x to GNOME 2.x and now
        <code>gnome-session</code> won't open a window manager.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>While under GNOME 1.x <code>gnome-session</code> invokes the
        <code>sawfish</code> window manager automatically, under GNOME 2.x,
        you'll have to call a window manager in <code>~/.xinitrc</code> before
        running <code>gnome-session</code>, e.g.:</p>
        <codeblock>... 
exec metacity &amp; exec gnome-session</codeblock>
        <p>Note:  this is no longer true for <em>GNOME 2.4</em>.  Running <filename>gnome-session</filename> invokes a window manager.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple-x11-no-windowbar">
      <question>
        <p>I upgraded to Apple's X11 in Panther and now my window title bars
        are missing.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You didn't upgrade X11 to version "X11 1.0 - XFree86 4.3.0"
        included with Panther. You can install X11 from X11.pkg on Disk 3.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="apple-x11-wants-xfree86">
      <!-- FAQ comp-general.apple-x11-wants-xfree86 is coded into VirtPackage.pm
         Do not rename, remove, move to a different chapter, or
         otherwise cause the URL to change. -->
      <question>
        <p>I installed Apple's X11 but Fink keeps asking to install
        XFree86 or X.org.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There are two possibilities to consider.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <em>You are installing from binaries:</em>
            <p>If you have a current version of <code>fink</code> (&gt;=0.18.3-1), typically what you need to do is reinstall the X11User package, since the installer application occasionally misses installing a file.  You may need to do this multiple times. Running</p>
	    <codeblock>fink list -i system-xfree86</codeblock>
	    <p>should show that the <code>system-xfree86</code> and <code>system-xfree86-shlibs</code> packages are installed. If reinstalling the X11User package doesn't work, then consult the <xref section="special-x11-debug">special debug</xref> instructions, below.</p>
            <p>If you are running an earlier version of the <code>fink</code> package, then updating <code>fink</code> may solve your problem immediately, e.g. via</p>
            <codeblock>sudo apt-get update
sudo apt-get install fink</codeblock>
          </li>
          <li>
            <em>You are installing from source:</em>
	    <p>If you have a current version of <code>fink</code>, then typically this error means that you need to (re)install the X11SDK, which is <em>mandatory</em> if you want to build packages from source. It is on the Panther Xcode CD or in the XCode Tools folder of a TIger DVD, and is <em>not</em> installed by default when you install XCode on Panther--it has to be installed either with a custom Xcode install, or by clicking on the <filename>X11SDK pkg</filename> icon in the <filename>Packages</filename> folder of the XCode CD.  It <em> is</em>, on the other hand, installed by default when you install Xcode on Tiger (even if X11User isn't present), but it's still possible for the Installer program to miss a file.  </p><p>If your computer didn't come with XCode media, then a disk image for it, containing <filename>X11SDK.pkg</filename> among other things, is quite likely present on your computer somewhere--check for a directory like <filename> /Applications/Installers </filename> for an XCode disk image.  <filename>X11User.pkg</filename> may be present in that directory as well. </p>
	    <p>If you are still having problems, run </p>
            <codeblock>fink list -i system-xfree86  </codeblock>
            <p>It should show the <code>system-xfree86</code>, <code>system-xfree86-shlibs</code>, and <code>system-xfree86-dev</code> packages as installed.  If the <code>-dev</code> package is missing, reinstall the X11SDK, since sometimes the Apple Installer misses a file.  You may need to keep doing this.  If either of the other two are missing, then reinstall the X11User package (same reason).</p>
            <p>
              <em>Note for Jaguar (X11 beta 3) users</em>:  As you aren't using XCode, you need to have already downloaded a copy of the proper X11SDK package on your system.  Since X11 beta 3 is expired, its X11SDK package (as well as the X11User package) is no longer available for download.  You'll either have to restrict yourself to installing X11 applications via the binary distribution, install XFree86 or X.org, or update to Panther.</p>
            <p>If you are running a version of <filename>fink</filename> prior to 0.17 then you should update
          <code>fink</code>, e.g. via a </p>
            <codeblock>fink selfupdate</codeblock>(assuming that you have either CVS or rsync updating turned on and aren't just using point releases).<p>If you're still having problems, then consult the <xref section="special-x11-debug">special debug</xref> instructions, below.</p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="wants-xfree86-on-upgrade">
      <question>
        <p>I switched from the 10.2 Fink version to 10.2-gcc3.3 or 10.3, I have Apple's X11, and Fink asks me to install XFree86 or X.org.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>You may need to remove one of the old place-holder packages: <filename>system-xfree86</filename>, <filename>system-xfree86-42</filename>, or <filename>system-xfree86-43</filename>.  Fink now figures out if you have a manually installed X11 flavor, e.g. Apple's, and generates virtual packages. Because other packages depend on <filename>system-xfree86</filename>, you must use the command</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-all system-xfree86 system-xfree86-42 system-xfree86-43</codeblock>
        <p>to remove the out-of-date versions.

You can check your installation by running</p>
        <codeblock>fink list -i system-xfree86</codeblock>
        <p>and checking to see that the <code>system-xfree86</code> and <code>system-xfree86-shlibs</code> packages are present.  If you installed the X11SDK, then you should also see <code>system-xfree86-dev</code>.</p>
        <p>If you are still having problems then refer to the <xref section="apple-x11-wants-xfree86">Fink wants XFree86 or X.org</xref> entry, above.</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="special-x11-debug">
      <question>
        <p>I'm still having problems with X11 and Fink.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>If the hints in the  <xref section="apples-x11-wants-xfree86">Fink tries to install XFree86 or X.org</xref> or <xref section="wants-xfree86-on-upgrade">X11 and upgrade from 10.2</xref> entries don't help, or aren't applicable to your situation, you may need to flush out your X11 installation and remove any old placeholders and partially/fully installed X11-related packages:</p>
        <codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-all system-xfree86 system-xfree86-42 system-xfree86-43 \
xorg xorg-shlibs xfree86 xfree86-shlibs \
xfree86-base xfree86-base-shlibs xfree86-rootless xfree86-rootless-shlibs \
xfree86-base-threaded xfree86-base-threaded-shlibs \
xfree86-rootless-threaded xfree86-rootless-threaded-shlibs
rm -rf /Library/Receipts/X11SDK.pkg /Library/Receipts/X11User.pkg
fink selfupdate; fink index</codeblock>
        <p>(the first line may give you warnings about trying to remove nonexistent packages).  Then, reinstall Apple's X11 (and the X11SDK, if needed), or an alternative X11 implementation, like XFree86 or X.org.</p>
        <p>If you are still having problems and you are running
        <code>fink-0.19.0</code> or later then you can run</p>
        <codeblock>fink-virtual-pkgs --debug</codeblock>
        <p>to get information about what's missing.</p>
        <p>If you are running an earlier version of <code>fink</code>, then
        there is a Perl script (courtesy of Martin Costabel) that you can
        download and run to get the same information.</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Get it here: <link url="http://perso.wanadoo.fr/costabel/fink-x11-debug">http://perso.wanadoo.fr/costabel/fink-x11-debug</link>
          </li>
          <li>Save it wherever you like.</li>
          <li>Run it in a terminal window via <codeblock>perl fink-x11-debug</codeblock>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="tiger-gtk">
      <question>
        <p>After updating to Tiger (OS 10.4), whenever I use a GTK app, I get errors involving <code>_EVP_idea_cbc</code>.</p>
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>This is caused by an apparent bug in Tiger's dynamic linker (current as of 10.4.1), but looks to be fixed in 10.4.3, and Fink has had a workaround in the guise of <code>base-files-1.9.7-1</code> or later.</p>
<p>If you haven't updated Tiger and/or <code>base-files</code> yet, you can work around this issue by prefixing the name of the software you want to run as follows:
</p>
        <codeblock>env DYLD_FALLBACK_LIBRARY_PATH=: </codeblock>
        <p>E.g., if you want to use <code>gnucash</code>, you'd use</p>
        <codeblock>env DYLD_FALLBACK_LIBRARY_PATH=: gnucash</codeblock>
        <p>This method works for applications that are launched via the Application Menu in Apple's X11 as well as a terminal.</p>
        <p>You may find it preferable to set this globally (e.g. in your startup script, and/or in your <code>.xinitrc</code>, which you may need to do to run GNOME).  Put</p>
        <codeblock>export DYLD_FALLBACK_LIBRARY_PATH=:</codeblock>
        <p>in your <code>.xinitrc</code> (regardless of your login shell) or your <code>.profile</code> (or other startup script) for <em>bash</em> users and:</p>
        <codeblock>setenv DYLD_FALLBACK_LIBRARY_PATH :</codeblock>
        <p>is the corresponding command to use in e.g. your <code>.cshrc</code> file for <em>tcsh</em> users.</p>
	<p>Note:  this will automatically be done if you install a recent enough <code>base-files</code>.
	</p>
      </answer>
    </faqentry>
    <faqentry name="yelp">
    	<question><p>I can't get the help to work for any GNOME application.</p></question>
	<answer><p>You need to install the <code>yelp</code> package.  This package was not placed within the GNOME bundle because it uses cryptography, and it was decided not to place all of GNOME in the crypto tree just to use the help system.</p></answer>
    </faqentry>
  </chapter>
</document>
