<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!-- <!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "finkdoc.dtd"> -->

<document filename="index">
<title>The Fink F.A.Q.</title>
<shorttitle>F.A.Q.</shorttitle>
<cvsid>$Id: faq.xml,v 1.5 2001/07/01 06:34:44 chrisp Exp $</cvsid>

<preface>
<p>This is the list of frequently asked questions about Fink. Like
in most FAQs, some questions are taken from real life and some are
made up. It's really more like a documentation written in an ad-hoc,
question and answer style.</p>
<p>The FAQ consists of several pages, one for each section. All
questions are listed and linked in the table of contents below.</p>
</preface>


<chapter filename="general">
<title>General Questions</title>
<shorttitle>General</shorttitle>

<faqentry name="what"><question><p>What is Fink?</p></question>
<answer><p>Fink is actually two things in one (doesn't that sound great?
;-) ) - a compile-from-source package manager and a distribution of
Unix software for Mac OS X. The package manager is built on top of
dpkg, the binary package manager written by the <link
url="http://www.debian.org/">Debian GNU/Linux</link> project. (Older
versions of Fink used GNU stow.)</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="naming"><question><p>What does the name Fink stand for?</p></question>
<answer><p>Nothing, it's just a name. It's not even an acronym.</p>
<p>Well, actually Fink is the German name for Finch, a kind of
bird. I was looking for a name for the project, and the name of the
OS, Darwin, led me to think about Charles Darwin, the Galapagos
Islands and evolution. I remembered a piece about the so-called Darwin
Finches and their beaks from school, and well, that's it...</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="bsd-ports"><question><p>How is Fink different
from the BSD port mechanism (this includes OpenPackages and
GNU-Darwin)?</p></question>
<answer><p>Some main advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>It's written in Perl, not make/shell. Thus it doesn't rely on
special features only found in BSD make. There is no need to flag
packages that need GNU make to build.</li>
<li>dpkg provides sophisticated management for binary packages -
smooth updating, special handling for configuration files, virtual
packages and other advanced dependencies.</li>
</ul>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="usr-local"><question><p>Why doesn't Fink install into
/usr/local?</p></question>
<answer><p>There are several reasons, but the common line is "because
breakage will occur".</p>
<p>Reason One: Third-party software. /usr/local is the
well-established place to put software that is not part of the system
shipped by the original vendor. This means that it is a good place to
put stuff. However, it also means that other people will put stuff
there, too. Most install routines will just overwrite what's there -
this also applies to dpkg. One can, of course, choose not to install
third-party software in /usr/local. Unfortunately, most installers
don't tell you beforehand what they will install where.</p>
<p>Reason Two: /usr/local/bin is in the default PATH. This means that
your shell will find the install programs without additional
measures. But it also means that you do have to take additional
measures if you do not want to use the programs. In extreme cases,
this can also affect the system itself - many parts depend on shell
scripts.</p>
<p>Reason Three: The compiler tool chain searches /usr/local by
default. The compiler searches /usr/local/include for header files and
the linker searches /usr/local/lib for libraries. Again, this is
sometimes a welcome convenience, but it's very hard to disable should
the need arise. You can easily disable the compiler by putting a
garbage file called <code>stdio.h</code> into /usr/local/include.</p>
<p>All that said, it is possible to install Fink into /usr/local. The
installation script will warn you explicitly, but proceed once you
acknowledge that you're doing this at your own risk.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="why-sw"><question><p>Then why did you choose
/sw?</p></question>
<answer><p>That choice is quite arbitrary. If you have a better
suggestion, post it to the fink-devel mailing list. But you should be
aware of the arguments about /usr/local in the previous question.</p>
</answer></faqentry>



</chapter>



<chapter filename="install">
<title>Installation Questions</title>
<shorttitle>Installation</shorttitle>

<faqentry name="stow-not-found"><question><p>Installing Fink fails
with a "stow not found" message.</p></question>
<answer><p>This is a known bug in Fink 0.1.8. It is caused by missing
dependencies in the gzip and tar packages. The bug is fixed in Fink
0.1.8a. To install it, either wipe out /sw (or whatever you used) and
use install.sh again or just use upgrade.sh and install any
package. Note that you do not need the update unless you did a
first-time installation with 0.1.8.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="bzip2"><question><p>I tried to install Fink 0.2.0, but it failed to
login to cygnus (?) to get bzip. (login denied). Is there an error in
the login script?</p></question>
<answer><p>There is no "login script" in Fink. What you're seeing is not a bug
in Fink (or wget, which is used for downloading files), but an
overloaded FTP server. Later releases of Fink use a different server
to get bzip2. As a workaround, you can download bzip2-1.0.1.tar.gz
manually and place it in /sw/src, then retry installing.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="proxy"><question><p>I'm behind a firewall. How do I configure Fink
to use an HTTP proxy?</p></question>
<answer><p>Fink does not have a proxy setting because it lets <link
url="http://www.gnu.org/software/wget/wget.html">wget</link> do all the
downloading. To use a proxy, you must tell wget to use it. You can do
that by setting the environment variable http_proxy. See the
<link url="http://www.gnu.org/manual/wget/html_chapter/wget_8.html#SEC36">wget
manual</link> for details.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="head"><question><p>I'm getting a strange usage message
from the head command. What's broken?</p></question>
<answer><p>If you're seeing this:</p>
<codeblock>Unknown option: 1
Usage: head [-options] &lt;url&gt;...</codeblock>
<p>followed by a list of options, you have a broken <code>head</code>
executable.
This happens when you install the Perl libwww library on an HFS+
system volume.
It tries to create a new command <code>/usr/bin/HEAD</code>, which
overwrites the existing <code>head</code> command because the file
system is case-insensitive.
<code>head</code> is a standard command used in many shell scripts and
Makefiles.
You need to get the original <code>head</code> executable back if you
want to use Fink.
</p>
</answer></faqentry>

</chapter>



<chapter filename="usage">
<title>Usage Questions</title>
<shorttitle>Usage</shorttitle>

<faqentry name="what-packages"><question><p>How can I find out what packages Fink supports?</p></question>
<answer><p>For Fink 0.1.x, look in the fink/info directory, e.g.:</p>
<codeblock>ls /sw/fink/info</codeblock>
<p>For Fink 0.2.x, you may want to try this:</p>
<codeblock>find /sw/fink -name '*.info'</codeblock>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="unstable"><question><p>There's this package in unstable that I want
to install, but Fink just says 'no package found'. How can I install
it?</p></question>
<answer><p>First make sure you understand what 'unstable' means. Packages
in there usually have not been tested at all, many have problems or
just won't compile. That is why Fink doesn't search the unstable
tree by default.</p>
<p>If you only want one or two specific packages, it is safer
to copy those .info files (and their associated .patch files, if there
are any) from <filename>/sw/fink/dists/unstable/main/finkinfo</filename> to
<filename>/sw/fink/dists/local/main/finkinfo</filename>. If you want Fink to use all of
unstable, edit <filename>/sw/etc/fink.conf</filename> and add <literal>unstable/main</literal> to the
<literal>Trees:</literal> line.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="sudo"><question><p>I'm tired of typing my password into sudo again
and again. Is there a way around this?</p></question>
<answer><p>If you're not paranoid, you can configure sudo to not ask you for a
password. To do this, edit <filename>/etc/sudoers</filename> as root
and add a line like this:</p>
<codeblock>username  ALL = NOPASSWD: ALL</codeblock>
<p>Replace <literal>username</literal> with your actual username, of course. This
line allows you to run any command via sudo without typing your
password.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="exec-init-csh"><question><p>When I'm trying to run
init.csh, I get a "Permission denied" error. What am I doing
wrong?</p></question>
<answer><p>init.csh is not supposed to be run like normal commands. It
sets environment variables like PATH and MANPATH in your shell. To
have a lasting effect on the shell, it must be processed with the
<code>source</code> command, like this:</p>
<codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.csh</codeblock>
<p>The same goes for Bourne-type shells and init.sh.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

</chapter>



<chapter filename="packages">
<title>Problems With Certain Packages</title>
<shorttitle>Packages</shorttitle>

<faqentry name="nox"><question><p>Package foo says there is no X11 on my system!?</p></question>
<answer><p>There are several things that can cause this:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>You don't have X11 installed. You must install X11 manually,
either <link url="http://www.xfree86.org/">XFree86</link> or <link
url="http://www.tenon.com/">Xtools</link>. XFree86 packages for Fink are
under development, but not yet ready for prime time.</p></li>
<li><p>You installed the XFree86 binary distribution, but left out the
Xprog.tgz tarball. It is an optional tarball, but must be installed to
compile X11 applications.</p></li>
<li><p>You installed XFree86 4.0.2 or 4.0.3 and used ranlib on the
static libraries. Now configure scripts are failing in the
<code>checking for XOpenDisplay in -lX11</code> test. To fix this, use the
<code>-c</code> option for ranlib, i.e.:</p>
<codeblock>cd /usr/X11R6/lib
sudo ranlib -c *.a</codeblock>
<p>Note that this can't happen with more recent versions of XFree86, as
they compile the libraries (both static and shared) without common
symbols.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Hopefully, this will soon be solved with proper X11 packages and
dependencies. But don't hold your breath yet.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="icewm"><question><p>IceWM won't compile.</p></question>
<answer><p>If you get messages about undefined symbols, you have only static
X11 libraries on your system. Unfortunately, the linker is sensitive
to the order in which the libraries are listed on the command line,
and IceWM's Makefiles use the wrong order. The problem disappears when
you have shared X11 libraries. To get them, use either <link
url="http://www.tenon.com/">Tenon Xtools</link> or a CVS version of
XFree86 (which will soon be released as XFree86 4.1).</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="gnomecore"><question><p>The gnome-core package won't compile. It
complains about multiple definitions of _login_tty. What's
wrong?</p></question>
<answer><p>The problem with this is actually the configure script in
gnome-libs. It fails to detect that Darwin has the login_tty() and
openpty() functions because they are in the system library, not in
libutil. It goes ahead and compiles replacements, which causes these
duplicate symbol errors. This has been fixed in Fink 0.2.0 and
later. A workaround is to create a symlink in
<filename>/usr/lib</filename>, like this:</p>
<codeblock>cd /usr/lib
sudo ln -s libSystem.dylib libutil.dylib</codeblock>
<p>Then rebuild the gnome-libs and gnome-core packages.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="qt"><question><p>Qt won't compile.</p></question>
<answer><p>Qt is one of the packages that will only compile when
shared X11 libraries are present. Unfortunately, it spits some quite
confusing error messages when it encounters static libraries.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="nedit"><question><p>nedit is broken.</p></question>
<answer><p>If you're seeing <code>Xm/BulletinB.h: No such file or
directory</code> in the error messages, that's because you have Xtools
installed. Xtools includes OpenMotif, but unfortunately Tenon forgot
to include some required header files. There is no workaround yet, and
it is unknown whether this is fixed in recent releases on Xtools.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

<faqentry name="sawfish"><question><p>Sawfish can't find rep-gtk.</p></question>
<answer><p>You need shared X11 libraries for rep-gtk to build correctly. It
doesn't build dynamically loadable modules when only static X11
libraries are available. The problem doesn't actually show until the
sawfish configure script tries to use rep-gtk.</p>
</answer></faqentry>

</chapter>


</document>
