<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "finknews.dtd">
<news lang="en">
<cvsid>$Id: news.en.xml,v 1.23 2005/06/09 15:39:01 dmrrsn Exp $</cvsid>


<newsitem>
<date>2005-06-09</date>
<headline>New Fink releases.</headline>
<body>
<p>
Three new Fink releases are 
<varlink url="download/index.php">available</varlink>
 today: version 0.8.0 (for 10.4),
version 0.7.2 (for 10.3), and version 0.6.4 (for 10.2).
All three releases include source files, binary packages, and a Fink
installer for new users.
</p>
<p>
The new release for 10.4 includes all currently-available "stable" packages
in source and binary form: there are 1565 of these, which constitutes more
than 80% of the 1909 packages available in the 10.3 release.  Work continues
by the fink developers on bringing more of the stable packages to Tiger.
</p>
<p>
The new release for 10.2 will be the last official release for that
version of Mac OS X.  Although no further updates (not even security
updates) will be provided by the Fink team, we anticipate that the
0.6.4 release will be usable for years to come.
</p>
<p>
Users upgrading to 10.4 can now simply issue a 
<code>fink selfupdate</code> command, followed by
<code>sudo /sw/lib/fink/postinstall.pl</code> (for first-time updaters
on 10.4), <code>fink scanpackages</code> and <code>sudo apt-get update</code>.
We don't recommend bootstrapping at the moment, since bootstrapping does
not work with the newly-released XCode 2.1 from Apple.
</p>

</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2005-04-29</date>
<headline>Fink and Tiger.</headline>
<body>
<p>
Fink can be used on OS X 10.4!  There are several ways you can update:
</p><ul>
<li>
A binary installer will be available within a few weeks, for binary-only
users.  In the meantime, new users should bootstrap fink 0.23.10, just
as stable users, below.
</li><li>
For users of the stable tree, we recommend that you delete your current
fink with <code>sudo rm -Rf /sw</code> and then "bootstrap" an
installation of fink-0.23.10 using
<varlink 
url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=17203&amp;package_id=13043&amp;release_id=326600">
fink-0.23.10.tar.gz</varlink>--download that file and expand it, 
eg. via
<code>tar -xvzf fink-0.23.10.tar.gz</code>.  After running the command
<code> ./bootstrap.sh </code> in the resulting
<filename>fink-0.23.10</filename> directory,
you'll need to run <code>fink selfupdate</code>
</li><li>
For users of the unstable tree, you may be able to upgrade just by running 
<code>fink selfupdate</code> if your version of fink is less than 0.24.6.  
It will install fink-0.24.6 for you.  After upgrading to 10.4, first check 
that you have the right version of fink by issuing <code>fink --version</code>
.  If your version is less than 0.24.6, run <code>fink selfupdate</code> to 
get the right version of fink.  Then, whether you selfupdated or not, 
reinstall the fink package using <code>fink rebuild fink</code>, 
and follow that with another <code>fink selfupdate</code>.
</li>
</ul>
<p>Not all packages are working yet under 10.4, but that situation will
improve over the next several weeks.  The stable tree contains substantially
fewer packages than in 10.3, but all of them should compile.
</p>
<p>Of course, some wrinkles still need to be ironed out.  We encourage 
users with mission-critical applications to check in on the mailing 
lists to verify whether anyone has had experience with the package in 
question before upgrading.</p>

</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2004-11-20</date>
<headline>Solution to gcc problems.</headline>
<body>
<p>
Apple has released the November 2004 gcc3 updater, available (upon free 
registration) at connect.apple.com.  This updater fixes the problems with
the gcc3 compiler in XCode 1.5.  If you are using XCode 1.5, you should 
install this updater.  (The updater will update correctly for users with
an untouched XCode 1.5, and also for users who installed the workaround which
the fink project had previously recommended.)
</p><p>
We would like to thank Apple for responding to our reports about this
matter, and working to resolve it as quickly as possible.
</p>


</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2004-10-15</date>
<headline>Workaround for gcc problems.</headline>
<body>
<p>
The version of gcc included with XCode 1.5 is known to produce 
incorrect output from c++ code under certain circumstances.
Fink now has a mechanism to warn users about this, and Fink will soon
refuse
to use the "broken" gcc to compile packages which are known to
have this problem.
</p><p>
If you have already upgraded XCode to version 1.5, there is a workaround,
described <link url="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.os.apple.fink.beginners/13580"> here </link>
and <link url="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.os.apple.fink.beginners/14200"> here </link>.
</p><p> If you have not yet upgraded, you should consider remaining with
XCode version 1.2 until the problem has been resolved.
</p>


</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2004-09-20</date>
<headline>Fink 0.7.1 released.</headline>
<body>
<p>
The latest Fink release, version 0.7.1 (for 10.3),
is now available for both source and binary users. This release is meant for Panther (10.3)  based
Mac OS X versions.  The 0.6.3 release remains available for Jaguar (10.2) based Mac OS X versions. 
</p>

<p>
This new release incorporates various fixes to the package manager, 
and many previously
unavailable binary packages have been added resulting in a total of 1650 binary packages. This includes
binaries for KDE 3.1.4 and GNOME 2.4.
</p>

<p>
To complete a new Fink installation you should follow the instructions posted
<varlink url="download/index.php">here</varlink>.
You may upgrade your existing Fink to the latest Fink using your current installation.

A full list of the differences between 0.7.0 and 0.7.1 can be viewed by visiting this

<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/pdb/compare.php?tree1=0.7.1-stable&amp;cmp=0&amp;tree2=0.7.0-stable&amp;splitoffs=on&amp;sort=name">page.</link>
</p>

<p>
If you have questions or problems, please try the Fink mailing lists.  You can learn more about them
<varlink url="lists/index.php">here</varlink>.
</p>

<p>
Please make sure you pick the <em>appropriate installer</em> for your platform.
Fink 0.6.3 will only install on Mac OS X 10.2.*, while Fink 0.7.1 will only install on Mac OS X 10.3.*
</p>

        <p>
The Fink Team would like to thank its many contributors, frequent helpers
and developers for making this release happen.
We also thank our community for downloading the prior release 0.7.0 more than 130,000 times. 
Without their constant support and valuable pointers, Fink would not be where we are now.
</p>

</body>
</newsitem>




<newsitem>
	<date>2004-08-23</date>
	<headline>Problems with XCode 1.5</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	In the past few days, there have been reports that some fink packages 
	do not compile correctly using XCode 1.5.  If you have not already
	upgraded to XCode 1.5, we suggest that you wait until this issue
	is resolved before doing so.
	</p><p>
	If you are having problems with a package which compiled under
	XCode 1.2 but does not compile correctly under XCode 1.5, 
	please report the package to
	the fink-devel mailing list.  (The usual symptom is: some symbols
	are  missing after compiling with g++.)  
	Packages already known to have this problem include
	octave, singular-factory, singular-libfac, and possibly sdl.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-08-21</date>
	<headline>Error in fink-0.22.0</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	The fink-0.22.0 package manager, which was available briefly in the 
	unstable tree this past week, had a bug which prevents further
	updating via rsync.  If you installed this version of fink, you
	can recover by running the command 
	<code>fink install fink-0.21.2-1</code> which will downgrade fink
	to the version in the stable tree, and subsequently running
	<code>fink selfupdate</code>
	</p><p>
	If for any reason those commands don't work, go to 
	<link url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=17203">the 
	fink file release page at sourceforge</link> and download the
	file <code>fink-0.22.1.tar.gz</code> (or a more recent, i.e.,
	higher numbered, version).  Unpack this file with
	<code>tar xfz fink-0.22.1.tar.gz</code> , and then from within the
	fink-0.22.1 directory, run the command <code>./inject.pl</code>
	</p>
	<p>
	The fink team apologizes for the error, and thanks the user 
	community for bringing it to our attention quickly.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-08-01</date>
	<headline>Improving our mirrors. Can you help?</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	Fink's decision to gradually build its own network of mirrors
	has paid off. To make sure that we can continue to offer
	a high quality service we need to improve our mirror network.
	It has been some time since we last asked for more mirrors. 
	It is time to do so again. Fink is very grateful for the resources 
	granted to us by our community. To further improve our service to the 
	community we require an even better mirror system. We especially lack 
	mirrors in central Europe, Russia and the Far East. If you feel that 
	you have at least two Mbit to spare for a rsync mirror, or more to offer 
	a distfiles mirror, please <link url="mailto:mirrors@finkmirrors.net">contact us</link>.
	</p>
	<p>
	 To get a better understanding of the different types of mirrors 
	 Fink offers, please review <link url="http://finkmirrors.net/">finkmirrors.net</link>. This is the official homepage for all mirror related issues.
	 If you feel that you can offer other types of resources, 
	 web-space for testing as an example, please do not hesitate in <link url="mailto:mirrors@finkmirrors.net">contacting us</link> as well.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-04-06</date>
	<headline>Fink 0.6.3 and 0.7.0 released.</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
The latest Fink releases, version 0.6.3 (for 10.2) and 0.7.0 (for 10.3), 
are now available for both source and binary users.  The 0.6.3 release has 
been built on <em>10.2</em>, while release 
0.7.0 has been built on <em>10.3</em>. This should facilitate better support for the different platforms. 
	</p>
	<p>
These new releases incorporate various fixes to the package manager, many previously 
unavailable binary packages have been added and problematic packages for 10.3 users have been rebuilt. 
	</p>
	<p>
To complete a new Fink installation you should follow the instructions posted 
<varlink url="download/index.php?phpLang=en">here</varlink>.
You may upgrade your existing Fink installation to the latest Fink release by following the instructions posted <varlink url="download/upgrade.php?phpLang=en">here</varlink>.

If you have questions or problems, please try the Fink mailing lists you can learn more about them 
<varlink url="lists/index.php?phpLang=en">here</varlink>.
		</p>
		<p>
Please make sure you pick the <em>appropriate installer</em> for your Platform.
Fink 0.6.3 will only install on Mac OS X 10.2.* while Fink 0.7.0 will only install on Mac OS X 10.3.* 
		</p>
	<p>
The Fink Team would like to thank its many contributors, frequent helpers 
and developers for making this release happen. 
We also thank our community, without their constant support and valuable 
pointers Fink would not be where we are now.. 

</p>

</body>
</newsitem>
	


<newsitem>
	<date>2004-02-19</date>
	<headline>Raise your Flag.</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
Thanks to Baba Yoshihiko, Fink has now taken the necessary steps to allow for 
internationalisation efforts. 
The improved infrastructure enables us to display a multilingual web-site to our visitors from all over the world. 
</p>
<p>
This also means that we need volunteers. The Fink web-site needs to be translated into the language of your choice. 
A translation into Japanese is being worked on and the translation into French has been taken over by Michele Garoche. 
Which language are you willing to translate?
</p>
<p>
If you are willing to become a member of the internationalisation team or wish to provide feedback on 
the web-site feel free to join the new mailing-list.
You can do so by going to our <varlink url="lists/index.php">mailing-lists page</varlink>. The full announcement on the existing 
mailing lists can be read <link url="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.os.apple.fink.devel/7554">here</link>.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
	<date>2004-02-02</date>
	<headline>Java 1.4.2 Update Removes Java SDK</headline> 
	<body>
	<p>
If you previously had Java 1.4.1 and the Java SDK installed, the new
Java 1.4.2 update from apple will upgrade the Java runtime to 1.4.2,
but will <em>remove</em> the previous 1.4.1 Java runtime and
SDK <em>without</em> upgrading the JDK.  To build Java packages in Fink
you will need to <link url="http://connect.apple.com/">go to
connect.apple.com and download the Java 1.4.2 SDK</link> (free
registration required).
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-01-18</date>
	<headline>10.3 binaries updated</headline> 
	<body>
	<p>
Many of the binary files for 10.3 have been updated, eliminating problems
with qt and kde, among others.  To access the updated files, bring your
index of binary files up-to-date by running the
command <code>sudo apt-get update</code> .  After this, you can use
apt-get, dselect or FinkCommander to install binary files as usual.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-01-10</date>
	<headline>Pssst want to install GNOME 2.4?</headline> 
	<body>
	<p>
	Thanks to the new Fink GNOME Core team, including a lot of hard work by packaging
	newcomer Keith Conger and GNOME 1.x maintainer Masanori Sekino, GNOME 2.4 has
	finally been released to the 10.3 unstable tree.
	</p>
	<p>
	It is there for the taking; please offer some of your time and test these packages
	if you are on unstable already.  Because of the massive number of changes, it is
	expected that there will be issues upgrading or installing the new GNOME.  If you
	have problems, you can reach the GNOME-savvy people at
	<link url="mailto:fink-gnome-core@lists.sourceforge.net">fink-gnome-core@lists.sourceforge.net</link>.
	Please do report success stories there as well.  The more good reports we get, the
	faster GNOME 2.4 can be moved to stable.
	</p>
	<p>
	For those of you who do not read our mailing lists, <link
	url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/lists/index.php">why aren't you subscribed yet</link>?
	Here is a link to detailed 
	<link url="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.os.apple.fink.gnome/57/match=gnome">instructions</link> 
	how to install or upgrade GNOME and what new stuff it brings.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2004-01-02</date>
	<headline>Whaaazaaap Dawgs, Two Zero Zero Four is on!</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	A happy new year to all of you from the whole team. Blame this outburst of an 
	attempt at slang language on some of us having to watch the MTV Music Awards all
   day long.
	</p>
	<p>
	Last year has been a good year for Fink. We have had hard times keeping up with 
	the changes introduces by Apple, but we also learned that we have a great community
	which is willing to go through great lengths to support us. 
	For this, we say &quot;Thank You&quot;. Much of what happens in the Fink project
   happens because of the amazing support and encouragement we get from our users.
	</p>
	<p>
	Two Zero Zero Four should not make us slow down, but speed up. There are some 
	interesting things in the pipeline, including GNOME 2.4, a new release of KDE, major 
	changes to the package manager itself, and organisational restructuring. 
	Hopefully we will advance into an even bigger project with developer conferences, 
	real life meetings, and a CD in your favourite shop.
	</p>
	<p>
	High ambitions can make one fall very deeply, thus we shall take it carefully, but 
	still we are all counting on your support during this year. Tell us what you think 
	about Fink; tell us what you like or dislike; show us ways to improve ourselves.
	Lend us your resources and sponsor a mirror or hardware. Devote some of your time
	to improve the package manager or add another piece of software by creating an
	info file. Browse this website and hopefully indulge yourself. We enjoy serving
	such a nice community; hopefully we shall make it a smooth ride for you and
	your Macintosh in Two Zero Zero Four.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-12-28</date>
	<headline>Merry Christmas and a happy new year</headline>
	<body>
		<p>
 The Fink team and I wish all of you a merry Christmas and happy Holidays. We are looking
 forward to yet another year where we can help the Macintosh community grow into the 
 world of UNIX together with Mac OS X.
 		</p>
		<p>
 We wish you all, that your hope is not too frail and that you will carry on following 
 through with your wishes. May the world we live in gradually become a better place and
 may peace and understanding settle just for a few days. 
		</p>
		<p>
 Enjoy your quiet time and in case we do not get around to saying it soon enough. 
 A happy new year to all of you, stay with us we count on your support.
		
		</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-11-30</date>
	<headline>There they are! New mirrors..</headline>
		<body>
		<p>
	Thank you, thank you, thank you. What a great community we have.
	Thank you for providing us with more mirrors. 
		</p>
		<p>
	Matthew Healey, member of the Western <link url="http://www.wamug.org.au">
	Australian</link> Macintosh User Group, and their 
	ISP <link url="http://www.extremedsl.com.au">extremedsl</link>
	are providing Fink with a full mirror in Perth, Australia. This is our first
	mirror in down under, thus I am pleased to welcome them to the family.
	Furthermore the <link url="http://www.mirror.ac.uk">UKMIRROR</link> service 
	has accepted us, making distfile services available for Fink 
	on 21 load balanced server.
		</p>
		<p>
	We are very happy about this development, but we still need more rsync mirrors.
	Thus, once more, if you feel like helping, please visit 
	<link url="http://finkmirrors.net">finkmirrors.net</link> and get in touch.
		</p>
		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-11-24</date>
	<headline>More mirrors....pretty please?</headline>
	<body>
	<p>While we welcome our latest full mirror in Norway, sponsored by Havar Valeur, 
        we crave more. To improve our service to all of you, we would like to ask that
        you evaluate carefully if you maybe do have the resources to become a mirror. 
        </p>    
        <p>     
        All it takes is a 10Mbit link, around 100MB of disk space  and some bandwidth you are 
        willing to share for Fink. The exact setup instructions for rsync mirrors can be found 
        <link url="http://finkmirrors.net/rsync.html">here</link>. Especially mirrors in
        Asia, Australia, New Zealand, South Europe and Middle Europe are welcome, since we have none in 
        those regions yet. If you feel generous and wish to donate even more resources, please visit
        <link url="http://finkmirrors.net">finkmirrors.net</link> to learn about your options.
        </p>    
        <p>     
        The current status of all available rsync mirrors can be viewed on the finkmirrors.net pages as well.
        We hope to improve this service in the future, yet this depends on your willingness to help us out. 
        We are looking forward to many new applications and thank our community in advance. 
        </p>    
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-11-17</date>
	<headline>Fink 0.6.2 released</headline>
	<body>
        <p>The latest Fink release, version 0.6.2, is now available
for both source and binary users.  This is a bug-fix release, intended
to address two problems: the dselect/user deletion bug, and a 
problem with ownership of files.  The dselect bug was addressed by
updating the fink, dpkg, and apt packages.  After updating to 0.6.2,
it is safe to once again use dselect.  However, if you ran dselect
at any time since 0.6.0, you should carefully check the integrity
of the file at <code>/sw/etc/apt/sources.list</code>.  If you have
any doubts about this file, you should replace it with
<varlink url="files/sources.list">the default sources.list file</varlink>.
</p>
<p>Users who have installed binary files from the 0.6.1 distribution
may find that certain files in their Fink installation are owned
by UID 2011 rather than by root.  To correct this problem,
run the command:</p>
<codeblock>sudo find /sw/ -user 2011 -exec chown root:admin {} \;</codeblock>
<p>This release, like the previous one, was built on OS X 10.2
using the gcc 3.3 compiler, and runs fine with some exceptions* on OS X 10.3.  Most Fink 
users who upgrade to 10.3 will continue to
want to only use the binaries from this
new distribution for now, while the Fink team continues to modify
Fink packages for 10.3.
</p>
<p>*Exceptions include: emacs, qt.
</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-11-04</date>
	<headline>User Deletion Bug/ Dselect Troubles</headline>
	<body>
<p><em>Quick Summary: DO NOT USE DSELECT,</em> and if you've used it,
check your /sw/etc/apt/sources.list file carefully.</p>
		<p>Users who have bootstrapped or installed Fink 0.5.3 or Fink 0.6.0
		on Mac OS X 10.3 could exhibit a problem where all users get deleted
		from the netinfo database, and you become unable to log in.
We believe that this problem can only occur if you've used dselect.</p>
		<p>If you are using Mac OS X 10.3, please be sure you're using the
		latest Fink version to avoid the issue.  To make sure you don't have
		upgrade problems, check your <code>/sw/etc/apt/sources.list</code>
		file.  You will need to modify it if it contains <code>deb</code>
		lines that point to "release" or "current" without a version number.
		In other words, if your <code>sources.list</code> file contains
		these lines:</p>
		<codeblock>deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download release main
deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download current main</codeblock>
		<p>...you should change them to this:</p>
		<codeblock>deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download 10.3/release main
deb http://us.dl.sourceforge.net/fink/direct_download 10.3/current main</codeblock>
		<p>We are working on updating the repository to make sure that even
		if you update you don't get the broken code, and to
repair dselect, but in the meantime,
		make sure your <code>sources.list</code> file has the correct entries.</p>
<p>Other users have experienced problems with dselect itself, particularly
complaints about a missing "darwin" package.  If you are running dselect
under 10.3 and you <em>don't</em> get this warning, then your 
<code>sources.list</code> file is likely to be corrupted and you should
repair it as above.
</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
        <date>2003-11-01</date>
        <headline>Fink 0.6.1 released</headline>
                <body>
        <p>The latest Fink release, version 0.6.1, is now available
for both source and binary users.  This release was built on OS X 10.2
using the gcc 3.3 compiler, and runs well on OS X 10.3.  Most Fink
users who upgrade to 10.3 will want to only use the binaries from this
new distribution for now, while the Fink team continues to modify
Fink packages for 10.3.
</p><p>
If you wish to access the 
new binaries, use apt-get, dselect, or the binary mode of
FinkCommander.  Unless you are interested in helping the Fink team
to test packages which are compiled on 10.3, 
do not use the command-line <code>fink</code> program to do your
installations for the
next few weeks.
</p>
<p>The simplest way to upgrade a binary installation is to run
"sudo apt-get update".  Further details and
other issues related to upgrading Fink to 10.3 are addressed on the
<varlink url="download/10.3-upgrade.php">Special 10.3 upgrade page.</varlink>
</p><p>
Before using the latest version of
the command-line <code>fink</code> program 
under OS X 10.2, be sure to install the August2003gccUpdater, available
after free registration from connect.apple.com.
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-31</date>
	<headline>Happy Halloween and welcome new mirrors</headline>
		<body>
		<p>
		We wish all of you a happy Halloween.
		</p>
		<p>
		Furthermore I would like to welcome our new mirrors to the Fink family.
		From Europe in Rijeka, Croatia a new full mirror joins us. This mirrors 
		has been sponsored by the <link url="http://mac.dir.hr/">Jabucnjak</link> Apple user group. 
		This is our first mirror in Europe, so I hope that more will be joining us 
		soon.
		</p>
		<p>
		Dave Schroeder from the <link url="http://mirror.services.wisc.edu/">University of 
		Wisconsin</link> in Madison is sponsoring a 100Mbit dedicated Master server.
		A. J. Wright and <link url="http://sunsite.utk.edu/">SunSITE@UTK</link> are helping out with 
		another full mirror in the United states. 
		</p>
		<p>
		This raises our full mirror count to four and the rsync mirror count to 
		five. We are happy to have such a great community back us up, but I know 
		that more mirrors will join over time. I will not stop nagging you until
		Fink has its own mirror in every state of the USA. Yet, with such a 
		brilliant community backing us up, I am not too worried about not
		reaching my goal very soon.
		</p>
		<p>
		Trick or treat! Our most wanted treat is more mirrors, so come forth 
		Administrators and fill our bag. Information on how you can be a mirror
		can be found on the official <link url="http://finkmirrors.net">
		mirroring website</link>.
		</p>
		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-25</date>
	<headline>Look Ma, a logo for Fink</headline>
		<body>
	<p>As you surely noticed, Fink has a logo. This is the result of our
	Logo <varlink url="logo.php">contest</varlink> held earlier this year.
	This new, official, logo has been displayed since the 24th of October and
	those of you who wondered how it has been picked and what the name of the
	winner is should read up in the PR <link url="pr/index.php">section</link>.
	</p>
	<p>
	The longer explanation also features a larger version of the logo itself,
	so that you may have a closer look at its details. We like our new logo,
	we hope that you will like it too.
	</p>
	<p>IMPORTANT: We do not yet have a formal licensing agreement for the new
   logo and so are unable to give permission to distribute it.  Currently, it
   can only be displayed on the Fink web page.  Thank you for your understanding.
	</p>
		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-24</date>
	<headline>Upgrade to gcc 3.3 and/or 10.3</headline>
		<body>
	<p>It is now possible to upgrade Fink to take full advantage of the gcc 3.3
compiler, or to use OS X 10.3 if you have that installed.  Binary packages
corresponding to these upgrades are not yet available, so if you make 
extensive use of binary packages you may wish to wait a few days before 
upgrading.
</p><p>
If you wish to perform this upgrade, and you had previously installed the
June 2003 Developer Tools update from Apple, you will need to install
the August 2003 Developer Tools update BEFORE you upgrade Fink.  Under
10.3, be sure to install XCode from the XCode disk before upgrading
Fink.
</p><p>
Running "fink selfupdate" should perform the upgrade for you.  The latest
version of the fink package manager will automatically detect which
version of OS X and which version of gcc you have installed, and will
adjust itself accordingly.
</p><p>
If you wish to do a fresh install of Fink on a 10.3 system, we recommend
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/srcdist.php">bootstrapping from
source,</link> starting from fink-full-0.6.0.tar.gz available
on fink's <link
url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=17203">sourceforge 
download page.</link>  You'll need XCode for this as
well.
</p><p>
Also note that once you have Fink version 0.15.0 or higher, you do
not need to install system-xfree86 anymore.  Fink is
capable of automatically determining your system-xfree86 version if you
don't already have any fink x11 packages installed.  If you currently
have an old system-xfree86 package of any kind installed, please run the
following:
</p>
<codeblock>sudo dpkg -r --force-all system-xfree86 system-xfree86-42 \
system-xfree86-43; fink selfupdate; fink index</codeblock>
<p>
The Fink team is still working on getting Fink packages working under 10.3,
but many many packages already work.
</p>
		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-23</date>
	<headline>Say Hello to Mirror Numero Uno</headline>
		<body>
	<p>You are too late. Rus Foster from <link url="http://www.jvds.com">JVDS</link>
	beat you all to it. He is the first one to provide us with resources 
	for a Fink rsync mirror.
	The mirror is located in Atlanta, GA and is updated every two hours, at 35 minutes past.
	</p>
	<p>For those of you who are still waiting, join in. The more mirrors we have
	the faster you can rsync your info files. As per usual, updated and current
	information on the mirror structure can be found on <link url="http://finkmirrors.net"> Finkmirrors.net </link>
	</p>
		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-22</date>
	<headline>Mirror, mirror on the wall...</headline>
		<body>
	<p>..who will mirror Fink above all? There is a new player on the turf
	and it belongs to the Fink team. <link url="http://finkmirrors.net"> Finkmirrors.net</link> tells you everything you wanted to know about mirroring Fink and its related resources on your Server. As our mirror structure will hopefully grow in the future, this web-site will also hold information about each individual mirror.
	</p>
	<p>To ensure that our service remains as stable as possible and to distribute the load imposed onto our main rsync server, we are looking for rsync mirrors or full mirrors. Those of you who are willing to share resources will find all the necessary information on <link url="http://finkmirrors.net"> Finkmirrors.net</link>. 
</p>
<p>
UPDATE: Yes, I screwed up when I initially installed the DNS records. If you cannot connect please try again later. I am very sorry for this inconvenience. Thank you for your understanding.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-10-12</date>
	<headline>New update method available</headline>
		<body>
<p>The latest version of the fink package manager offers a new update
method, <code>fink selfupdate-rsync</code>, as an alternative to the
CVS updates which have been so problematic in the past few months.
If you have difficulty updating to the new version, please follow
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/rsync-upgrade.php">these 
special update instructions</link>.
</p>
<p>In addition, this version of the fink package manager is compatible
with last summer's Developer Tools updates.  After installing both the new
package manager and the Developer Tools update, 
fink will ask you to reset your gcc version whenever
that is necessary.</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-09-02</date>
	<headline>Logo contest ends</headline>
		<body>
<p>The Logo contest held by Fink, announced <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/logo.php">here</link>,
ended yesterday. With over 80 different proposals from countries all over the world we 
consider the contest a big success.  
In the next couple of days all the submitted entries will be put on-line in a publicly accessible gallery and more details on the participants shall be published. For those who are 
curious and cannot wait may have a look at an incomplete <link url="http://nour.net/logo/incomplete.html">preview</link>.</p>
<p>Fink is proud to be part of such a supportive community and would like to thank those who submitted entries and <link url="http://www.macwelt.de">MacWelt</link> for their continued support.
</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
        <date>2003-08-18</date>
        <headline>Source files from ftp.gnu.org</headline>
               <body>
<p>As announced in <link
url="http://www.cert.org/advisories/CA-2003-21.html">this CERT 
advisory</link>, it has recently been discovered that
the ftp servers for GNU software were compromised back in March, 
although it is not believed that any of the source code housed there
was affected.
</p><p>
Fink relies on MD5 checksums when downloading software, and we have had
no reports of incorrect checksums in Fink packages.  The Free Software
Foundation is in the process of verifying the integrity of all of the
source code distributed from that ftp site.  As of this writing, the source
code for the following Fink packages have not yet been verified:
<code>autoconf2.54</code>,
<code>emacs21</code>,
<code>gprolog</code>,
<code>groff</code>,
<code>guile16</code>,
<code>help2man</code>,
<code>jwhois</code>,
<code>libtool14</code>,
<code>libosip1</code>,
<code>sed</code>,
<code>slib</code>.
It may be difficult to install those packages at present.
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-26</date>
        <headline>Developer Tools Update.</headline>
               <body>
<p><em>Quick Summary: DO NOT INSTALL THIS UPDATE.</em></p>
               <p>
Apple has released a patch to the December 2002 
Developer Tools which includes gcc 3.3,
their new compiler.
</p><p>
Fink does not yet support compiling with gcc 3.3.  In addition, it is important
not to "mix and match" between compilers:  all C++ code in fink packages
needs to be compiled
with the same compiler.
</p><p>
For this reason, the Fink team recommends that if you update your
Developer Tools with the new patch, you should be careful to run
<code>sudo gcc_select 3</code>
prior to any "fink build" or "fink install" commands.
</p>
<p><em>Update 30 June 2003:</em> A 
<link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=2680195&amp;forum_id=2056">problem
has now been detected</link> with
the new assembler program which the update installs, which may prevent
certain Fink packages from being compiled at all if you install this
update.  
</p>
<p><em>Generally, Fortran programs will break if you install the update;
the breakage does not stop by simply switching back to gcc 3.1.</em>
The Fink team is working on a workaround for this problem, but until it
is ready, if you need Fortran-related programs you should not install
the update.</p>

                </body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-20</date>
        <headline>Darwin packaging groups to coordinate efforts.</headline>
               <body>
               <p>
The <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net">Fink</link>, 
<link url="http://www.gentoo.org">Gentoo</link>, 
and 
<link url="http://opendarwin.org/projects/darwinports/">DarwinPorts</link> 
projects are pleased to announce the formation of  a cooperative development 
alliance forged to facilitate delivery of freely available software to 
Mac OS X.  Under this new alliance, the projects will share information and 
coordinate efforts for porting software to 
Apple's <link url="http://www.apple.com/macosx">Mac OS X</link> 
and <link url="http://www.apple.com/darwin">Darwin</link> operating 
systems.  Members of the alliance will share information using 
the <link url="http://www.metapkg.org">www.metapkg.org</link> Web 
site,  which  will provide a home for this cooperative effort. 
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-16</date>
        <headline>Fink logo contest begins.</headline>
               <body>
               <p>Fink and 
<link url="http://www.macwelt.de/">MacWelt</link> have managed to organize a logo contest.
For the next six weeks everyone is invited to submit their logo creations. 
Fink needs a new face and with your help we might just get one.  We are curious to see what you imagine Fink to be as a graphical representation.
The initial announcement by Macnews is in German, for those of you not capable of reading German a translated version can be found
 <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/logo.php">here</link>. 
                </p>
<p>
Fink and MacWelt hope that many of you will participate as we might just find some prices for the winners. Good luck and.... start drawing.
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>



<newsitem>
	<date>2003-05-05</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1.1 Binaries Available</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>KDE 3.1.1 binaries are now available.  Since they
have been released after 0.5.2 came out, you will need to update
your package descriptions by running <code>sudo apt-get update</code>
(or equivalent) before they will be available for installation.
For pointers to the changes and security fixes in this release,
see <link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=2068947&amp;forum_id=2022">the
announcement</link>.
</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-16</date>
	<headline>Virex problem resolved</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>McAfee has released Virex 7.2.1, which no longer
overwrites the main Fink directory <code>/sw</code>.  Fink users should
continue to avoid Virex 7.2.
</p><p>Early reports indicate that upgrading Virex from 7.2 to 7.2.1
still leaves some problems however.  If you upgrade Virex with Fink not
installed, and subsequently
wish to install Fink, you will need to delete the <code>/sw</code>
directory by hand before installing.  And if you upgrade Virex with
Fink already installed, you should immediately run
<em>
fink reinstall openssl-shlibs dlcompat-shlibs curl-ssl-shlibs
</em>
to restore files which the Virex upgrade may have deleted.
</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-14</date>
	<headline>Fink 0.5.2 released</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>Fink is proud to announce that the Fink binary distribution 0.5.2 is available from the <link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download.php">download</link> page.
		With over 190 new binary packages, KDE, KOffice and KDevelop binaries amongst other various improvements this is a recommended download for any new and all existing Fink users.
		The full announcement can be read on the <link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=fink-announce">fink-announce</link> mailing list.
		</p>
<p>(If you are having trouble upgrading a source installation, consult
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/fix-upgrade.php">these
special instructions</link>.)</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-09</date>
	<headline>Interview on OSNews.com</headline>
	<body>
	<p><link url="http://osnews.com/">OSNews.com</link> today is featuring a
	<link url="http://osnews.com/story.php?news_id=3236">mini-interview</link> with
	one of our project leaders, Max Horn. It contains some rather unusual questions,
	so even if you know Fink fairly well, you might find it informative.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-29</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1.1 Final In Unstable</headline>
	<body>
	<p>KDE 3.1.1 is now in Fink unstable.  The full announcement can be
<link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=1898907&amp;forum_id=2022">read here</link>.
	Improvements over 3.1 final include many upstream bugfixes,
	build improvements, koffice bugfixes, kmail crash fixes,
	and other miscellaneous updates.  Binary packages will not
	be available in time for the next binary distribution, but
	will be released as an update shortly thereafter.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-18</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1 Final In Stable</headline>
	<body>
	<p>KDE 3.1 is now in Fink stable.  The full announcement can be
<link url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=1833081&amp;forum_id=2022">read here</link>.
	Improvements over 3.1 beta1 include an updated audio driver, 
	faster startup times, cleaned up fink package info, support
	for Apple X11's window manager, and many bugfixes.  Binary
	packages will be available in the next binary distribution
	release.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-17</date>
	<headline>Apple X11 Beta 3 Released</headline>
	<body>
	<p><link url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/download/">A new
version of Apple's X11 for Mac OS X is available</link>.  It fixes a number
of bugs including a few that can cause problems with building Fink packages.
It is recommended that all Fink users who are using Apple X11 upgrade.
A new version of the system-xfree86 package has been released to unstable
that takes the new Apple X11 into account.  It should be appearing in stable
shortly.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
        <date>2003-02-14</date>
        <headline>New version of FinkCommander</headline>
        <body>
        <p><link
 url="http://finkcommander.sourceforge.net/">FinkCommander</link>,
 a separate project which provides a GUI for Fink,
has released version 0.5.0, their first Jaguar-only version.  The new
version includes a package browser which allows you to view the files 
that Fink has installed for a particular package, as well as <link 
url="http://finkcommander.sourceforge.net/pages/VERSION_HISTORY.html">many 
other improvements.</link>
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
        <date>2003-02-07</date>
        <headline>DO NOT INSTALL VIREX 7.2</headline>
        <body>
        <p>
        The Virex 7.2 package, currently being distributed free to all .Mac 
members, has a serious conflict with Fink.  <em>Fink users should not install 
Virex 7.2 under any circumstances.</em>
  Installing it after Fink is installed
will damage your Fink installation; installing it prior to Fink will make
it impossible to install Fink without damaging Virex.
</p><p>
This bug has been <link 
url="http://forums.mcafeehelp.com/viewtopic.php?t=6318&amp;sid=33d08f3c34f7e09dc546aa1ddf1c299c">reported 
to Virex's manufacturer.</link>  We will keep the
Fink community informed about the situation as it develops.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-26</date>
	<headline>Apple X11 Library Warning</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	While Apple's X11 works just fine with existing binaries, it
has a bug in the install name of the libraries that can cause some
software to build incorrectly, and will break forward-compatibility
with future X11 releases.
</p>
<p>
	Ben Hines has created a script (available <link url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/fink/fix-fink/install_name_fix.pl">here</link>) that you can use
that will fix the install_name entries in Apple's X11 libraries,
but it will not repair software you have already built against the
broken libraries.
</p>
<p><em>Update 11 February 2003:</em> This script is not needed with 
version 0.2 of Apple's X11.app which was released yesterday.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-21</date>
	<headline>Gnome, libpng, and the unstable tree</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
        A problem was uncovered today concerning the versions of imlib,
 libpng, and gnome in Fink's unstable tree.  The Fink team is hard at
 work addressing this problem.  As a workaround, users can downgrade
their imlib package to the stable version, "<code>fink install
 imlib-1.9.10-9</code>", until the problem is fixed.
</p><p>
   Many Fink users may be using Fink's unstable tree without being
fully aware of what this entails.  For a few months in the fall,
enabling the unstable tree was the only way to gain access to
 10.2-compatible versions of Fink packages.  
<em>That is no longer the case.</em>
Fink users who do not wish to help the Fink team with testing should
disable their unstable tree.  To do this, edit the file
<code>/sw/etc/fink.conf</code> and remove the items
 <code>unstable/main</code> and <code>unstable/crypto</code> from the
 <code>Trees</code> line.
	</p>
<p>The Fink team appreciates those users who are willing to stick with
the unstable tree, even when there are problems like today's, and provide
the team with prompt feedback.  This is a community effort and we
appreciate your participation.
</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-17</date>
	<headline>Anonymous CVS issues resolved</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	UPDATE: We are pleased to announce that SourceForge have resolved the issues with anonymous CVS access, and the selfupdate-cvs command should work again. Further details on the downtime can be found on the SourceForge.net <link url="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=2352&amp;group_id=1#cvs">site status</link> page.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-07</date>
	<headline>Fink Interaction with Apple's X11 Public Beta</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	Fink works just fine with the <link url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/">public beta X11 release</link>
	with some caveats.  Please read <varlink url="doc/x11/inst-xfree86.php#apple-binary">the newly added Apple X11</varlink> section of the Fink X11 Documentation for details.</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-07</date>
	<headline>RSS Feeds available</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	Thanks to Benjamin Reed, it is now possible to receive RSS 1.0 Feeds that contain a lot of valuable information.

<varlink url="news/fink-stable.rdf">fink-stable.rdf</varlink> will tell you about the changes and additions in the stable tree, reflecting packages which have been added or modified.
</p>
<p><varlink url="news/fink-unstable.rdf">fink-unstable.rdf</varlink> will tell you about changes or additions to the unstable tree and is most likely the most active RSS feed.
The above Feeds are automatically updated every 60 minutes to make sure that they keep you all on top of the latest development.
</p>
<p><varlink url="news/news.rdf">news.rdf</varlink> This feed reflects the contents of the Fink News Page. The Feed is updated as soon as a new item is added on the Website.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
  <date>2002-12-22</date>
  <headline>New Upgrade Matrix</headline>
  <body>
  <p>A new <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink> is
  now available, for use in upgrading earlier versions of Fink to the
  current version, under either OS X 10.1 or OS X 10.2.  Users upgrading
  under 10.1 will be brought to Fink version 0.4.1a, while users
  upgrading under 10.2 will be brought to Fink version 0.5.0a.
  </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>  
  <date>2002-12-11</date>
  <headline>New Upgrade Matrix coming</headline>
  <body>
  <p>The Fink team is aware of the shortcomings of the current
  <em>Upgrade Matrix</em> page, which is inadequate for upgrading
to Fink 0.5.0a.  Please be patient as we construct
  a new version of that page, whose existence will be announced
  here.  In the meantime, some of you may wish to use the <link
  url="news/jaguar.php">test version of the Jaguar updater</link> which was
made available on 2002-09-08.
  </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-12-09</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.5.0a Released</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
    Fink 0.5.0a for Mac OS X 10.2 is now complete. (Note: 0.5.0a is a final
    release, and replaces 0.5.0 which was never officially released.) This
    release includes over 700 
    binary packages for OS X 10.2 as well as over 1800 source packages of
    all kinds. 
  </p>
  <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as all binary packages. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink>. 
  </p>
  <p>
  This release is for Mac OS X 10.2 only. 10.1 users should use Fink 0.4.1.
  </p>
  </body>
  </newsitem>
  
<newsitem>
  <date>2002-11-11</date>
  <headline>Update XFree86 for use with OS X 10.2.2</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
Users should update their XFree86 installations to version 4.2.1.1
for use with OS X 10.2.2.  If you are using system-xfree86, you
can get the new version from the <link
url="https://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=118483">XonX 
project</link>.  If you are using Fink's
xfree86 packages, you should update to xfree86-base-4.2.1.1-1 and
xfree86-rootless-4.2.1.1-1.  These packages are recent additions to
the 10.2/unstable tree; to gain access to them, you may need to run 
"fink selfupdate-cvs" and/or enable the unstable tree
  </p>
  </body>
  </newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-10-30</date>
  <headline>Don't reuse binary installer</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
  Users are cautioned to use the binary installer for Fink 0.4.1 <em>only
once</em> on a given machine.  Due to an apparent bug in Apple's
Installer.app program, attempting a second installation on the same
machine can result in permissions being altered in the machine's root
directory, in some cases leaving the machine in a non-bootable state.
</p><p> If Installer.app presents you with an "Upgrade" button rather
than an "Install" button when installing Fink 0.4.1, <em>do not proceed
any further!</em> </p>
<p>A new version of the binary installer for Fink 0.4.1 became available
on November 5.  The new version avoids
the problem of the machine not booting, but even with the new version,
users are advised to only "Install",
not "Upgrade."  (You can recognize the new version by its filesize of
12582912 bytes, while the old version had a filesize of 10541112 bytes.)
</p></body></newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-09-28</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.4.1 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as all binary packages. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink>. 
    </p>
    <p>
    This is the <em>last release for Mac OS X 10.1</em>. Future versions of Fink will <em>not</em> officially support Mac OS X 10.1 anymore, we are gearing all our efforts towards 10.2.
    </p>
    <p>
    At the same time, this release is not meant for Mac OS X 10.2. Fink 0.5.0. which is targeted for October, will be geared towards 10.2. In the meantime refer to the news item below on how to upgrade Fink for 10.2.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2002-09-27</date>
<headline>Possible conflicts with anti-virus software</headline>
<body>
<p> A number of recent reports on the 
<link
url="http://www.mail-archive.com/fink-users@lists.sourceforge.net/">fink-users
mailing list</link> have indicated problems (including kernel panics and
infinite hangs during patching) when using Fink to compile packages while
anti-virus software is installed.  You may need to switch off any anti-virus
software before using Fink.
</p></body></newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2002-09-08</date>
	<headline>Test version of Jaguar updater available</headline>
	<body>
		<p>
			A test version of the 10.2 updater for Fink is now available. The update process is somewhat complicated at the moment, but is explained in <varlink url="news/jaguar.php">step-by-step instructions for updating</varlink>. We also have separate <varlink url="news/jag-bootstrap.php">instructions to install Fink from scratch on 10.2</varlink>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			At the moment, approximately 800 out of 1150 Fink packages have been made ready for 10.2. However, virtually all of these packages are still being tested and have not yet been moved to the "stable" tree in the 10.2 section; moreover, binaries for 10.2 packages are not yet available. 
		</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-08-20</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X 10.2 / Jaguar</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      During the last few weeks, we got a lot of emails asking whether Fink will work Mac OS X 10.2.
    </p>
    <p>
      The answer is: Yes, we will support 10.2. However, due to some
      major changes in this new OS version, we had to make a lot of adjustments both
      to the Fink tool itself and to many packages. The current binary distribution,
      0.4.0a, will only work partially on 10.2. We are working on an upgrade guide,
      as well as a new Fink release, to support 10.2.
    </p>
	<p>
	 If you upgrade your system to 10.2 before the official Fink update for 10.2 is ready,
	 many Fink packages built on 10.1 are going to work fine, but others need to be rebuilt.
	 Some packages need special changes to build on 10.2. Adding "unstable/main" to your
	 list of trees in /sw/etc/fink.conf (see also the <varlink url="faq/usage-fink.php#unstable">FAQ</varlink>)
	 will give you access to the latest versions of packages, many of which include important
	 fixes for 10.2.
	</p>
    <p>
     As of now, please do not email us asking about 10.2 support. If you can't wait,
     consult the <varlink url="lists/index.php">mailing list archives</varlink> instead.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-08-06</date>
  <headline>Fink package manager 0.10.0 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Yesterday version 0.10.0 of the Fink package manager was released to the unstable tree, along with version 1.6 of the base-files package. All Fink users which are using the unstable tree are recommended to update to this version. The easiest way to do so usually is to run 'fink selfupdate-cvs' which will automatically take care of updating these essential packages.
    </p>
    <p>
      Please report any problems you encounter with this version via our bug tracker.
    </p>
    <p>
      An overview of what changed since version 0.9.12 can be found <link url="http://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=103599">here.</link>
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-07-17</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution moves</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The Fink binary distribution has moved to a new location. All Fink users wishing to use the binary distribution will have to make sure they are using the new binary distribution (many of you already are using it, maybe without even noticing). If you want to know how to switch and why we do this, <varlink url="news/bindist_move.php">read more here.</varlink>.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-05-29</date>
  <headline>KDE support</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Fink <varlink url="news/kde.php">announces support</varlink> for <link url="http://www.kde.org">KDE</link>. Packages are available in the unstable distribution, as well as pre-built binaries. For more information on installing and running it, see the full <varlink url="news/kde.php">KDE Support In Fink</varlink> announcement. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-05-03</date>
  <headline>Bug in passwd package</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      All Fink users are urged to update their <em> passwd </em> package to version 20020329 or newer. Older versions of the <em> passwd </em> package are affected by a bug which could lead to the loss of all data on your hard disk if you remove system users created by Fink manually from the system via System Preferences. (Removing them via the NetInfo tool is safe.) You can check the version of your passwd package by entering <em> dpkg -s passwd</em>. If your version is outdated, you can update to the current one in two ways: 
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Via the binary distribution. First make sure you have the latest list of packages available: <em> sudo apt-get update</em>. Then you can perform the actual update: <em> sudo apt-get install passwd</em>. 
      </li>
      <li>
        Via the source distribution. First make sure you have the latest set of package descriptions: <em> fink selfupdate-cvs</em>. Then, update the passwd package: <em> fink update passwd</em> 
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      See <varlink url="faq/usage-general.php#passwd">Fink's FAQ, question 6.3,</varlink> for more information about the passwd package. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-04-18</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.4.0 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as many of the binary packages. As usual, the rest of the binaries will be made available during the next few days. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-16</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.2a is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, the bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink> and the <varlink url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-09</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.2 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release is available now, the binary installer will follow soon. The bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink> and the <varlink url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-08</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution lost</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Due to a faulty script, the whole fink website, including our binary distro, has been wiped! This means you can't use the binary distro right now. I am working as quick as I can on uploading the new Fink 0.3.2 binary distro. In addition, the package database is not working for now. Please bear with us. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-12-16</date>
  <headline>Yes, we are alive!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Despite the fact that no news were listed here for over a month, the fink project was quite busy in the recent time. Sadly, our leader, Christoph, left us last month. But despite this, development is going on actively. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Version 0.9.5 of the Fink package manager was recently released, and many updated and new packages are in our <varlink url="doc/cvsaccess/index.php">CVS</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-11-04</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.1 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, the bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <varlink url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</varlink> and the recently updated <varlink url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-11-02</date>
  <headline>Running X11 document updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The <varlink url="doc/x11/index.php">Running X11</varlink> document has had a significant update. The troubleshooting section now has a comprehensive list of XDarwin error messages with explanations. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-31</date>
  <body>
    <p>
      <link url="http://www.macosxhints.com/">MacOSXHints</link> has
      posted an <link url="http://homepage.mac.com/rgriff/xdarwin.html">
      installation guide</link> for XFree86, Fink, Window Maker and The GIMP.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-23</date>
  <headline>forked.net</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      In addition to ripping off Fink packages and breaking the GPL, the ports
      collection at <link url="http://macosx.forked.net/">forked.net
      </link> has just gone commercial. More details soon. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-03</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution complete</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The binary distribution update is now complete.
    The <varlink url="news/puma.php">10.1 compatibility report</varlink> has been
    updated to reflect the fixes in Fink 0.3.0.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-30</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.0 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The source release, the binary installer and a binary upgrade kit for
    broken-by-10.1 installations are available in the new <link
    url="download/index.php">download section</link>.
    The bulk of the binary distribution will be updated gradually over the
    next few days, as usual.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-26</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X 10.1 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Mac OS X 10.1 has been officially released yesterday. Before you use Fink
    on 10.1, check out the <varlink url="news/puma.php">compatibility report</varlink>.
    <em>Update:</em> The apt-get issue has been solved, expect a new release
    this weekend.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-07</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution fully updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The binary distribution is now fully updated to
    Fink 0.2.6. Enjoy.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-04</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.2.6 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Fink 0.2.6 is released, fixing several bootstrap problems. The source
    release is available from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>
    or via the 'fink selfupdate' command. The binary release will follow soon.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-02</date>
  <headline>Fink IRC Channel</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Chat with the developers and other users! We now have a #fink channel
    on the <link url="http://openprojects.net/">openprojects.net</link>
    IRC network.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-25</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.2.5 was released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The source release is
    available from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>, the
    binary release will follow soon.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-23</date>
  <headline>OpenOSX.com</headline>
  <body>
    <p>OpenOSX.com refuses to give fair credit after using Fink to create GIMP
    CDs. Read Christoph's <link url="pr/openosx.php">public statement</link>
    on the issue.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-22</date>
  <headline>New help page</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The new <link url="help/index.php">help page</link> lists various ways
    to get help using Fink. It also lists some ideas how you can give back to
    the project.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-13</date>
  <headline>Porting tips and X11 document updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <varlink url="doc/porting/index.php">porting tips</varlink> document has
    a new chapter on shared libraries and modules. The <link
    url="doc/x11/index.php">X11</link> document was also updated recently.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-01</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.4a is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>There was a bootstrapping problem in Fink 0.2.4. It is fixed in Fink
    0.2.4a. You only need this if you're doing a first time install, updates
    are not affected.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-01</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.4 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Version 0.2.4 is released. Get it from the <link
    url="download.php">download page</link>. Some highlights: The GIMP
    1.2.2, sound playback and recording via esound (thanks to Shawn Hsiao
    and Masanori Sekino for the CoreAudio patch), xmms 1.2.5.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-19</date>
  <headline>New document: X11 on Darwin and Mac OS X</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A comprehensive document about <link url="doc/x11/index.php">X11 on
    Darwin and Mac OS X</link> is now available. It was written to be useful
    for anyone, not just Fink users.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-13</date>
  <headline>Package database now online</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A prototype of the <link url="pdb/index.php">package database</link>
    is now online.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-09</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.3 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Get it from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>. This
    version fixes the dpkg download problems many of you were having.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-03</date>
  <headline>Packaging Manual updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <varlink url="doc/packaging/index.php">Packaging Manual</varlink> was
    updated to include all recently added fields.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-06-30</date>
  <headline>Web site restructuring</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A major restructuring of the web site has started. The non-Fink-specific
    documents were removed because I don't have the time to maintain them. All
    documentation will be consolidated in the new <link url="doc/index.php">
    Documentation section</link>.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-06-24</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.2 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Version 0.2.2 is finally released. Get it from the <link
    url="download.php">download page</link>. Be sure to read the notes
    about X11 in the INSTALL file.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-05-19</date>
  <headline>CVS instructions updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <varlink url="fink/cvs.php">CVS instructions</varlink> have
    been updated for Fink 0.2.x.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-26</date>
  <headline>FAQ online</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      This site now sports a <varlink url="faq/index.php">FAQ section</varlink>. Not much content yet, but it's here to stay. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-20</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.0 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      It now uses dpkg for binary package management. You can get it from the download page, but be aware that this version is not yet as stable as the 0.1.x series. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-15</date>
  <headline>Released version 0.1.8a</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Released version 0.1.8a, fixing install problems. You only need this if you downloaded 0.1.8 and had install problems ("stow not found"). Get it from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-14</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.8 is out</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-30</date>
  <headline>Porting notes updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The <varlink url="darwin/porting.php">porting notes</varlink> have been updated with information on Mac OS X Final. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-30</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.7 is out!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-24</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X is released!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Expect Fink packages to be adapted to the final release within the next one or two weeks. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-15</date>
  <headline>Libtool page updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Updated the <varlink url="darwin/libtool.php">libtool page</varlink> with a revised patch that does full shared library versioning. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-08</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.6 is out</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <varlink url="download.php">download page</varlink>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

</news>
