<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "finknews.dtd">
<news>
<cvsid>$Id: news.xml,v 1.62 2003/06/26 23:16:15 dmrrsn Exp $</cvsid>

<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-26</date>
        <headline>Developer Tools Update.</headline>
               <body>
               <p>
Apple has released a patch to the December 2002 
Developer Tools which includes gcc 3.3,
their new compiler.
</p><p>
Fink does not yet support compiling with gcc 3.3.  In addition, it is important
not to "mix and match" between compilers:  all C++ code in fink packages
needs to be compiled
with the same compiler.
</p><p>
For this reason, the Fink team recommends that if you update your
Developer Tools with the new patch, you should be careful to run
<code>sudo gcc_select 3</code>
prior to any "fink build" or "fink install" commands.
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-20</date>
        <headline>Darwin packaging groups to coordinate efforts.</headline>
               <body>
               <p>
The <extlink url="http://fink.sourceforge.net">Fink</extlink>, 
<extlink url="http://www.gentoo.org">Gentoo</extlink>, 
and 
<extlink url="http://opendarwin.org/projects/darwinports/">DarwinPorts</extlink> 
projects are pleased to announce the formation of  a cooperative development 
alliance forged to facilitate delivery of freely available software to 
Mac OS X.  Under this new alliance, the projects will share information and 
coordinate efforts for porting software to 
Apple's <extlink url="http://www.apple.com/macosx">Mac OS X</extlink> 
and <extlink url="http://www.apple.com/darwin">Darwin</extlink> operating 
systems.  Members of the alliance will share information using 
the <extlink url="http://www.metapkg.org">www.metapkg.org</extlink> Web 
site,  which  will provide a home for this cooperative effort. 
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>


<newsitem>
        <date>2003-06-16</date>
        <headline>Fink logo contest begins.</headline>
               <body>
               <p>Fink and 
<extlink url="http://www.macwelt.de/">Macwelt</extlink> have managed to organise a logo contest.
For the next six weeks everyone is invited to submit their logo creations. 
Fink needs a new face and with your help we might just get one.  We are curious to see what you imagine Fink to be as a graphical representation.
The initial announcement by Macnews is in German, for those of you not capable of reading German a translated version can be found
 <extlink url="http://fink.sf.net/logo.php">here</extlink>. 
                </p>
<p>
Fink and Macwelt hope that many of you will participate as we might just find some prices for the winners. Good luck and.... start drawing.
</p>
                </body>
</newsitem>



<newsitem>
	<date>2003-05-05</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1.1 Binaries Available</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>KDE 3.1.1 binaries are now available.  Since they
have been released after 0.5.2 came out, you will need to update
your package descriptions by running <code>sudo apt-get update</code>
(or equivalent) before they will be available for installation.
For pointers to the changes and security fixes in this release,
see <extlink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=2068947&amp;forum_id=2022">the
announcement</extlink>.
</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-16</date>
	<headline>Virex problem resolved</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>McAfee has released Virex 7.2.1, which no longer
overwrites the main Fink directory <code>/sw</code>.  Fink users should
continue to avoid Virex 7.2.
</p><p>Early reports indicate that upgrading Virex from 7.2 to 7.2.1
still leaves some problems however.  If you upgrade Virex with Fink not
installed, and subsequently
wish to install Fink, you will need to delete the <code>/sw</code>
directory by hand before installing.  And if you upgrade Virex with
Fink already installed, you should immediately run
<em>
fink reinstall openssl-shlibs dlcompat-shlibs curl-ssl-shlibs
</em>
to restore files which the Virex upgrade may have deleted.
</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-14</date>
	<headline>Fink 0.5.2 released</headline>
	       <body>
	       <p>Fink is proud to announce that the Fink binary distribution 0.5.2 is available from the <extlink url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download.php">download</extlink> page.
		With over 190 new binary packages, KDE, KOffice and KDevelop binaries amongst other various improvements this is a recommended download for any new and all existing Fink users.
		The full announcement can be read on the <extlink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum=fink-announce">fink-announce</extlink> mailing list.
		</p>
<p>(If you are having trouble upgrading a source installation, consult
<extlink url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/fix-upgrade.php">these
special instructions</extlink>.)</p>

		</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2003-04-09</date>
	<headline>Interview on OSNews.com</headline>
	<body>
	<p><extlink url="http://osnews.com/">OSNews.com</extlink> today is featuring a
	<extlink url="http://osnews.com/story.php?news_id=3236">mini-interview</extlink> with
	one of our project leaders, Max Horn. It contains some rather unusual questions,
	so even if you know Fink fairly well, you might find it informative.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-29</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1.1 Final In Unstable</headline>
	<body>
	<p>KDE 3.1.1 is now in Fink unstable.  The full announcement can be
<extlink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=1898907&amp;forum_id=2022">read here</extlink>.
	Improvements over 3.1 final include many upstream bugfixes,
	build improvements, koffice bugfixes, kmail crash fixes,
	and other miscellaneous updates.  Binary packages will not
	be available in time for the next binary distribution, but
	will be released as an update shortly thereafter.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-18</date>
	<headline>KDE 3.1 Final In Stable</headline>
	<body>
	<p>KDE 3.1 is now in Fink stable.  The full announcement can be
<extlink url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_id=1833081&amp;forum_id=2022">read here</extlink>.
	Improvements over 3.1 beta1 include an updated audio driver, 
	faster startup times, cleaned up fink package info, support
	for Apple X11's window manager, and many bugfixes.  Binary
	packages will be available in the next binary distribution
	release.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-03-17</date>
	<headline>Apple X11 Beta 3 Released</headline>
	<body>
	<p><extlink url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/download/">A new
version of Apple's X11 for Mac OS X is available</extlink>.  It fixes a number
of bugs including a few that can cause problems with building Fink packages.
It is recommended that all Fink users who are using Apple X11 upgrade.
A new version of the system-xfree86 package has been released to unstable
that takes the new Apple X11 into account.  It should be appearing in stable
shortly.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
        <date>2003-02-14</date>
        <headline>New version of FinkCommander</headline>
        <body>
        <p><extlink
 url="http://finkcommander.sourceforge.net/">FinkCommander</extlink>,
 a separate project which provides a GUI for Fink,
has released version 0.5.0, their first Jaguar-only version.  The new
version includes a package browser which allows you to view the files 
that Fink has installed for a particular package, as well as <extlink 
url="http://finkcommander.sourceforge.net/pages/VERSION_HISTORY.html">many 
other improvements.</extlink>
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
        <date>2003-02-07</date>
        <headline>DO NOT INSTALL VIREX 7.2</headline>
        <body>
        <p>
        The Virex 7.2 package, currently being distributed free to all .Mac 
members, has a serious conflict with Fink.  <em>Fink users should not install 
Virex 7.2 under any circumstances.</em>
  Installing it after Fink is installed
will damage your Fink installation; installing it prior to Fink will make
it impossible to install Fink without damaging Virex.
</p><p>
This bug has been <extlink 
url="http://forums.mcafeehelp.com/viewtopic.php?t=6318&amp;sid=33d08f3c34f7e09dc546aa1ddf1c299c">reported 
to Virex's manufacturer.</extlink>  We will keep the
Fink community informed about the situation as it develops.
</p></body></newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-26</date>
	<headline>Apple X11 Library Warning</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	While Apple's X11 works just fine with existing binaries, it
has a bug in the install name of the libraries that can cause some
software to build incorrectly, and will break forward-compatibility
with future X11 releases.
</p>
<p>
	Ben Hines has created a script (available <extlink url="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/fink/fix-fink/install_name_fix.pl">here</extlink>) that you can use
that will fix the install_name entries in Apple's X11 libraries,
but it will not repair software you have already built against the
broken libraries.
</p>
<p><em>Update 11 February 2003:</em> This script is not needed with 
version 0.2 of Apple's X11.app which was released yesterday.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-21</date>
	<headline>Gnome, libpng, and the unstable tree</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
        A problem was uncovered today concerning the versions of imlib,
 libpng, and gnome in Fink's unstable tree.  The Fink team is hard at
 work addressing this problem.  As a workaround, users can downgrade
their imlib package to the stable version, "<code>fink install
 imlib-1.9.10-9</code>", until the problem is fixed.
</p><p>
   Many Fink users may be using Fink's unstable tree without being
fully aware of what this entails.  For a few months in the fall,
enabling the unstable tree was the only way to gain access to
 10.2-compatible versions of Fink packages.  
<em>That is no longer the case.</em>
Fink users who do not wish to help the Fink team with testing should
disable their unstable tree.  To do this, edit the file
<code>/sw/etc/fink.conf</code> and remove the items
 <code>unstable/main</code> and <code>unstable/crypto</code> from the
 <code>Trees</code> line.
	</p>
<p>The Fink team appreciates those users who are willing to stick with
the unstable tree, even when there are problems like today's, and provide
the team with prompt feedback.  This is a community effort and we
appreciate your participation.
</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-17</date>
	<headline>Anonymous CVS issues resolved</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	UPDATE: We are pleased to announce that SourceForge have resolved the issues with anonymous CVS access, and the selfupdate-cvs command should work again. Further details on the downtime can be found on the SourceForge.net <extlink url="http://sourceforge.net/docman/display_doc.php?docid=2352&amp;group_id=1#cvs">site status</extlink> page.
	</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-07</date>
	<headline>Fink Interaction with Apple's X11 Public Beta</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	Fink works just fine with the <extlink url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/x11/">public beta X11 release</extlink>
	with some caveats.  Please read <link url="doc/x11/inst-xfree86.php#apple-binary">the newly added Apple X11</link> section of the Fink X11 Documentation for details.</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
	<date>2003-01-07</date>
	<headline>RSS Feeds available</headline>
	<body>
	<p>
	Thanks to Benjamin Reed, it is now possible to receive RSS 1.0 Feeds that contain a lot of valuable information.

<link url="news/fink-stable.rdf">fink-stable.rdf</link> will tell you about the changes and additions in the stable tree, reflecting packages which have been added or modified.
</p>
<p><link url="news/fink-unstable.rdf">fink-unstable.rdf</link> will tell you about changes or additions to the unstable tree and is most likely the most active RSS feed.
The above Feeds are automatically updated every 60 minutes to make sure that they keep you all on top of the latest development.
</p>
<p><link url="news/news.rdf">news.rdf</link> This feed reflects the contents of the Fink News Page. The Feed is updated as soon as a new item is added on the Website.
</p>
</body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>
  <date>2002-12-22</date>
  <headline>New Upgrade Matrix</headline>
  <body>
  <p>A new <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link> is
  now available, for use in upgrading earlier versions of Fink to the
  current version, under either OS X 10.1 or OS X 10.2.  Users upgrading
  under 10.1 will be brought to Fink version 0.4.1a, while users
  upgrading under 10.2 will be brought to Fink version 0.5.0a.
  </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>
<newsitem>  
  <date>2002-12-11</date>
  <headline>New Upgrade Matrix coming</headline>
  <body>
  <p>The Fink team is aware of the shortcomings of the current
  <em>Upgrade Matrix</em> page, which is inadequate for upgrading
to Fink 0.5.0a.  Please be patient as we construct
  a new version of that page, whose existence will be announced
  here.  In the meantime, some of you may wish to use the <link
  url="news/jaguar.php">test version of the Jaguar updater</link> which was
made available on 2002-09-08.
  </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-12-09</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.5.0a Released</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
    Fink 0.5.0a for Mac OS X 10.2 is now complete. (Note: 0.5.0a is a final
    release, and replaces 0.5.0 which was never officially released.) This
    release includes over 700 
    binary packages for OS X 10.2 as well as over 1800 source packages of
    all kinds. 
  </p>
  <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as all binary packages. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link>. 
  </p>
  <p>
  This release is for Mac OS X 10.2 only. 10.1 users should use Fink 0.4.1.
  </p>
  </body>
  </newsitem>
  
<newsitem>
  <date>2002-11-11</date>
  <headline>Update XFree86 for use with OS X 10.2.2</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
Users should update their XFree86 installations to version 4.2.1.1
for use with OS X 10.2.2.  If you are using system-xfree86, you
can get the new version from the <link
url="https://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=118483">XonX 
project</link>.  If you are using Fink's
xfree86 packages, you should update to xfree86-base-4.2.1.1-1 and
xfree86-rootless-4.2.1.1-1.  These packages are recent additions to
the 10.2/unstable tree; to gain access to them, you may need to run 
"fink selfupdate-cvs" and/or enable the unstable tree
  </p>
  </body>
  </newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-10-30</date>
  <headline>Don't reuse binary installer</headline>
  <body>
  <p>
  Users are cautioned to use the binary installer for Fink 0.4.1 <em>only
once</em> on a given machine.  Due to an apparent bug in Apple's
Installer.app program, attempting a second installation on the same
machine can result in permissions being altered in the machine's root
directory, in some cases leaving the machine in a non-bootable state.
</p><p> If Installer.app presents you with an "Upgrade" button rather
than an "Install" button when installing Fink 0.4.1, <em>do not proceed
any further!</em> </p>
<p>A new version of the binary installer for Fink 0.4.1 became available
on November 5.  The new version avoids
the problem of the machine not booting, but even with the new version,
users are advised to only "Install",
not "Upgrade."  (You can recognize the new version by its filesize of
12582912 bytes, while the old version had a filesize of 10541112 bytes.)
</p></body></newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-09-28</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.4.1 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as all binary packages. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link>. 
    </p>
    <p>
    This is the <em>last release for Mac OS X 10.1</em>. Future versions of Fink will <em>not</em> officially support Mac OS X 10.1 anymore, we are gearing all our efforts towards 10.2.
    </p>
    <p>
    At the same time, this release is not meant for Mac OS X 10.2. Fink 0.5.0. which is targeted for October, will be geared towards 10.2. In the meantime refer to the news item below on how to upgrade Fink for 10.2.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
<date>2002-09-27</date>
<headline>Possible conflicts with anti-virus software</headline>
<body>
<p> A number of recent reports on the 
<link
url="http://www.mail-archive.com/fink-users@lists.sourceforge.net/">fink-users
mailing list</link> have indicated problems (including kernel panics and
infinite hangs during patching) when using Fink to compile packages while
anti-virus software is installed.  You may need to switch off any anti-virus
software before using Fink.
</p></body></newsitem>

<newsitem>
	<date>2002-09-08</date>
	<headline>Test version of Jaguar updater available</headline>
	<body>
		<p>
			A test version of the 10.2 updater for Fink is now available. The update process is somewhat complicated at the moment, but is explained in <link url="news/jaguar.php">step-by-step instructions for updating</link>. We also have separate <link url="news/jag-bootstrap.php">instructions to install Fink from scratch on 10.2</link>. 
		</p>
		<p>
			At the moment, approximately 800 out of 1150 Fink packages have been made ready for 10.2. However, virtually all of these packages are still being tested and have not yet been moved to the "stable" tree in the 10.2 section; moreover, binaries for 10.2 packages are not yet available. 
		</p>
	</body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-08-20</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X 10.2 / Jaguar</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      During the last few weeks, we got a lot of emails asking whether Fink will work Mac OS X 10.2.
    </p>
    <p>
      The answer is: Yes, we will support 10.2. However, due to some
      major changes in this new OS version, we had to make a lot of adjustments both
      to the Fink tool itself and to many packages. The current binary distribution,
      0.4.0a, will only work partially on 10.2. We are working on an upgrade guide,
      as well as a new Fink release, to support 10.2.
    </p>
	<p>
	 If you upgrade your system to 10.2 before the official Fink update for 10.2 is ready,
	 many Fink packages built on 10.1 are going to work fine, but others need to be rebuilt.
	 Some packages need special changes to build on 10.2. Adding "unstable/main" to your
	 list of trees in /sw/etc/fink.conf (see also the <link url="faq/usage-fink.php#unstable">FAQ</link>)
	 will give you access to the latest versions of packages, many of which include important
	 fixes for 10.2.
	</p>
    <p>
     As of now, please do not email us asking about 10.2 support. If you can't wait,
     consult the <link url="lists/index.php">mailing list archives</link> instead.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-08-06</date>
  <headline>Fink package manager 0.10.0 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Yesterday version 0.10.0 of the Fink package manager was released to the unstable tree, along with version 1.6 of the base-files package. All Fink users which are using the unstable tree are recommended to update to this version. The easiest way to do so usually is to run 'fink selfupdate-cvs' which will automatically take care of updating these essential packages.
    </p>
    <p>
      Please report any problems you encounter with this version via our bug tracker.
    </p>
    <p>
      An overview of what changed since version 0.9.12 can be found <link url="http://sourceforge.net/project/shownotes.php?release_id=103599">here.</link>
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-07-17</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution moves</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The Fink binary distribution has moved to a new location. All Fink users wishing to use the binary distribution will have to make sure they are using the new binary distribution (many of you already are using it, maybe without even noticing). If you want to know how to switch and why we do this, <link url="news/bindist_move.php">read more here.</link>.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-05-29</date>
  <headline>KDE support</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Fink <link url="news/kde.php">announces support</link> for <extlink url="http://www.kde.org">KDE</extlink>. Packages are available in the unstable distribution, as well as pre-built binaries. For more information on installing and running it, see the full <link url="news/kde.php">KDE Support In Fink</link> announcement. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-05-03</date>
  <headline>Bug in passwd package</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      All Fink users are urged to update their <em> passwd </em> package to version 20020329 or newer. Older versions of the <em> passwd </em> package are affected by a bug which could lead to the loss of all data on your hard disk if you remove system users created by Fink manually from the system via System Preferences. (Removing them via the NetInfo tool is safe.) You can check the version of your passwd package by entering <em> dpkg -s passwd</em>. If your version is oudated, you can update to the current one in two ways: 
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Via the binary distribution. First make sure you have the latest list of packages available: <em> sudo apt-get update</em>. Then you can perform the actual update: <em> sudo apt-get install passwd</em>. 
      </li>
      <li>
        Via the source distribution. First make sure you have the latest set of package descriptions: <em> fink selfupdate-cvs</em>. Then, update the passwd package: <em> fink update passwd</em> 
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
      See <link url="faq/usage-general.php#passwd">Fink's FAQ, question 6.3,</link> for more information about the passwd package. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-04-18</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.4.0 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, as well as many of the binary packages. As usual, the rest of the binaries will be made available during the next few days. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-16</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.2a is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, the bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link> and the <link url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-09</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.2 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release is available now, the binary installer will follow soon. The bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link> and the <link url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2002-01-08</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution lost</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Due to a faulty script, the whole fink website, including our binary distro, has been wiped! This means you can't use the binary distro right now. I am working as quick as I can on uploading the new Fink 0.3.2 binary distro. In addition, the package database is not working for now. Please bear with us. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-12-16</date>
  <headline>Yes, we are alive!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Despite the fact that no news were listed here for over a month, the fink project was quite busy in the recent time. Sadly, our leader, Christoph, left us last month. But despite this, development is going on actively. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Version 0.9.5 of the Fink package manager was recently released, and many updated and new packages are in our <link url="doc/cvsaccess/index.php">CVS</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-11-04</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.1 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The source release and the binary installer are available now, the bulk of binary packages will be built and made available gradually over the next few days as usual. For information about upgrading, visit the <link url="download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link> and the recently updated <link url="doc/users-guide/index.php">User's Guide</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-11-02</date>
  <headline>Running X11 document updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The <link url="doc/x11/index.php">Running X11</link> document has had a significant update. The troubleshooting section now has a comprehensive list of XDarwin error messages with explanations. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-31</date>
  <body>
    <p>
      <extlink url="http://www.macosxhints.com/">MacOSXHints</extlink> has
      posted an <extlink url="http://homepage.mac.com/rgriff/xdarwin.html">
      installation guide</extlink> for XFree86, Fink, Window Maker and The GIMP.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-23</date>
  <headline>forked.net</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      In addition to ripping off Fink packages and breaking the GPL, the ports
      collection at <extlink url="http://macosx.forked.net/">forked.net
      </extlink> has just gone commercial. More details soon. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-10-03</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution complete</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The binary distribution update is now complete.
    The <link url="news/puma.php">10.1 compatibility report</link> has been
    updated to reflect the fixes in Fink 0.3.0.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-30</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.3.0 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The source release, the binary installer and a binary upgrade kit for
    broken-by-10.1 installations are available in the new <link
    url="download/index.php">download section</link>.
    The bulk of the binary distribution will be updated gradually over the
    next few days, as usual.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-26</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X 10.1 released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Mac OS X 10.1 has been officially released yesterday. Before you use Fink
    on 10.1, check out the <link url="news/puma.php">compatibility report</link>.
    <em>Update:</em> The apt-get issue has been solved, expect a new release
    this weekend.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-07</date>
  <headline>Binary distribution fully updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The binary distribution is now fully updated to
    Fink 0.2.6. Enjoy.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-04</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.2.6 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Fink 0.2.6 is released, fixing several bootstrap problems. The source
    release is available from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>
    or via the 'fink selfupdate' command. The binary release will follow soon.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-09-02</date>
  <headline>Fink IRC Channel</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Chat with the developers and other users! We now have a #fink channel
    on the <extlink url="http://openprojects.net/">openprojects.net</extlink>
    IRC network.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-25</date>
  <headline>Fink 0.2.5 was released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The source release is
    available from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>, the
    binary release will follow soon.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-23</date>
  <headline>OpenOSX.com</headline>
  <body>
    <p>OpenOSX.com refuses to give fair credit after using Fink to create GIMP
    CDs. Read Christoph's <link url="pr/openosx.php">public statement</link>
    on the issue.
    </p>
 </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-22</date>
  <headline>New help page</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The new <link url="help/index.php">help page</link> lists various ways
    to get help using Fink. It also lists some ideas how you can give back to
    the project.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-13</date>
  <headline>Porting tips and X11 document updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <link url="doc/porting/index.php">porting tips</link> document has
    a new chapter on shared libraries and modules. The <link
    url="doc/x11/index.php">X11</link> document was also updated recently.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-01</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.4a is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>There was a bootstrapping problem in Fink 0.2.4. It is fixed in Fink
    0.2.4a. You only need this if you're doing a first time install, updates
    are not affected.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-08-01</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.4 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Version 0.2.4 is released. Get it from the <link
    url="download.php">download page</link>. Some highlights: The GIMP
    1.2.2, sound playback and recording via esound (thanks to Shawn Hsiao
    and Masanori Sekino for the CoreAudio patch), xmms 1.2.5.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-19</date>
  <headline>New document: X11 on Darwin and Mac OS X</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A comprehensive document about <link url="doc/x11/index.php">X11 on
    Darwin and Mac OS X</link> is now available. It was written to be useful
    for anyone, not just Fink users.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-13</date>
  <headline>Package database now online</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A prototype of the <link url="pdb/index.php">package database</link>
    is now online.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-09</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.3 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Get it from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>. This
    version fixes the dpkg download problems many of you were having.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-07-03</date>
  <headline>Packaging Manual updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <link url="doc/packaging/index.php">Packaging Manual</link> was
    updated to include all recently added fields.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-06-30</date>
  <headline>Web site restructuring</headline>
  <body>
    <p>A major restructuring of the web site has started. The non-Fink-specific
    documents were removed because I don't have the time to maintain them. All
    documentation will be consolidated in the new <link url="doc/index.php">
    Documentation section</link>.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-06-24</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.2 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>Version 0.2.2 is finally released. Get it from the <link
    url="download.php">download page</link>. Be sure to read the notes
    about X11 in the INSTALL file.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-05-19</date>
  <headline>CVS instructions updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>The <link url="fink/cvs.php">CVS instructions</link> have
    been updated for Fink 0.2.x.
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-26</date>
  <headline>FAQ online</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      This site now sports a <link url="faq/index.php">FAQ section</link>. Not much content yet, but it's here to stay. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-20</date>
  <headline>Version 0.2.0 is released</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      It now uses dpkg for binary package management. You can get it from the download page, but be aware that this version is not yet as stable as the 0.1.x series. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-15</date>
  <headline>Released version 0.1.8a</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Released version 0.1.8a, fixing install problems. You only need this if you downloaded 0.1.8 and had install problems ("stow not found"). Get it from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-04-14</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.8 is out</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-30</date>
  <headline>Porting notes updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      The <link url="darwin/porting.php">porting notes</link> have been updated with information on Mac OS X Final. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-30</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.7 is out!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-24</date>
  <headline>Mac OS X is released!</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Expect Fink packages to be adapted to the final release within the next one or two weeks. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-15</date>
  <headline>Libtool page updated</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Updated the <link url="darwin/libtool.php">libtool page</link> with a revised patch that does full shared library versioning. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

<newsitem>
  <date>2001-03-08</date>
  <headline>Version 0.1.6 is out</headline>
  <body>
    <p>
      Get it from the <link url="download.php">download page</link>. 
    </p>
  </body>
</newsitem>

</news>
