<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document filename="index">
<title>Fink User's Guide</title>
<shorttitle>User's Guide</shorttitle>
<cvsid>$Id: uguide.xml,v 1.8 2001/10/20 22:52:51 chrisp Exp $</cvsid>

<preface>
<p>
<em>This document is a work in progress.</em>
At this time the various other documents are more useful:
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/bundled/readme.php">ReadMe</link>,
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/bundled/install.php">Installation</link>,
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/bundled/usage.php">Usage</link>
and the ReadMe.rtf included in the binary distribution.
Also check out the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/index.php">documentation
section</link> of the web site, it has some other useful documents
beyond that.
</p>

<p>
Welcome to the Fink User's Guide.
This guide covers first time installation and upgrade procedures for
both the source and the binary distribution.
Package installation and maintenance is covered as well.
</p>
</preface>


<chapter filename="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<shorttitle>Introduction</shorttitle>

<section name="what"><title>What is Fink?</title>
<p>
Fink is a distribution of Unix Open Source software for Mac OS X and
Darwin.
It brings free command-line and graphical software developed for Linux
and similar operating systems to your Mac.
</p>
</section>

<section name="req"><title>Requirements</title>
<p>
In any case you will need:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>
An installed Mac OS X system, version 10.0 or later, or equivalent
Darwin releases.
Earlier versions of both will <em>not</em> work.
See below for more information about supported systems.
</p></li>
<li><p>
Internet access.
Both source code and binary packages are downloaded from Internet
download sites.
</p></li>
</ul>
<p>
If you intend to use the source distribution (see below), you will
also need:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>
Development tools.
On Mac OS X, install the Developer.pkg package from the Developer
Tools CD.
Note that the tools must match your Mac OS X version.
On Darwin, the tools should be present in the default install.
</p>
<p>
It's a good idea to have the Developer Tools installed even if you
don't intend to build packages from source.
Some of the programs installed by the package are actually general
purpose command line tools.
Some packages may depend on those to run.
</p></li>
<li><p>
Patience.
Compiling several big packages takes time.
I'm talking hours or even days here.
</p></li>
</ul>
</section>

<section name="supported-os"><title>Supported Systems</title>
<p>
<em>Mac OS X 10.0.x</em> is fully tested and supported at this point
in time.
It is strongly recommended that you upgrade to the latest update in
that series, 10.0.4, through the Software Update panel in the System
Preferences.
Note that support for 10.0.x will be dropped in the future once 10.1
is in widespread use.
</p>
<p>
<em>Mac OS X 10.1</em> has been out for some weeks now.
The BSD subsystem and the development tools have seen significant
updates and there are still some packages that haven't been updated
to compile on 10.1 yet.
Those are rare, however; most packages work.
</p>
<p>
<em>Darwin 1.3.1</em> is the Darwin version corresponding to Mac OS X
10.0.x and should work as well.
However, this has not been tested as most people just run Mac OS X
proper instead.
You may run into problems with packages that use features specific to
Mac OS X - affected packages include XFree86 and possibly esound.
</p>
<p>
<em>Darwin 1.4.1</em> is the Darwin version corresponding to Mac OS X
10.1.
Both the notes about Darwin 1.3.1 and about Mac OS X 10.1 apply in
this case.
</p>
</section>

<section name="src-vs-bin"><title>Source vs. Binary</title>
<p>
Software is written ("developed") in human-readable programming
languages; this form is called the "source code".
Before a computer can actually run a program, it must be transformed
into low-level machine code instructions (unreadable by most humans).
That process is called "compiling" and the resulting program is called
"executable" or "binary".
(The process is also refered to as "building", because it usually
involves more steps than just compiling.)
</p>
<p>
When you buy commercial software you don't get to see the source code,
though - companies treat it as a trade secret.
You only get the ready-to-run executable, which means you have no way
to modify the program or even find out what it actually does when it's
run.
</p>
<p>
Not so with <link url="http://www.opensource.org/">Open Source</link>
software.
As the name implies, the source code is open for anyone to see and
modify.
In fact, most Open Source software is only distributed as source code
by its authors, and you must compile it on your computer to get a
program that can be run.
</p>
<p>
Fink lets you choose between the two models.
The "source" distribution will download the original source, adapt it
to Mac OS X and to Fink's policy, and compile it on your computer.
That process is fully automated, but takes some time.
The "binary" distribution on the other hand will download pre-compiled
packages from the Fink site and install those, saving you the time for
compiling.
It is actually possible to mix the two models at will.
The rest of this manual will show you how.
</p>
</section>

</chapter>


<chapter filename="install">
<title>First Time Installation</title>
<shorttitle>Install</shorttitle>

<preface>
<p>
During first time installation, a base system with the package
management tools is installed on your machine.
After that you must set up your shell environment to use the software
installed by Fink.
You only need to do this once; you can upgrade any Fink installation
(starting with release 0.2.0) in place, without reinstalling.
This is covered in the <xref chapter="upgrade">Upgrading
chapter</xref>.
</p>
<p>
Once you have the package management tools installed, you can use them
to install more software.
This is covered in the <xref chapter="packages">Installing Packages
chapter</xref>.
</p>
</preface>

<section name="bin"><title>Installing the Binary Distribution</title>
<p>
The binary distribution comes as a Mac OS X installer package (.pkg),
wrapped in a disk image (.dmg).
After downloading the disk image from the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/bindist.php">download page</link>
(you may have to use your browser's "Save Target as..." or "Download
to Disk" function), double-click it to mount it.
Open the "Fink 0.x.x Installer" disk icon that appears on your desktop
after Disk Copy has verified the file.
Inside you'll find some documentation and a installer package.
Double-click the installer package and follow the instructions on
screen.
</p>
<p>
You will be asked for an administrator password and shown some texts.
Please read them - they may be more up-to-date than this user's guide.
When the installer prompts you for a drive to install to, be sure to
pick your system volume (the one on which you installed Mac OS X).
If you pick the wrong volume, the install will proceed, but Fink won't
work afterwards.
When the installer is finished, proceed with the
<xref section="setup">Setting Up Your Environment</xref> section.
</p>
</section>

<section name="src"><title>Installing the Source Distribution</title>
<p>
The source distribution comes as a standard Unix tarball (.tar.gz).
It contains only the <code>fink</code> package manager and its package
descriptions and will download the source for packages on the fly.
You can get it from the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/srcdist.php">download page</link>.
It is important that you don't use StuffIt Expander to extract the tar
archive.
For some reason StuffIt still can't handle long file names.
If StuffIt Expander already extracted the archive, throw away the
folder it created.
</p>
<p>
The source release must be installed from the command line, so open
Terminal.app and change to the directory where you put the
fink-0.x.x-full.tar.gz archive.
The following command extracts the archive:
</p>
<codeblock>tar -xzf fink-0.x.x-full.tar.gz</codeblock>
<p>
That creates a directory with the same name as the archive.
We'll just keep on using the placeholder <code>fink-0.x.x-full</code>
here.
Now, change into that directory and run the bootstrap script:
</p>
<codeblock>cd fink-0.x.x-full
./bootstrap.sh</codeblock>
<p>
The script will run some checks on your system and use sudo to become
root - that will prompt you for your password.
Then, the script will ask you for the installation path.
Unless you have a good reason, you should use the default -
<code>/sw</code>.
Only that will allow you to install downloaded binary packages later
on.
Also, all examples use that path; be sure to substitute your actual
path if you use a different one.
</p>
<p>
Next up is Fink configuration.
You'll be asked for things like proxy and mirror settings and whether
you want verbose messages.
If you don't understand a question, just press return to accept the
default choice.
You can re-run this process later using the <code>fink
configure</code> command.
</p>
<p>
When the bootstrap script has all the information it needs, it will
start to download the source code for the base system and compile it.
No further interaction should be necessary at this point.
Don't worry if you see some packages being compiled twice.
This is required because to build a binary package of the package
manager, you first must have the package manager available.
</p>
<p>
When the bootstrap is finished, proceed with the
<xref section="setup">Setting Up Your Environment</xref> section.
</p>
</section>

<section name="setup"><title>Setting Up Your Environment</title>
<p>
To use the software installed in Fink's directory hierarchy, including
the package management programs themselves, you must set your PATH
environment variable (and some others) accordingly.
Shell scripts are provided to make this easy.
If you use tcsh (the default on Mac OS X), add the following line to
the file <code>.cshrc</code> in your home directory:
</p>
<codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.csh</codeblock>
<p>
If you don't know how to add the line, run these commands:
</p>
<codeblock>cd
pico .cshrc</codeblock>
<p>
You're not in a full-screen (well, full terminal window) text editor
and can simply start typing the <code>source /sw/bin/init.csh</code>
line.
It's okay if there is a note that says "New file".
Be sure that you pressed Return at least once after the line, then
press Control-O, Return, Control-X to get out of the editor.
</p>
<p>
Editing .cshrc will only affect new shells (i.e. newly opened Terminal
windows), so you should also run this command in all Terminal windows
that you opened before you edited the file.
You'll also need to run <code>rehash</code> because tcsh caches the
list of available commands internally.
</p>
<p>
If you use a Bourne style shell (e.g. sh, bash, zsh), use
<code>/sw/bin/init.sh</code> instead.
The file to edit varies with the shell, although <code>.profile</code>
should work for all Bourne style shells.
</p>
<p>
Note that the scripts also add /usr/X11R6/bin and /usr/X11R6/man to
your path so you can use X11 when it is installed.
Fink packages have the ability to add settings of their own, e.g. the
qt package sets the QTDIR environment variable.
</p>
<p>
Once your environment is set up, proceed to the
<xref chapter="packages">Installing Packages</xref> chapter to see how
you can install some actually useful packages using the various
package management tools included in Fink.
</p>
</section>

</chapter>


<chapter filename="packages">
<title>Installing Packages</title>
<shorttitle>Packages</shorttitle>

<preface>
Now that you have something that can be called a Fink installation,
this chapter shows you how to install the actual software packages you
came for.
Before we explain how to install packages using either the source or
the binary distribution, some important notes that apply to both.
</preface>

<section name="x11"><title>Getting X11 Sorted Out</title>
<p>
Since there are several X11 implementations available for Mac OS X
(XFree86, Tenon Xtools, eXodus) and several ways to install them
(manually or via Fink), there are several alternative packages - one
for each setup.
Fink is very bad at guessing what you have, so it's important to pick
the right one and install it before you start installing X11
applications.
Here is a list of the available packages and X11 installation methods:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>
xfree86-base:
This package is the real thing.
It installs the whole load of XFree86 as a Fink package.
For maximum flexibility, this package does not contain the actual
XDarwin server.
To get that, you can install the xfree86-server or the
xfree86-rootless package.
Or you can install it manually, for example using an "XDarwin" test
release from the XonX project or one of the "rootless" servers
circulating the net.
</p></li>
<li><p>
system-xfree86:
This package expects that you installed XFree86 manually, either from
source or from the official binary distribution.
It will just check that the installation is useful and then act as a
dependency placeholder.
Note that XFree86 4.0.2 or 4.0.3 will not pass the test.
You need a version that builds shared libraries.
Usually that will be 4.1.0, but CVS versions of XFree86 starting
around spring 2001 will also work.
</p></li>
<li><p>
system-xtools:
Install this package if you have Tenon's Xtools product installed.
Like system-xfree86, this will just do a sanity check and leave the
actual files alone.
</p></li>
</ul>
<p>
For more information on installing and running X11, refer to the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/x11/">X11 on Darwin
and Mac OS X document</link>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="bin-dselect"><title>Installing Binary Packages with
dselect</title>
<p>
<code>dselect</code> is a program that lets you browse the list of
available packages and select which ones you want installed.
It runs inside Terminal.app, but takes over the whole "screen" and
uses simple keyboard navigation.
Like the other package management tools, <code>dselect</code> requires
root privileges, so you must either become root before you start it or
use sudo:
</p>
<codeblock>sudo dselect</codeblock>
<p>
The main menu has several choices:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>
<em>[A]ccess</em> - this configures the network access method to use.
<em>You do not need to run this</em>, since Fink pre-configures
everything for you.
Actually, you should avoid this menu item as it may overwrite the
default configuration with one that doesn't work.
</p></li>
<li><p>
<em>[U]pdate</em> - this item downloads the list of available packages
from the Fink site.
This item does not install or update any actual packages, it just
updates the listings used for the package browser.
You must run this at least once after installing Fink.
</p></li>
<li><p>
<em>[S]elect</em> - this gives you the actual package listing, where
you can select and deselect the packages you want on your system.
More about this later.
</p></li>
<li><p>
<em>[I]nstall</em> - this is where the action is.
The menu items above only affect dselect's package listings and status
database.
This one actually goes out and downloads and installs the packages you
have requested.
It also removes the packages you have deselected in the browser.
</p></li>
<li><p>
<em>[C]onfig</em> and <em>[R]emove</em> - these are relics from the
time before apt.
You do not need them, although they won't do harm.
</p></li>
<li><p>
<em>[Q]uit</em> - now that should really be obvious.
</p></li>
</ul>

<p>
You'll spend most of your time with dselect in the package browser,
reachable through the "[S]elect" menu item.
Before dselect shows you the package list, it presents you with an
introductory help screen.
You can press 'k' to get a full listing of keyboard commands, or just
Space to get to the package list.
</p>
<p>
You can move through the list using the up and down keys.
Selections are made with '+' and '-'.
When you select a package that needs some other packages, dselect will
show you a sublist with the affected packages.
In most cases you can just press Return to accept dselect's choices.
You can also make adjustments in the sublist (e.g. to choose another
alternative for a virtual package dependency), or press 'R'
(i.e. Shift-R) to return to the previous state.
Both the sublists and the main package list are left by pressing
Return.
When you're happy with your selections, leave the main list and use
the "[I]nstall" menu item to actually install the packages.
</p>
</section>

<section name="bin-apt"><title>Installing Binary Packages with
apt-get</title>
<p>
<code>dselect</code> doesn't actually download the packages itself.
Instead, it runs apt to do the dirty work.
If you prefer a pure command line interface, you can access the
functions of apt directly, with the <code>apt-get</code> command.
</p>
<p>
Like with dselect, you must first download the current listing of
available packages with this command:
</p>
<codeblock>sudo apt-get update</codeblock>
<p>
Like the "[U]pdate" menu item in dselect, this doesn't update the
actual files on your computer, just apt's list of available packages.
To install a package, you just give apt-get the name, like this:
</p>
<codeblock>sudo apt-get install lynx</codeblock>
<p>
If apt-get determines that the packages requires other pckages to be
installed, it will show you the list and ask for confirmation.
It then downloads and installs the requested packages.
Removing packages is just as easy:
</p>
<codeblock>sudo apt-get remove lynx</codeblock>
<p>
[FIXME: using apt-cache to search for packages]
</p>
</section>

<section name="src"><title>Installing Packages from Source</title>
<p>
[FIXME: 'fink list', 'fink install']
</p>
<p>
For the meantime, see the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/doc/bundled/usage.php">Usage Document</link>.
</p>
</section>

</chapter>


<chapter filename="upgrade">
<title>Upgrading Fink</title>
<shorttitle>Upgrade</shorttitle>

<preface>
This chapter covers the procedures used to update your Fink
installation with the latest and greatest stuff.
</preface>

<section name="bin"><title>Upgrading using Binary Packages</title>
<p>
[FIXME: no special procedure, just hit update in dselect or run
'apt-get update' and install as normal (apt-0.5.3-7 or later
required)]
</p>
<p>
For the meantime, see the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="src"><title>Upgrading the Source Distribution</title>
<p>
[FIXME: selfupdate (available in 0.2.5 and later) or download
packages-### tarball and run inject.pl, then 'fink update-all']
</p>
<p>
For the meantime, see the
<link url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/download/upgrade.php">Upgrade Matrix</link>.
</p>
</section>

</chapter>


</document>
