<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<document filename="index">
<title>Running X11 on Darwin and Mac OS X</title>
<shorttitle>Running X11</shorttitle>
<cvsid>$Id: x11.xml,v 1.10 2001/10/26 20:57:48 chrisp Exp $</cvsid>

<preface>
<p>
This document is about running X11 / XFree86 / Xtools on Apple's Mac
OS X and Darwin systems.
It gives an introduction and a history of development, then goes on to
describe the current situation and the many options you have to use
X11 with or without Fink.
</p>
</preface>


<chapter filename="intro">
<title>Introduction</title>
<shorttitle>Intro</shorttitle>


<section name="def-x11"><title>What is X11?</title>
<p>
The <link url="http://www.x.org/">X Window System</link> Version 11,
or X11 for short, is a graphics display system with a
network-transparent client-server architecture.
It allows applications to draw pixels, lines, text, images, etc. on
your screen.
X11 also comes with additional libraries that let applications easily
draw user interfaces, i.e. buttons, text fields, and so on.
</p>
<p>
X11 is the de facto standard graphics system in the Unix world.
It comes with Linux, the *BSDs and most commercial Unix flavors.
Desktop environments like CDE, KDE and GNOME are based on it.
</p>
</section>

<section name="def-macosx"><title>What is Mac OS X?</title>
<p>
<link url="http://www.apple.com/macosx/">Mac OS X</link> is an
operating system produced by <link url="http://www.apple.com/">Apple
Computer</link>.
Like its predecessors NeXTStep and OpenStep, it is based on BSD and is
thus a member of the Unix OS family.
However, it comes with a proprietary graphics display system.
The graphics engine is called Quartz and the look and feel is called
Aqua, although the two names are often used interchangably.
</p>
</section>

<section name="def-darwin"><title>What is Darwin?</title>
<p>
<link url="http://www.opensource.apple.com/">Darwin</link> is
basically a stripped-down version of Mac OS X that is available free
of charge and with full source code.
It does not contain Quartz, Aqua, or any other related technology.
By default, it only offers a text console.
</p>
</section>

<section name="def-xfree86"><title>What is XFree86?</title>
<p>
<link url="http://www.xfree86.org/">XFree86</link> is an open source
implementation of X11.
It was initially developed to run on Intel x86 PCs, hence the name.
Nowadays, it runs on many architectures and operating systems,
including OS/2, Darwin, Mac OS X and Windows.
</p>
</section>

<section name="def-xtools"><title>What is Xtools?</title>
<p>
Xtools is a product of <link url="http://www.tenon.com/">Tenon
Intersystems</link>.
It is a version of X11 for Mac OS X, based on XFree86.
</p>
</section>

<section name="client-server"><title>Client and Server</title>
<p>
X11 has a client-server architecture.
There is one central program that does the actual drawing and
coordinates access by several applications; that is the server.
An application that wants to draw using X11 connects to the server and
tells it what to draw.
Thus applications are called clients in the X11 world.
</p>
<p>
X11 allows the server and the clients to be on different machines,
which often results in confusion over the terms.
In an environment with workstations and servers, you will run the X11
display server on the workstation machine and the applications (the X
clients) on the server machine.
So when talking about the "server", that means the X11 display server
program, not the machine hidden in your wardrobe.
</p>
</section>

<section name="rootless"><title>What does rootless mean?</title>
<p>
A little background:
X11 models the screen as a hierarchy of windows contained in each
other.
At the top of the hierarchy is a special window which is the size of
the screen and contains all other windows.
This window contains the desktop background and is called the "root
window".
</p>
<p>
Now back on topic:
Like any graphical environment, X11 was written to stand alone and
have full control over the screen.
In Mac OS X, Quartz already governs the screen, so one must make
arrangements if both are to get along together.
</p>
<p>
One arrangement is to let the two take turns.
Each environment gets a complete screen, but only one of them is
visible at a time and the user can switch between them.
This is called full-screen or rooted mode.
It is called rooted because there is a perfectly normal root window on
the X11 screen that works like on other systems.
</p>
<p>
Another arrangement is to mix the two environments window by window.
This eliminates the need to switch between two screens.
It also eliminates the X11 root window, because Quartz already takes
care of the desktop background.
Because there is no (visible) root window, this mode is called
"rootless".
It is the most comfortable way to use X11 on Mac OS X, so everyone is
trying to get it. <code>:-)</code>
</p>
</section>


<section name="wm"><title>What is a window manager?</title>
<p>
In most graphical environments the look of window frames (title bar,
close button, etc.) is defined by the system.
X11 is different.
With X11, the window frames (also called "decoration") are provided by
a separate program, called the window manager.
In most respects, the window manager is just another client
application; it is started the same way and talks to the X server
through the same channels.
</p>
<p>
There is a large number of different window managers to choose from.
<link url="http://www.xwinman.org/">xwinman.org</link> has a
comprehensive list.
Most popular ones allow the user to customize the appearance via
so-called <link url="http://www.themes.org/">themes</link>.
Many window managers also provide additional functionality, like pop
up menus in the root window, docks or launch buttons.
</p>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="history">
<title>History</title>
<shorttitle>History</shorttitle>

<p>[Sorry for the epic language, I couldn't resist...]</p>

<section name="early"><title>The early days</title>
<p>
In the beginning, there was void.
Darwin was in its infancy, Mac OS X was still in development and there
was no X11 implementation for both of them.
</p>
<p>
Then there came John Carmack and ported XFree86 to Mac OS X Server,
which was the only OS in the Darwin family available at that time.
Later that port was updated for XFree86 4.0 and Darwin 1.0 by Dave
Zarzycki.
The patches found their way into the Darwin CVS repository and slept
there, waiting for things to come.
</p>
</section>

<section name="xonx-forms"><title>XonX forms</title>
<p>
One fine day Torrey T. Lyons came along and gave the Darwin patches
the attention they had been waiting for.
Finally, he brought them to a new home, the official XFree86 CVS
repository.
This was the time of the Mac OS X Public Beta and Darwin 1.2.
XFree86 4.0.2 worked fine on Darwin, but on Mac OS X it required users
to log out of Aqua and go to the console to run it.
So Torrey gathered the <link
url="http://sourceforge.net/projects/xonx/">XonX team</link> around
him and set out on a voyage to bring XFree86 to Mac OS X.
</p>
<p>
At about the same time Tenon started to build Xtools, using XFree86
4.0 as the foundation.
</p>
</section>

<section name="root-or-not"><title>To root or not to root</title>
<p>
Soon the XonX team had XFree86 running in a fullscreen mode in
parallel to Quartz and was putting out test releases for adventurous
users.
The test releases were called XFree86-Aqua, or XAqua for short.
Since Torrey had taken the lead, changes went directly to
XFree86's CVS repository, which was heading towards the 4.1.0
release.
</p>
<p>
In the first stages interfacing with Quartz was done via a small
application called Xmaster.app (written with Carbon, then rewritten
with Cocoa).
Later that code was integrated into the X server proper, giving birth
to XDarwin.app.
Shared library support was also added at this time (and Tenon was
convinced to use this set of patches instead of their own to ensure
binary compatibility).
There was even good progress on a rootless mode (using the Carbon
API), but alas, it was too late to get it into XFree86 4.1.0.
And the rootless patch was free, and continued to float around the
net.
After XFree86 4.1.0 shipped with just the fullscreen mode, work on the
rootless mode continued, now using the Cocoa API.
An experimental rootless mode is now in XFree86's CVS repository.
</p>
<p>
In the meantime, Apple released Mac OS X 10.0 and Darwin 1.3,
and Tenon released Xtools 1.0 some weeks after that.
</p>
</section>

</chapter>



<chapter filename="inst-xfree86">
<title>Getting and Installing XFree86</title>
<shorttitle>Installing XFree86</shorttitle>

<section name="official-binary"><title>The Official Binaries</title>
<p>
The XFree86 project has an official binary distribution of XFree86
4.1.0.
You can find it on you local <link
url="http://www.xfree86.org/MIRRORS.shtml">XFree86 mirror</link> in
the directory <code>4.1.0/binaries/Darwin-ppc</code>.
Be sure to get the <code>Xprog.tgz</code> and <code>Xquartz.tgz</code>
tarballs even though they are marked as optional.
If you're unsure what you need, just download the whole directory.
Run the <code>Xinstall.sh</code> script as root to install the stuff.
(You might want to read the <link
url="http://www.xfree86.org/4.1.0/Install.html">official
instructions</link> before installing.)
You've now got XFree86 with a server that can do fullscreen, but not
rootless under Mac OS X.
</p>
</section>


<section name="official-source"><title>The Official Source</title>
<p>
If you've got the time to spare, you can build XFree86 4.1.0 from
source.
You can find the source on you local <link
url="http://www.xfree86.org/MIRRORS.shtml">XFree86 mirror</link> in
the directory <code>4.1.0/source</code>.
Grab all three <code>X410src-#.tgz</code> tarballs and extract them in
the same directory.
You can customize the build by putting macro definitions in the file
<code>config/cf/host.def</code> in the XFree86 source tree.
<!--
To build on pure Darwin, create the file
<code>config/cf/host.def</code> in the XFree86 source tree and put the
following line in it:
</p>
<codeblock>#define DarwinQuartzSupport NO</codeblock>
<p>
You can add further defines to that file if you want; see
-->
See
<code>config/cf/darwin.cf</code> for some hints.
(Note: Only the macros that have an #ifndef check around them can be
overwritten in host.def.)
</p>
<p>
When you're happy with your configuration, compile and install XFree86
with the following commands:
</p>
<codeblock>make World
sudo make install install.man</codeblock>
<p>
As with the official binaries, you've now got XFree86 with a server
that can do fullscreen, but not rootless under Mac OS X.
</p>
<p>
Note: The 4.1.0 source needs a small patch to compile on Mac OS X
10.1.
<link
url="http://fink.sourceforge.net/files/xfree86-4.1.0-10.1.patch">Download
it</link>, change into the <code>xc</code> directory and apply it with
<code>patch -p1 &lt;/path/to/xfree86-4.1.0-10.1.patch</code>.
</p>
</section>


<section name="latest-cvs"><title>The Latest Development Source</title>
<p>
If you have not only time, but also some nerves to spare you can get
the latest development version of XFree86 from the public CVS
repository.
This is the version that will eventually become XFree86 4.2.
It contains improvements made after 4.1.0 was released,
most notably OpenGL support (just software rendering, but useful
anyway) and a reimplementation of rootless mode.
Note that the code is under constant development; what you get today
is usually not the same as what you got yesterday.
</p>
<p>
To install, follow the <link url="http://www.xfree86.org/cvs/">XFree86
CVS</link> instructions to download the <code>xc</code> module.
Then, follow the source build instructions above.
</p>
</section>


<section name="xonx-bin"><title>The XonX binary test releases (XAqua,
XDarwin)</title>
<p>
In the time before 4.1.0 was released, the XonX team put out a series
of binary test releases with the name XAqua.
These releses are obsolete and should not be used.
</p>
<p>
With the introduction of rootless mode into XFree86's mainline CVS
(after 4.1.0 was released), the XonX team has once again started to
put out binary test releases, this time under the name XDarwin.
These releases are available from the <link url="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=18034&amp;release_id=43842">SourceForge
download page</link>.
You should also check the <link url="http://www.mrcla.com/XonX/">XonX
web page</link> for additional notes.
</p>
<p>
To install one of these releases, you must first install XFree86
4.1.0, e.g. the official binary release.
Then, extract the XDarwin tarball as root like this:
</p>
<codeblock>cd /
sudo gnutar xzvf /path/to/XDarwin1.0a3.tgz</codeblock>
<p>
That will update the X servers in /Applications and /usr/X11R6/bin.
For OpenGL support you need an additional tarball.
In the case of XDarwin 1.0a3 it's called <code>GLXSupport.tgz</code>.
It is installed the same way as the main tarball.
</p>
</section>


<section name="fink"><title>Installing through Fink</title>
<p>
Fink will let you install X11 in any way you like, but it
also provides XFree86 packages of its own.
If you use <code>fink install ...</code>, it will download the source
code and compile it on your computer.
If you use <code>apt-get install ...</code> or the
<code>dselect</code> frontend, it will download precompiled binary
packages, similar to the official XFree86 distribution.
</p>
<p>
The <code>xfree86-base</code> package contains all of XFree86 4.1.0
except the XDarwin servers.
There are several ways to add the servers to the mix.
The <code>xfree86-server</code> package installs the standard XFree86
4.1.0 servers, i.e. you'll only get fullscreen mode.
The <code>xfree86-rootless</code> package uses a (more or less) recent
CVS snapshot taken for Fink and uses that.
It contains a server with rootless mode plus the OpenGL libraries.
Finally, you have the option to install the server yourself; see
below.
In this case, you should only install <code>xfree86-base</code>, or
you'll risk that Fink overwrites your manually installed server.
</p>
</section>


<section name="macgimp"><title>MacGimp</title>
<p>
The downloadable installer currently offered by the MacGimp people
does not contain XFree86.
(It will overwrite some XFree86 configuration files, though.)
</p>
<p>
The CD that <link url="http://www.macgimp.com/">MacGimp, Inc.</link>
offers for sale reportedly contains XFree86.
It's still not quite clear what version it is; it may be a mix of
4.0.3, 4.1.0 and a development snapshot.
The server does rootless mode, using a patch from the time before
4.1.0.
</p>
</section>


<section name="rootless"><title>Roaming Rootless Servers</title>
<p>
There are various rootless server binaries roaming around the net.
These are not self-sufficient; they must be installed on top of
another XFree86 installation (e.g. the official 4.1.0 binaries or
Fink's <code>xfree86-base</code> package).
</p>
<p>
Installing such a server happens in two steps.
First, place the files you got in the right directories.
These are:</p>
<ul>
<li>XDarwin.app in /Applications</li>
<li>XDarwin in /usr/X11R6/bin</li>
<li>XDarwinStartup in /usr/X11R6/bin</li>
</ul>
<p>
Note that you must be the superuser ("root", run "sudo -s" to become
root) for this procedure.
If some of these items are already present, overwrite them.
Make sure that XDarwin and XDarwinStartup have the executable flag
set, e.g. <code>chmod 755 XDarwin XDarwinStartup</code>.
</p>
<p>
In the second step, you need to set some symbolic links in
/usr/X11R6/bin.
You can use these commands:
</p>
<codeblock>cd /usr/X11R6/bin
rm -f X XDarwinQuartz
ln -s XDarwinStartup X
ln -s /Applications/XDarwin.app/Contents/MacOS/XDarwin XDarwinQuartz</codeblock>
<p>
Now you should have an XFree86 installation that can run in rootless
mode.
</p>
</section>


<section name="fink-summary"><title>Fink package summary</title>
<p>
A quick summary of the install options and the Fink packages you
should install:
</p>
<pairtable labelt="Install Type" labeld="Fink packages">

<item><itemt>4.1.0 official binaries</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> only</p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 built from source</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> only</p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 binaries + XDarwin 1.0a#</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> only</p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 binaries + XDarwin 1.0a# + OpenGL tarball</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> and <code>system-opengl</code></p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 binaries + binary rootless server from other sources</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> only</p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>Latest CVS source</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>system-xfree86</code> and <code>system-opengl</code></p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 built via Fink</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>xfree86-base</code> and <code>xfree86-server</code></p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 + new rootless server, both built via Fink</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>xfree86-base</code> and <code>xfree86-rootless</code> (in
unstable)</p></itemd></item>

<item><itemt>4.1.0 base system built via Fink + binary rootless server</itemt>
<itemd><p><code>xfree86-base</code> only</p></itemd></item>

</pairtable>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="run-xfree86">
<title>Starting XFree86</title>
<shorttitle>Starting XFree86</shorttitle>


<section name="darwin"><title>Darwin</title>
<p>
On pure Darwin, XFree86 behaves like on any other Unix.
The usual way to start it is via <code>startx</code> from the console;
that starts both the server and some initial clients like the window
manager and a terminal emulator with a shell.
On pure Darwin it is not necessary to specify any parameters, so you
can just type:
</p>
<codeblock>startx</codeblock>
<p>
You can customize what is started through several files in your home
directory.
<code>.xinitrc</code> controls what clients get started.
<code>.xserverrc</code> controls server options and may even start a
different server.
If you're having trouble (as in, you only get a blank screen or
XFree86 drops you right back to the console), you can start
troubleshooting by moving these files out of the way.
When <code>startx</code> doesn't find these files, it will use safe
defaults that should always work.
</p>
<p>
Alternatively, you can start the server directly with one of the XDMCP
options, like this:
</p>
<codeblock>X -query remotehost</codeblock>
<p>
Details about this can be found in the <code>Xserver</code> manual
page.
</p>
<p>
Finally, there is the option to set up <code>xdm</code>; read its
manual page for details.
</p>
<p>
Note: If you're running Mac OS X, you can type <code>&gt;console</code>
at the login window and you'll get a text console that is
equivalent to pure Darwin.
You can use all of the start methods outlined above, with the
exception of <code>xdm</code>.
</p>
</section>


<section name="macosx-41"><title>Mac OS X + XFree86 4.1.0</title>
<p>
This section describes starting the server from XFree86 4.1.0.
That also covers the old-style rootless servers still circulating;
they are based on a late development version of XFree86 4.1.0 and
sufficiently similar.
</p>
<p>
There are basically two ways to start XFree86 under Mac OS X.
One is double-clicking the XDarwin.app application in your
Applications folder.
When you start XFree86 this way it already knows you are running under
Quartz (or Aqua or whatever you choose to call the
graphical environment of Mac OS X).
It will fire up fullscreen mode automatically and start your clients
from the <code>.xinitrc</code> file.
However, there is no way to get rootless mode by double-clicking the
application.
</p>
<p>
The other way to start XFree86 under Mac OS X is via
<code>startx</code> from Terminal.app.
If you start the server this way, you must tell it that it should run
in parallel with Quartz.
You do this by passing the <code>-quartz</code> option, like this:
</p>
<codeblock>startx -- -quartz</codeblock>
<p>
That will start up the server in fullscreen mode, plus the clients in
your <code>.xinitrc</code>.
If the server you have supports rootless operation, you can start it
in rootless mode with the <code>-rootless</code> option:
</p>
<codeblock>startx -- -rootless</codeblock>
</section>


<section name="macosx-42"><title>Mac OS X + XFree86 CVS</title>
<p>
Recent development versions of XFree86 (this includes the XDarwin
1.0a# test releases from the XonX project and the
<code>xfree86-rootless</code> package from Fink 0.2.4 and later) come
with rootless mode built in.
They let you choose between fullscreen and rootless mode in a dialog
at startup, just double-click the XDarwin.app application.
You can disable the dialog and set XDarwin to always use the mode of
your choice in the Preferences dialog.
</p>
<p>
You can still use startx and the command line options if you prefer.
The options to choose the mode have changed slightly.
The <code>-quartz</code> option no longer selects fullscreen mode, but
rather uses the default mode set in the preferences.
The <code>-fullscreen</code> option forces fullscreen mode, while
<code>-rootless</code> forces rootless mode.
</p>
</section>


<section name="xinitrc"><title>The .xinitrc File</title>
<p>
If a file named <code>.xinitrc</code> exists in your home directory,
it will be used to start some initial X clients, e.g. the window
manager and some xterms or a desktop environment like GNOME.
The <code>.xinitrc</code> file is a shell script that contains the
commands to do this.
It is <em>not</em> necessary to put the usual <code>#!/bin/sh</code>
in the first line and to set the executable bit on the file;
xinit will still know how to run it through a shell.
</p>
<p>
When there is no <code>.xinitrc</code> file in your home directory,
XFree86 will use its default file,
<code>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xinit/xinitrc</code>.
You can use the default file as a starting point for your own
.xinitrc:
</p>
<codeblock>cp /usr/X11R6/lib/X11/xinit/xinitrc ~/.xinitrc</codeblock>
<p>
If you're using Fink, you should source <code>init.sh</code> right at
the beginning to make sure the environment is set up correctly.
</p>
<p>
You can put fairly arbitrary commands in an <code>.xinitrc</code>, but
there are some cheavats.
First, the shell that interprets the file will by default wait for
every program to finish before it starts the next one.
If you want several programs to run in parallel, you must tell the
shell to put them "in the background" by adding a <code>&amp;</code> at
the end of the line.
</p>
<p>
Second, <code>xinit</code> waits for the <code>.xinitrc</code> script
to finish and interprets that as "the session has ended, I should kill
the X server now, too".
This means that the last command of your <code>.xinitrc</code> must
not be run in the background and it should be a long-living program.
Customarily, the window manager is used for this purpose.
In fact, most window managers assume that <code>xinit</code> is
waiting for them to finish and use this to make the "Log out" entry in
their menus work.
(Note: To save some memory and CPU cycles, you can put an
<code>exec</code> before the last line like in the examples below.)
</p>
<p>
A simple example that starts up GNOME:
</p>
<codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.sh
exec gnome-session</codeblock>
<p>
A more complex example that turns the X11 bell off, starts some clients
and finally executes the Enlightenment window manager:
</p>
<codeblock>source /sw/bin/init.sh

xset b off

xclock -geometry -0+0 &amp;
xterm &amp;
xterm &amp;

exec enlightenment</codeblock>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="xtools">
<title>Xtools</title>
<shorttitle>Xtools</shorttitle>


<section name="install"><title>Installing Xtools</title>
<p>
Now that's easy for a change.
Get the installer, double-click it, and follow the instructions.
Be sure to select the startup volume when asked.
</p>
<p>
If you're using Fink, you should install the
<code>system-xtools</code> package after you've installed Xtools.
That package will not install any files, it will just check that the
libraries etc. are there and act as a placeholder in Fink's dependency
system.
</p>
</section>


<section name="run"><title>Running Xtools</title>
<p>
To run Xtools, double-click Xtools.app in your Applications folder.
Like XFree86, Xtools will run the clients you specify in your
<code>.xinitrc</code> file.
Xtools additionally allows you to start clients via the menu.
</p>
</section>


<section name="opengl"><title>OpenGL Notes</title>
<p>
Xtools does hardware-accelerated OpenGL in rootless mode and comes
with the libraries to support it.
While the main libGL library is fine, the libGLU and libglut libraries
are only present as static libraries, which is not sufficient for
full binary compatibility with XFree86.
Also, some headers are missing.
Fink doesn't offer a workaround at this time.
Hopefully this will be fixed in Xtools 1.1 once it is released.
</p>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="other">
<title>Other X11 Possibilities</title>
<shorttitle>Other Stuff</shorttitle>


<section name="vnc"><title>VNC</title>
<p>
VNC is a network-capable graphics display system similar in design to
X11.
However, it works at a lower level, making implementation easier.
With the Xvnc server and a Mac OS X display client, it is possible to
run X11 applications with Mac OS X.
Jeff Whitaker's <link
url="http://www.cdc.noaa.gov/~jsw/macosx_xvnc/">Xvnc page</link> has
more information on that.
</p>
</section>


<section name="wiredx"><title>WiredX</title>
<p>
<link url="http://www.jcraft.com/wiredx/">WiredX</link> is an X11
server written in Java.
It also supports rootless mode.
An Installer.app package is available at the web site.
</p>
</section>


<section name="exodus"><title>eXodus</title>
<p>
According to the website, <link
url="http://www.powerlan-usa.com/exodus/">eXodus 8</link> by Powerlan
USA runs natively on Mac OS X.
It is unknown what codebase it uses and whether/how it supports local
clients.
Because of this, there is no special support for eXodus in Fink.
If you have more info, please throw it my way.
</p>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="trouble">
<title>Troubleshooting XFree86</title>
<shorttitle>Troubleshooting</shorttitle>

<section name="immedate-quit"><title>When I launch XDarwin, it quits
or crashes almost immediately</title>
<p>
First of all: Don't Panic!
There are lots of things than can go wrong with XFree86, and a good
number of them can cause startup failures.
Further, it is not unusual that XDarwin crashes when it experiences
startup problems.
This section tries to provide a comprehensive list of problems you may
come across.
But first, you need to gather two important pieces of information:
</p>
<p>
<em>XDarwin version.</em>
You can find the XDarwin version in the Finder by clicking
<em>once</em> on the XDarwin icon and then selecting "Show Info"
from the menu.
The version is only incremented when a new binary test release is made
by the XonX project, so "1.0a1" may actually be any version between
1.0a1 and 1.0a2.
</p>
<p>
<em>Error messages.</em>
These are essential in pinpointing the particular problem you
experience.
How you get the error messages depends on how you started XDarwin.
If you ran <code>startx</code> from a Terminal window, you'll have the
messages right there in that window.
Remember that you can scroll up.
If you started XDarwin by double-clicking the icon, the messages end
up in the system log, which you can access through the Console
application in the Utilities folder.
Be sure to pick the right set of messages, i.e. the last one.
</p>
<p>
We'll start with a list of the messages you may see:
</p>

<codeblock>_XSERVTransmkdir: Owner of /tmp/.X11-unix should be set to root</codeblock>
<codeblock>_IceTransmkdir: Owner of /tmp/.ICE-unix should be set to root</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Harmless.
X11 creates hidden directories in /tmp to store the socket "files" for
local connections.
For security reasons, X11 prefers if these directories are owned by
root, but since they are world-writable anyway it will still run
without any problems.
(Note: It's quite hard to have these dirs owned by root, as Mac OS X
wipes out /tmp on reboots and XDarwin doesn't run with root privileges
and doesn't need to.)
</p>

<codeblock>cat: /Users/chrisp/.Xauthority: No such file or directory</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Mostly harmless.
It is unknown where these messages come from and they seem to have no
impact on operations.
You can get rid of them by running <code>touch .Xauthority</code> in
your home directory.
</p>

<codeblock>Gdk-WARNING **: locale not supported by C library</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Harmless.
This just means what it says and won't keep the application from
working.
For more information, <xref section="locale">see below</xref>.
</p>

<codeblock>Gdk-WARNING **: locale not supported by Xlib, locale set to C
Gdk-WARNING **: can not set locale modifiers</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Bad, but not fatal.
These messages may appear in addition to the one above.
This indicates that XFree86's locale data files are not present.
It appears that this happens unreproducably when building XFree86 from
source.
Most applications will still work, GNU Emacs is a noteable exception.
</p>

<codeblock>Unable to open keymapping file USA.keymapping.
Reverting to kernel keymapping.</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Often fatal.
This can happen with XDarwin 1.0a1, with the "Load from file"
keymapping option enabled.
That version needs a full path when the file to load is set via the
Preferences dialog, but searches automatically when it is passed on
the command line.
The message will usually be followed by the "assert" message shown
below.
To fix this, follow the directions below.
</p>

<codeblock>Fatal server error:
assert failed on line 454 of darwinKeyboard.c!</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Fatal.
Changes Apple made in Mac OS X 10.1 broke the code in XFree86 that
reads the keyboard layout from the operating system kernel;
the message above is the result of that.
You must use the "Load from file" keymapping option on Mac OS X 10.1.
The setting is in the XDarwin Preferences dialog.
Be sure that a file is selected (i.e. use the "Pick file" button) -
simply activating the check box may not be sufficient with some
versions of XDarwin.
If you can't get to the Preferences dialog because XDarwin closes
before you get a chance, run it from Terminal with the command
<code>startx -- -quartz -keymap USA.keymapping</code>.
This usually allows XDarwin to start up, and you can then make the
permanent choice in the Preferences dialog.
</p>

<codeblock>Warning: no access to tty (Inappropriate ioctl for device).
Thus no job control in this shell.</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Mostly harmless.
XDarwin 1.0a2 and later launch an interactive shell behind the scenes
to run your client startup file (.xinitrc).
This was done so that you don't have to add statements to set up PATH
in that file.
Some shells complain that they're not connected to a real terminal,
but that can be ignored since that shell instance is not used for
anything that requires job control or the like.
</p>

<codeblock>Fatal server error:
failed to connect as window server!</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Fatal.
This means that the console-mode server (for pure Darwin) got started
while you were logged into Aqua.
Usually this happens when you installed the official XFree86 binary
distribution and left out the Xquartz.tgz tarball.
It can also happen when the symlinks in /usr/X11R6/bin are messed up
or when you used the command <code>XDarwin</code> to start the
server.
</p>
<p>
In any case, you can run <code>ls -l /usr/X11R6/bin/X*</code> and
check the output.
You should see four relevant entries:
<code>X</code>, a symlink pointing at <code>XDarwinStartup</code>;
<code>XDarwin</code>, an executable file (this is the console
mode server);
<code>XDarwinQuartz</code>, a symlink pointing at
<code>/Applications/XDarwin.app/Contents/MacOS/XDarwin</code>; and
<code>XDarwinStartup</code>, a small executable file.
If any of these are missing or pointing at different files, you need
to fix that.
How you do that depends on the method you used to install XFree86.
</p>

<codeblock>The XKEYBOARD keymap compiler (xkbcomp) reports:
&gt; Error:            Can't find file "unknown" for geometry include
&gt;                   Exiting
&gt;                   Abandoning geometry file "(null)"
Errors from xkbcomp are not fatal to the X server</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Mostly harmless.
As the message says, it is not fatal.
To my knowledge, XDarwin doesn't use the XKB extension at all.
Probably some client program tries to use it anyway...
</p>

<codeblock>startx: Command not found.</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Fatal.
This can happen with XDarwin 1.0a2 and 1.0a3 when your shell
initialization files are not set up to add /usr/X11R6/bin to the PATH
variable.
If you use Fink and haven't changed your default shell, adding
<code>source /sw/bin/init.csh</code> to <code>.cshrc</code> in your
home directory (as recommended by the Fink instructions) should be
sufficient.
</p>

<codeblock>Xlib: connection to ":0.0" refused by server
Xlib: Client is not authorized to connect to Server</codeblock>
<p>
Class: Fatal.
The client programs can't connect to the display server (XDarwin)
because they use bogus authentication data.
This can be caused by some VNC installations,
by running XDarwin through sudo,
and probably some other freak accidents.
The usual fix is to delete the .Xauthority file (which stores the
authentication data) in your home directory and re-create an empty
file:
</p>
<codeblock>cd
rm .Xauthority
touch .Xauthority</codeblock>

<p>
more to be written...
</p>


<!--
<p>
This usually happens when your <code>.xinitrc</code> isn't set up
correctly.
See also: <link url="run-xfree86.php#xinitrc">The .xinitrc File</link>.
</p>
<p>
What happens is that the <code>.xinitrc</code> is run and for some
reason terminates almost immediately.
<code>xinit</code> interprets this as "the user's session has ended"
and kills XDarwin.
Some common problems that lead to this:
</p>
<ul>

<li><p>
All apps are started in the background.
Instead the last one must be started if the foreground (no
<code>&amp;</code> at the end of the line), or better with
<code>exec</code>.
</p></li>

<li><p>
The app that should run in the foreground can't be found.
This can happen when you give just the name without the path
(e.g. <code>xterm</code>), but forget to set the shell's search path
(environment variable PATH).
Neither /usr/X11R6/bin nor /sw/bin are in the default path.
If you use Fink, just add an <code>source /sw/bin/init.sh</code> to
the start of the <code>.xinitrc</code>.
To set the path manually, use this piece:
</p>
<codeblock>PATH=$PATH:/usr/X11R6/bin
export PATH</codeblock>
</li>

<li><p>
The app that should run in the foreground doesn't start or quits
immediately for some other reason.
There are many possibilities here, like missing libraries or missing
configuration files.
WindowMaker for instance requires that you run
<code>wmaker.inst</code> once before using it.
A good troubleshooting tactic in this situation is to replace the
forground app with <code>xterm</code> and launch it manually from the
xterm that comes up.
This way you can see diagnostic messages.
</p></li>

</ul>
<p>
Of course, there's always the last reason: a bug in XDarwin.
But most of the time, it really boils down to one of the above, even
when XDarwin crashes after some seconds.
</p>
-->
</section>


<section name="black"><title>Black icons in the GNOME panel or in the
menu of a GNOME application</title>
<p>
A common problem is that icons or other images are displayed as black
rectangles or black outlines.
Ultimately, this is caused by limitations in the operating system
kernel.
The problem has been reported to Apple, but so far they seem unwilling
to fix it; see the filed <link
url="http://www.opensource.apple.com/bugs/X/Kernel/2691632.html">Darwin
bug report</link> for details.
</p>
<p>
The current situation is that the MIT-SHM extension of the X11
protocol is practically unusable on Darwin and Mac OS X.
There are two ways to turn the protocol extension off: in the server
or in the clients.
The XFree86 servers installed by Fink (i.e. the xfree86-server and
xfree86-rootless packages) have it turned off.
The GIMP and the GNOME panel have been innoculated as well.
If you experience black icons in another application, start that
application with the <code>--no-xshm</code> command line option.
</p>
</section>


<section name="keyboard"><title>The keyboard doesn't work in XFree86</title>
<p>
This is a known problem that so far seems to affect only portables
(PowerBook, iBook).
To work around this, the "Load from file" keymapping option was
implemented.
Nowadays it has become the default because the old method (reading the
mapping from the kernel) stopped working with Mac OS X 10.1.
If you haven't enabled the option already, you can do so in the
XDarwin preferences dialog.
Check the "Load from file" checkbox and select the keymapping file to
load.
After restarting XDarwin, your keyboard should mostly work (see
below).
</p>
<p>
If you're starting XFree86 from the command line, you can pass the
name of the keymapping file to load as an option, as in:
</p>
<codeblock>startx -- -quartz -keymap USA.keymapping</codeblock>
</section>


<section name="delete-key"><title>The Backspace key doesn't work</title>
<p>
This can happen when you use the "Load keymapping from file" option
described above.
The mapping files describe the backspace key as "Delete", not as
"Backspace".
You can correct that by putting the following line in your .xinitrc
file:
</p>
<codeblock>xmodmap -e "keycode 59 = BackSpace"</codeblock>
<p>
If I remember correctly, XDarwin 1.0a2 and later have code that
correctly maps the Backspace key automatically.
</p>
</section>


<section name="locale"><title>"Warning: locale not supported by C library"</title>
<p>
These messages are quite common, but harmless.
It just means what it says - internationalization is not supported
through the standard C library, the program will use the default
English messages, date formats, and so on.
There are several ways to deal with this:
</p>
<ul>
<li><p>
Just ignore the messages.
</p></li>
<li><p>
Get rid of the messages by unsetting the environment variable LANG.
Note that this will also turn internationalization off in programs
that actually support it (via gettext/libintl).
Example for .xinitrc:
</p>
<codeblock>unset LANG</codeblock>
<p>
Example for .cshrc:
</p>
<codeblock>unsetenv LANG</codeblock>
</li>
<li><p>
Use the <code>libxpg4</code> Fink package.
It builds a small library that contains working locale functions and
arranges that it is loaded before the system libraries (using the
DYLD_INSERT_LIBRARIES environment variable).
You may have to set the LANG environment variable to a fully qualified
value, e.g. <code>de_DE.ISO_8859-1</code> instead of <code>de</code>
or <code>de_DE</code>.
</p></li>
<li><p>
Ask Apple to include proper locale support in a future version of Mac
OS X.
</p></li>
</ul>
</section>


</chapter>


<chapter filename="tips">
<title>Usage Tips</title>
<shorttitle>Tips</shorttitle>


<section name="terminal-app"><title>Launching X11 apps from Terminal.app</title>
<p>
To launch X11 applications from a Terminal.app window, you must set
the environment variable "DISPLAY".
This variable tells the applications where to find the X11 window
server.
In the default setup - XDarwin runs on the same machine, your shell is
tcsh - you can set the variable as follows:
</p>
<codeblock>setenv DISPLAY :0.0</codeblock>
<p>
A nice setup is to have XDarwin.app started when you log in (settable
in the Login panel of the System Preferences) and add the following to
your .cshrc:
</p>
<codeblock>if (! $?DISPLAY) then
  setenv DISPLAY :0.0
endif</codeblock>
<p>
This sets DISPLAY automatically in every shell.
It doesn't override the current value when DISPLAY is already set,
though.
This way you can still run X11 applications remotely or through ssh
with X11 tunneling.
</p>
</section>


<section name="open"><title>Launching Aqua apps from an xterm</title>
<p>
One way to launch Aqua applications from an xterm (or any other shell,
actually) is the <code>open</code> command.
Some examples:
</p>
<codeblock>open /Applications/TextEdit.app
open SomeDocument.rtf
open -a /Applications/TextEdit.app index.html</codeblock>
<p>
The second example opens the document in the application that is
associated with it, the third example explicitly gives an application
to use.
</p>
</section>


<section name="copy-n-paste"><title>Copy and Paste</title>
<p>
Copy and Paste generally works between the Aqua and X11 environments.
There are still some bugs.
Emacs is reported to be picky about the current selection.
Copy and paste from Classic to X11 doesn't work.
</p>
<p>
Anyway, the trick is to use the respective methods of the environment
you're in.
To transfer text from Aqua to X11, use Cmd-C in Aqua, then bring the
destination window to the front and use the middle mouse button to
paste.
To transfer text from X11 to Aqua, simply select the text with the
mouse in X11, then use Cmd-V in Aqua to paste it.
</p>
<p>
The X11 system actually has several separate clipboards (called "cut
buffers" in X11 speak), and some applications have weird views which
one should be used.
In particular, pasting into GNU Emacs or XEmacs sometimes doesn't work
because of this.
The program <code>autocutsel</code> can help here; it automatically
synchronizes the two main cut buffers.
To run it, install the autocutsel Fink package and add the following
line to your .xinitrc:
</p>
<codeblock>autocutsel &amp;</codeblock>
<p>
(Make sure it's <em>before</em> the line that exec's the window
manager and never returns! Don't just add it at the end, it won't
be executed.)
</p>
</section>


</chapter>

</document>
