<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../finkdoc.dtd">
<document filename="index" lang="en">
    <title>General Fink security policy for accepted packages.</title>
    <shorttitle>Security Policy</shorttitle>
    <cvsid>$Id: sec-policy.en.xml,v 1.1 2004/06/15 18:19:01 dmalloc Exp $</cvsid>
    <preface>
        <p>This document explains security incident handling for packages that
            have been accepted by Fink. While main responsibility for every
            accepted package in Fink remains with the respective maintainer,
            Fink recognises the necessity to offer a uniform policy how to react
            to security incidents found in software which are offered as Fink
            packages. </p>
    </preface>
    <chapter filename="respo">
        <title>Responsibility</title>
        <shorttitle>Respo</shorttitle>
        <section name="who">
            <title>Who is responsible?</title>
            <p>Every Fink package has a Maintainer. The maintainer of a
                particular package can be found by typing <code>fink info
                packagename</code> at the command line prompt. This will return
                a listing with a field similar to this one: <tt>Maintainer: Fink
                    Core Group
                &lt;fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net&gt;</tt>. The
                maintainer has full responsibility for his/her package(s).</p>
        </section>
        <section name="contact">
            <title>Whom shall I contact?</title>
            <p>If there are security incidents within a certain piece of
                packaged software, you should notify the maintainer of that
                packages as well as the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> The email of
                the maintainer can be found within the packages info, the email
                of the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> is
                fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net </p>
        </section>
        <section name="prenotifications">
            <title>Pre-notifications</title>
            <p>Serious security incidents in a Fink packaged software might
                require you to pre-notify the maintainer of that package. Since
                it is possible that the maintainer cannot be reached timely,
                pre-notification should always be submitted to the <em>Fink Core
                Team.</em> at fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net</p>
        </section>
        <section name="response">
            <title>Response</title>
            <p>Submitted reports about a security incident will be answered by
                the <em>Fink Core Team.</em>, each Maintainer is required by
                Fink to acknowledge the reported issue individually. In the
                unlikely event that the maintainer is not available and the
                maintainer has not acknowledged the report within 24 hours, a
                note should be sent to the <em>Fink Core Team</em> informing the
                team that the maintainer might be unresponsive. </p>
            <p>In the event, that you attempted to notify the maintainer of the
                package in question but the mail system returned a delivery
                error for that email you should notify the <em>Fink Core
                Team.</em> immediately informing them that the maintainer is
                unreachable and this package may be updated irrespective of the
                maintainer. </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="severity">
        <title>Response times and immediate actions.</title>
        <shorttitle>responses</shorttitle>
        <preface>
            <p>Response time and actions taken greatly depend on the loss
                severity that is introduced by a particular flaw in the software
                that has been packaged for Fink. This is a work in progress, it
                is meant as a pointer for the package maintainers. In any case
                the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> will take immediate action whenever
                it feels it is necessary ti protect the Fink using community.</p>
        </preface>
        <section name="resptimes">
            <title>Response times</title>
            <p>Each package should strive to meet the following response times.
                For some type of vulnerabilities the <em>Fink Core Team.</em>
                might choose to take immediate action. If that is the case one
                of the Core Team members will notify the maintainer of the
                package in question.</p>
            <itemtable labeld="Repsonse time" labelt="Vulnerability">
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote root exploit</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>immediate</em>; maximum: <em>12</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local root exploit</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>12</em> hours; maximum: <em>36</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote DOS</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>6</em> hours; maximum: <em>12</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local DOS</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>24</em> hours; maximum: <em>72</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote data corruption</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>12</em> hours; maximum: <em>24</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local data corruption</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>24</em> hours; maximum: <em>72</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
            </itemtable>
        </section>
        <section name="forced">
            <title>Forced updates</title>
            <p>A member of the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> might choose to update a
                package without waiting for the packages maintainer to take
                action. This is called a <strong>forced update.</strong>. Not
                meeting the maximum required response time for a particular
                vulnerability in a Fink package also results in a <strong>forced
                update</strong> of that package.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="sources">
        <title>Incident Sources</title>
        <shorttitle>isource</shorttitle>
        <section name="sources">
            <title>Acceptable incident Sources.</title>
            <p>As submitter of a security incident in a fink packaged software
                you have to ensure that the vulnerability of the software also
                exists on Mac OS X. It the responsibility of the notifying party
                to ensure that one of the following sources reinforces the
                reported issue for the particular software in question.</p>
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <em>AIXAPAR</em>: AIX APAR (Authorised Problem Analysis Report)</li>
                <li>
                    <em>APPLE</em>: Apple Security Update</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ATSTAKE</em>: @stake security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>AUSCERT</em>: AUSCERT advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BID</em>: Security Focus Bugtraq ID database entry</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BINDVIEW</em>: BindView security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BUGTRAQ</em>: Posting to Bugtraq mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CALDERA</em>: Caldera security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CERT</em>: CERT/CC Advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CERT-VN</em>: CERT/CC vulnerability note</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CIAC</em>: DOE CIAC (Computer Incident Advisory Center) bulletins</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CONECTIVA</em>: Conectiva Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CONFIRM:</em> URL to location where vendor confirms that
                    the problem exists</li>
                <li>
                    <em>DEBIAN</em>: Debian Linux Security Information</li>
                <li>
                    <em>EEYE</em>: eEye security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>EL8</em>: EL8 advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ENGARDE</em>: En Garde Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FEDORA</em>: Fedora Project security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FULLDISC</em>: Full-Disclosure mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FreeBSD</em>: FreeBSD security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>GENTOO</em>: Gentoo Linux security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>HERT</em>: HERT security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>HP</em>: HP security advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>IBM</em>: IBM ERS/BRS advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>IMMUNIX</em>: Immunix Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>INFOWAR</em>: INFOWAR security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ISS</em>: ISS Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>KSRT</em>: KSR[T] Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>L0PHT</em>: L0pht Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>MANDRAKE</em>: Linux-Mandrake advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>MLIST</em>: generic reference form for miscellaneous
                    mailing lists</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NAI</em>: NAI Labs security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NETECT</em>: Netect security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NetBSD</em>: NetBSD Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>OPENBSD</em>: OpenBSD Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>REDHAT</em>: Security advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>RSI</em>: Repent Security, Inc. security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SEKURE</em>: Sekure security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SF-INCIDENTS</em>: posting to Security Focus Incidents
                    mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SGI</em>: SGI Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SLACKWARE</em>: Slackware security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SNI</em>: Secure Networks, Inc. security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUN</em>: Sun security bulletin</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUNALERT</em>: Sun security alert</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUNBUG</em>: Sun bug ID</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUSE</em>: SuSE Linux: Security Announcements</li>
                <li>
                    <em>TRUSTIX</em>: Trustix Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>TURBO</em>: TurboLinux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>VULN-DEV</em>: Posting to VULN-DEV mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>VULNWATCH</em>: VulnWatch mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>XF</em>: X-Force Vulnerability Database</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CVE</em>: CVE Candidates </li>
            </ol>
            <p>The above keywords are in full compliance with the CVE
                recommended keyword list found <link
                url="http://www.cve.mitre.org/cve/refs/refkey.html">here</link>. </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="updating">
        <title>Security update procedure.</title>
        <shorttitle>secup</shorttitle>
        <section name="procedure">
            <title>Adding security related updates.</title>
            <p>Security updates may only be applied once they have been verified
                by the original Author of the software which has been packaged
                for Fink and found to be vulnerable to a security issue. Before
                an update one or more of the following conditions <em>have</em>
                to be met:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The author of the software has contacted the maintainer
                    and/or the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> directly providing a
                    patch or work around to a vulnerability.</li>
                <li>One of the keyword donated sources has issued a security
                    bulletin with updates sources for the software packaged for
                    Fink in question.</li>
                <li>A patch has been issued to one of the following keyword
                    denoted sources: BUGTRAQ,FULLDISC,SF-INCIDENTS,VULN-DEV.</li>
                <li>An official security bulletin has been issued and assigned
                    CVE Candidate status, describing the vulnerability,
                    supplying a work around, patch or link to updated sources.</li>
                <li>Pre-notification has been sent to the maintainer and/or the
                        <em>Fink Core Team</em> directly providing a patch or
                    work around to a vulnerability asking to take action.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="moving">
            <title>Unstable to stable moves.</title>
            <p>Security updates for a specific package will first be applied to
                the unstable tree. After a waiting period of no less than
                <em>12</em> hours the packages' info file will be moved into the
                stable tree as well. The retention period shall be used to
                carefully observe whether the updated package works and the
                security update does not introduce any new issues.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</document>
