<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document SYSTEM "../finkdoc.dtd">
<document filename="index" lang="en">
    <title>General Fink security policy for accepted packages.</title>
    <shorttitle>Security Policy</shorttitle>
    <cvsid>$Id: sec-policy.en.xml,v 1.8 2004/06/25 21:13:51 dmalloc Exp $</cvsid>
    <preface>
        <p>This document explains security incident handling for packages that
            have been accepted by Fink. While the main responsibility for every
            accepted package in Fink remains with the respective maintainer,
            Fink recognizes the necessity to offer a uniform policy on how to
            react to security incidents found in software which are offered as
            Fink packages. </p>
    </preface>
    <chapter filename="respo">
        <title>Responsibility</title>
        <shorttitle>Respo</shorttitle>
        <section name="who">
            <title>Who is responsible?</title>
            <p>Every Fink package has a Maintainer. The maintainer of a
                particular package can be found by typing <code>fink info
                packagename</code> at the command line prompt. This will return
                a listing with a field similar to this one: <tt>Maintainer: Fink
                    Core Group
                &lt;fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net&gt;</tt>. The
                maintainer has full responsibility for his/her package(s).</p>
        </section>
        <section name="contact">
            <title>Whom shall I contact?</title>
            <p>If there are security incidents within a certain piece of
                packaged software, you should notify the maintainer of that
                package as well as the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> The email of the
                maintainer can be found within the packages info, and the email
                of the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> is
                fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net </p>
        </section>
        <section name="prenotifications">
            <title>Pre-notifications</title>
            <p>Serious security incidents in software packaged by Fink might
                require you to pre-notify the maintainer of that package. Since
                it is possible that the maintainer cannot be reached in a timely
                manner, pre-notification should always also be submitted to the
                    <em>Fink Security Team.</em> Each team members e-mail is
                listed individually later on in this document. Please note that
                fink-core@lists.sourceforge.net is a publically archived mailing
                list, private pre-notifications should <em>never</em> be sent to
                that list.</p>
        </section>
        <section name="response">
            <title>Response</title>
            <p>Submitted reports about a security incident will be answered by
                the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> Each maintainer is required by Fink
                to acknowledge the reported issue individually. In the unlikely
                event that the maintainer is not available and the maintainer
                has not acknowledged the report within 24 hours, a note should
                be sent to the <em>Fink Core Team</em> informing the team that
                the maintainer might be unresponsive. </p>
            <p>In the event that you attempted to notify the maintainer of the
                package in question but the mail system returned a delivery
                error for that email you should notify the <em>Fink Core
                Team</em> immediately to inform them that the maintainer is
                unreachable and that the package may be updated irrespective of
                the maintainer. </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="severity">
        <title>Response times and immediate actions.</title>
        <shorttitle>responses</shorttitle>
        <preface>
            <p>Response time and actions taken greatly depend on the severity of
                the loss introduced by a particular flaw in the software that
                has been packaged for Fink. In any case the <em>Fink Core
                Team</em> will take immediate action whenever it feels it is
                necessary to protect the Fink user community.</p>
        </preface>
        <section name="resptimes">
            <title>Response times</title>
            <p>Each package should strive to meet the following response times.
                For some types of vulnerabilities the <em>Fink Core Team</em>
                might choose to take immediate action. If that is the case one
                of the Core Team members will notify the maintainer of the
                package in question. Also, keep in mind that while we strive to
                meet these response times, Fink is a volunteer effort, and they
                cannot be guaranteed.</p>
            <itemtable labeld="Repsonse time" labelt="Vulnerability">
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote root exploit</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>immediate</em>; maximum: <em>12</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local root exploit</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>12</em> hours; maximum: <em>36</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote DOS</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>6</em> hours; maximum: <em>12</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local DOS</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>24</em> hours; maximum: <em>72</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>remote data corruption</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>12</em> hours; maximum: <em>24</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
                <item>
                    <itemt>local data corruption</itemt>
                    <itemd>
                        <p>minimum: <em>24</em> hours; maximum: <em>72</em> hours.</p>
                    </itemd>
                </item>
            </itemtable>
        </section>
        <section name="forced">
            <title>Forced updates</title>
            <p>A member of the <em>Fink Core Team</em> might choose to update a
                package without waiting for the package's maintainer to take
                action. This is called a <strong>forced update</strong>. Not
                meeting the maximum required response time for a particular
                vulnerability in a Fink package also results in a <strong>forced
                update</strong> of that package.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="sources">
        <title>Incident Sources</title>
        <shorttitle>isource</shorttitle>
        <section name="sources">
            <title>Acceptable Incident Sources.</title>
            <p>As submitter of a security incident in Fink-packaged software you
                have to ensure that the vulnerability of the software also
                exists on Mac OS X. It the responsibility of the notifying party
                to ensure that one of the following sources reinforces the
                reported issue for the particular software in question.</p>
            <ol>
                <li>
                    <em>AIXAPAR</em>: AIX APAR (Authorised Problem Analysis Report)</li>
                <li>
                    <em>APPLE</em>: Apple Security Update</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ATSTAKE</em>: @stake security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>AUSCERT</em>: AUSCERT advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BID</em>: Security Focus Bugtraq ID database entry</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BINDVIEW</em>: BindView security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>BUGTRAQ</em>: Posting to Bugtraq mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CALDERA</em>: Caldera security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CERT</em>: CERT/CC Advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CERT-VN</em>: CERT/CC vulnerability note</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CIAC</em>: DOE CIAC (Computer Incident Advisory Center) bulletins</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CONECTIVA</em>: Conectiva Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CONFIRM:</em> URL to location where vendor confirms that
                    the problem exists</li>
                <li>
                    <em>DEBIAN</em>: Debian Linux Security Information</li>
                <li>
                    <em>EEYE</em>: eEye security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>EL8</em>: EL8 advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ENGARDE</em>: En Garde Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FEDORA</em>: Fedora Project security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FULLDISC</em>: Full-Disclosure mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>FreeBSD</em>: FreeBSD security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>GENTOO</em>: Gentoo Linux security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>HERT</em>: HERT security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>HP</em>: HP security advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>IBM</em>: IBM ERS/BRS advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>IMMUNIX</em>: Immunix Linux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>INFOWAR</em>: INFOWAR security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>ISS</em>: ISS Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>KSRT</em>: KSR[T] Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>L0PHT</em>: L0pht Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>MANDRAKE</em>: Linux-Mandrake advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>MISC</em>: generic reference from an URL </li>
                <li>
                    <em>MLIST</em>: generic reference form for miscellaneous
                    mailing lists</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NAI</em>: NAI Labs security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NETECT</em>: Netect security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>NetBSD</em>: NetBSD Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>OPENBSD</em>: OpenBSD Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>REDHAT</em>: Security advisories</li>
                <li>
                    <em>RSI</em>: Repent Security, Inc. security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SEKURE</em>: Sekure security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SF-INCIDENTS</em>: posting to Security Focus Incidents
                    mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SGI</em>: SGI Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SLACKWARE</em>: Slackware security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SNI</em>: Secure Networks, Inc. security advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUN</em>: Sun security bulletin</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUNALERT</em>: Sun security alert</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUNBUG</em>: Sun bug ID</li>
                <li>
                    <em>SUSE</em>: SuSE Linux: Security Announcements</li>
                <li>
                    <em>TRUSTIX</em>: Trustix Security Advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>TURBO</em>: TurboLinux advisory</li>
                <li>
                    <em>VULN-DEV</em>: Posting to VULN-DEV mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>VULNWATCH</em>: VulnWatch mailing list</li>
                <li>
                    <em>XF</em>: X-Force Vulnerability Database</li>
                <li>
                    <em>CVE</em>: CVE Candidates </li>
            </ol>
            <p>The above keywords are in full compliance with the CVE
                recommended keyword list found <link
                url="http://www.cve.mitre.org/cve/refs/refkey.html">here</link>. </p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="updating">
        <title>Security update procedure.</title>
        <shorttitle>secup</shorttitle>
        <section name="procedure">
            <title>Adding security related updates.</title>
            <p>Security updates may only be applied once they have been verified
                by the original Author of the software which has been packaged
                for Fink and found to be vulnerable to a security issue. Before
                an update one or more of the following conditions <em>have</em>
                to be met:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>The author of the software has contacted the maintainer
                    and/or the <em>Fink Core Team.</em> directly providing a
                    patch or work around to a vulnerability.</li>
                <li>One of the keyword-denoted sources has issued a security
                    bulletin with updated sources for the software packaged for
                    Fink in question.</li>
                <li>A patch has been issued to one of the following
                    keyword-denoted sources: BUGTRAQ,FULLDISC,SF-INCIDENTS,VULN-DEV.</li>
                <li>An official security bulletin has been issued and assigned
                    CVE Candidate status, describing the vulnerability,
                    supplying a work around, patch or link to updated sources.</li>
                <li>Pre-notification has been sent to the maintainer and/or the
                        <em>Fink Core Team</em> directly providing a patch or
                    work around to a vulnerability asking to take action.</li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="moving">
            <title>Unstable to stable moves.</title>
            <p>Security updates for a specific package will first be applied to
                the unstable tree. After a waiting period of no less than
                <em>12</em> hours the packages' info file will be moved into the
                stable tree as well. The retention period shall be used to
                carefully observe whether the updated package works and the
                security update does not introduce any new issues.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    <chapter filename="notification">
        <title>Sending notifications</title>
        <shorttitle>notify</shorttitle>
        <preface>
            <p>Some users might choose not to update their software too
                frequently. To ensure that those who install their packages from
                source are using updated packages which have been reported to
                have security issues as soon as possible, a maintainer may call
                for a notification to be sent to the Fink announcement list.</p>
        </preface>
        <section name="who">
            <title>Who may send them?</title>
            <p>These announcements may only be sent by the <em>Fink Security
                Team</em>. Most announcement will be sent from
                dmalloc@users.sourceforge.net signed by the PGP key with the
                fingerprint:
            </p>
                <ul>
                    <li>
                <tt>FD77 F0B7 5C65 F546 EB08 A4EC 3CCA 1A32 7E24
                291E</tt>.
                </li>
                <li>Found at
                <tt>http://pgp.mit.edu:11371/pks/lookup?op=get&amp;search=0x7E24291E</tt></li></ul>
                <p>
                The above is intentionally not marked as a link.</p>
            <p> Other authorised Team members are: (here you add your email +
                public key like I did above)</p><p>
	        peter@pogma.com signed by the PGP key with the fingerprint:</p>
	        <ul>
	            <li><tt>
		4D67 1997 DD32 AE8E D7ED  9C79 8491 2AB7 DF3B 6004</tt>.</li>
		<li>
		Found at <tt>http://pgp.mit.edu:11371/pks/lookup?op=get&amp;search=0xDF3B6004</tt>
        </li>
            </ul>
        </section>
        <section name="how">
            <title>How to submit </title>
            <p> To ensure that a common look for security notifications is met,
                all security notices <em>must</em> follow the following common
                template. </p>
            <codeblock> ID: FINK-YYYY-MMDD-NN 
                        Reported: YYYY-MM-DD 
                        Updated:  YYYY-MM-DD 
                        Package:  package-name
                        Affected: &lt;= versionid
                        Maintainer: maintainer-name
                        Tree(s): 10.3/stable, 10.3/unstable, 10.2-gcc3.3/stable,10.2-gcc3.3/unstable
                        Mac OS X version: 10.3, 10.2 
                        Fix: patch|upstream 
                        Updated by: maintainer|forced update (Email)
                        Description: A short description describing the issue.
                        References: KEYWORD (see above) Ref-URL: URL </codeblock>
            
            <p>A sample report could look somewhat like this:</p>
            <codeblock> ID: FINK-2004-06-01 
                        Reported:             2004-06-09 
                        Updated:              2004-06-09 
                        Package:              cvs
                        Affected:             &lt;= 1.11.16, &lt;= = 1.12.8
                        Maintainer:           Sylvain Cuaz 
                        Tree(s):    10.3/stable, 10.3/unstable, 10.2-gcc3.3/stable,10.2-gcc3.3/unstable 
                        Mac OS X version: 10.3, 10.2 
                        Fix: upstream
                        Updated by: forced update (dmalloc@users.sourceforge.net)
                        Description: Multiple vulnerabilities in CVS found my ematters
                        Security. References: BID 
                        Ref-URL:    http://www.securityfocus.com/bid/10499 
                        References: CVE 
                        Ref-URL:    http://www.cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CAN-2004-0414
                        References: CVE 
                        Ref-URL:    http://www.cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CAN-2004-0416
                        References: CVE 
                        Ref-URL:    http://www.cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CAN-2004-0417
                        References: CVE 
                        Ref-URL:    http://www.cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CAN-2004-0418
                        References: FULLDISCURL 
                        Ref-URL:    http://lists.netsys.com/pipermail/full-disclosure/2004-June/022441.html
                        References: MISC 
                        Ref-URL:    http://security.e-matters.de/advisories/092004.html </codeblock>
            <p> Please note that the <em>Affected</em> keyword referrs to all vulnerable software versions not
            only those that might be packaged for Fink. The sample report shows this clearly.</p>
        </section>
    </chapter>
</document>
